<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
 <teiHeader>
 <fileDesc>
 <titleStmt>
 <title>Huon d'Auvergne, Kupferstichkabinett 78 D 8 (olim Hamilton 337)
 Annotations</title>
 <respStmt>
 <name xml:id="SPM">Stephen Patrick McCormick</name>
 <resp>Annotations</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt>
 <publisher>Washington and Lee University</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Lexington, Virginia</pubPlace>
 </publicationStmt>
 <sourceDesc>
 <msDesc xml:lang="en">
 <!-- xml:id ??? See Cummings 52 -->
 <!-- add encodingDesc -->
 <msIdentifier>
 <country>Germany</country>
 <settlement>Berlin</settlement>
 <repository>Kupferstichkabinett</repository>
 <idno>78 D 8</idno>
 </msIdentifier>
 </msDesc>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
	 <front>
	 	<divGen type="toc"/>
	 </front>
 	<body>
		 <div>
 <note xml:id="b1" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Holtus ("Considerazioni") published lines 1-109; his edition is a diplomatic one (45-48), with abbreviations reproduced and word divisions as in the manuscript. Tobler published lines 1-111 (pp. 617-19); he reproduces the text without punctuation other than the final periods and the lines that mark caesura here at the beginning of the poem, and without distinguishing u/v.</note>
 <note xml:id="b12" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: une (final -e is expunctuated)</note>
 <note xml:id="b55" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: quilens with a dot under each letter, "il" <hi rend="italic">i</hi>"; emend to <hi rend="italic">queus</hi> </note>
 <note xml:id="b76" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Tobler omits the superscript after ".iiii."; Holtus seems to have a small "m" over the roman numeral. This MS abbreviation appears only with ".iiii." (six times) and would seem to be validated by line 6271, when in a prayer Christ arose after 4 days; and in line 11057, where four men are chosen as electors for the king to replace Charles Martel, and listed immediately thereafter. Furthermore, the "m" in lines 9334 and 11496 has no final upstroke. </note>
 <note xml:id="b109" type="trans" resp="#LZM">End of Holtus's diplomatic transcription.</note>
 <note xml:id="b111" type="trans" resp="#LZM">End of Tobler's edited selection. </note>
 <note xml:id="b136" type="codic" resp="#LZM">All text that is written above the line in the original is enclosed in parentheses in this transcription. </note>
 <note xml:id="b200" type="interp" resp="#LZM">This line is problematic for sense; the Turin version is also unclear. </note>
 <note xml:id="b216" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> MS: neis. We are understanding as "n'es," the pronouns (es= (the) same); cf. Turin line 215, "<hi rend="italic">così è</hi>"</note>
 <note xml:id="b245" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: revser</note>
 <note xml:id="b343" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: nolōs. This is an interesting slip: <hi rend="italic">non</hi> added to a form of <hi rend="italic">voloir</hi>.</note>
 <note xml:id="b405" type="interp" resp="#LZM">For the forms <hi rend="italic">glese, glesse, glesie</hi>, see Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 341). </note>
 <note xml:id="b415" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: ia belist. <hi rend="italic">belist</hi> is a hapax. Elsewhere in the text, we find <hi rend="italic">l'abelist</hi>, e.g., 4169, 6321, etc.</note>
 <note xml:id="b508" type="codic" resp="#LZM">There is a "+" in the right margin in light brown ink, perhas inserted by a nineteenth-century reader.</note>
 <note xml:id="b542" type="lex" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Entrée d'Espagne, gaumenter</hi> (TL <hi rend="italic">gaimenter</hi>), but also 9746 here, <hi rend="italic">gamenta de soit</hi>, 'he complained of thirst,' and note.</note>
 <note xml:id="b669" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS missing an abbreviation mark here in <hi rend="italic">acoplir</hi>; cf. Vv. 1271, 1282, etc.</note>
 <note xml:id="b674" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> The MS is difficult to read: 'r'of <hi rend="italic">complira</hi> is unclear.</note>
 <note xml:id="b751" type="codic" resp="#LZM">p<hi rend="italic">re</hi>gant: the "g" has an unusual form; it looks more like a "y"</note>
 <note xml:id="b790" type="interp" resp="#LZM">MS: empial. Cf. vv. 47, 73, 373, etc., where we see <hi rend="italic">emp[er]ial</hi>. However, see <hi rend="italic">empir</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Prise de Pampelune</hi> (v. 4970) and the many other variants. As one of the most frequent words in epic vocabulary, it is greatly varied in rhyme. Furthermore, in Italian, "empio" means "irreligioso, sacrilego, profanatore" and "spietato, crudele" (Zingarelli) so while there is the hint of emperor, there is also the sense of merciless, sacrilegious ruler.</note>
 <note xml:id="b818" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> MS: abosdivoir. Cf. <hi rend="italic">Entrée d'Espagne: bosdeor</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Guerra d'Attila: bosder, bosdeor, bosdera, bosdie</hi>, etc.</note>
 <note xml:id="b888" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: confortas ɾoe</note>
 <note xml:id="b923" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Tutore</hi>: cf. www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/tuttora_(Enciclopedia-Dantesca)/. Typical of Old Italian, found in Dante, the <hi rend="italic">Fiore</hi>, etc. Consulted Nov. 26, 2016.</note>
 <note xml:id="b948" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: monreç</note>
 <note xml:id="b960" type="ling" resp="#LZM">Note the Italianate construction of definite article + possessive.</note>
 <note xml:id="b977" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">haïr</hi>: this could be <hi rend="italic">haïr</hi>, anger, but we are interpreting it as "air" to go with the Turin reading and also the sense here: out the window and into the air, the sky.</note>
 <note xml:id="b1062" type="trans" resp="#LZM">This laisse is included in Tobler, p. 615. He does not always resolve abbreviations as here, always using "n" for the titulus indicating a nasal. There are no substantial differences in transcription. </note>
 <note xml:id="b1149" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">la</hi> is almost unreadable in the manuscript. It is unclear whether this was intentional or not on the part of the scribe or was done later; it seems to be something painted over those letters, but similar to a spot on the left side of the page of a chocolate or cafeaulait color.</note>
 <note xml:id="b1152" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Catchword at the bottom of the page, almost entirely washed out:<hi rend="italic">si</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b1159" type="ling" resp="#LZM">There are three other forms (<hi rend="italic">aflicions</hi> twice, <hi rend="italic">aflicion</hi> once), all in rhyme position. Therefore I here presume <hi rend="italic">aflicion</hi> as the base form, here elided with the preposition <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</note>
 <note xml:id="b1180" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Transcribed by Tobler, lines 1180-1220 (pp. 615-16). We note any substantial differences here. As noted above, his resolution of abbreviations differs; thus, "Par moy" for line 1218, etc. </note>
 <note xml:id="b1250" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Between lines 1249 and 1250 in column 9Va, running into the right margin is a line with an "x"; also at the bottom of column 9va, there is a line with a corresponding "x" in the left margin. Since the column is one line too long in comparison to the other, and normally the columns are equal, this final line (1264) is clearly to be moved to the position between 1249 and 1250.</note>
 <note xml:id="b1295" type="trans" resp="#LZM">This laisse is also transcribed by Tobler (pp. 616-17); again we note any substantial differences of transcription. </note>
 <note xml:id="b1300" type="inter" resp="#LZM">This line is problematic; we are interpreting as a separated future (<hi rend="italic">ti ho dire = ti dirò</hi>). T has difficulties with it as well, with a substantial difference in reading: line 1287 <hi rend="italic">Se zò mantene ch[e]</hi> tu ai dito i[n] to s[er]mone, ("If you continue that which you have said in your speech"); cf. <hi rend="italic">diroy</hi> (vv. 1246, 1944, 2422, 2448), in rhyme position. </note>
 <note xml:id="b1329" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Tobler: uoire / non poit. The MS reads "voie"</note>
 <note xml:id="b1361" type="interp" resp="#JVC"><hi rend="italic">"Sir</hi> désigne la ville de Tyr, puisque les tissus d'Orient étaient réputés et [...] l'on indique volentiers une ville d'Orient comme lieu d'où provient un tissu précieux" ("Sir" refers to the city Tyre, since oriental fabrics were famous and a famous city of the East is frequently used as a source for a valuable fabric (Vallecalle, trans. LZM)).</note>
 <note xml:id="b1399" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> MS: ma[n]da na, however it seems most likely to be an error for "via[n]da na"; cf. line 6181 <hi rend="italic">viande n'a</hi>.</note>
 <note xml:id="b1451" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: q eloiaute; an <hi rend="italic">n</hi>seems to be elided, which would have read: <hi rend="italic">Q'en loiauté</hi>.</note>
 <note xml:id="b1559" type="inter" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">chareme</hi>: interpreted as "carême," fasting.</note>
 <note xml:id="b1643" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The rhyme here is normally a diphthongue but the simple past of <hi rend="italic">oïr</hi> is bisyllabic, so the editor must choose between the rhyme spellings or the usual representation of the simple past of this verb. See also 8160, 11274.</note>
 <note xml:id="b1667" type="ling" resp="#LZM"> In the rhyme position, the verb "savoir" takes this unusual form.</note>
 <note xml:id="b1698" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> MS: riponse; cf. forms of <hi rend="italic"> reponser </hi>(v. 2505, 2690, etc.).</note>
 <note xml:id="b1707" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: constatinople</note>
 <note xml:id="b1711" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: afie đs (crossed 'd' and long 's' above the line between 'a' and 'f').</note>
 <note xml:id="b1748" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">trainé</hi> here is the infinitive, missing the final <hi rend="italic"> -r</hi> ; this is how T understood the line. Alternatively it could be <hi rend="italic">v'oit trainé</hi>, "the kings had there dragged before them"</note>
 <note xml:id="b1749" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: S maint de lor soit bien o voir gravois? The MS is damaged at this point and extremely difficult to read. T: <hi rend="italic">morty zasere al sabione</hi> [dead men lying on the sand]. If the reading here were similar, it might be <hi rend="italic">hon veit sor ce gravois</hi>; but the two are not always parallel. <hi rend="italic">Gravoy</hi> appears appears five times, <hi rend="italic">gravois</hi> once, meaning "sand" or "gravel" in some way (path, etc.) in this MS.</note>
 <note xml:id="b1753" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The beginning of this column is faded in parts, though the outlines of strokes are clear. For multiple minims, there can always be doubts, but in searching other F-I texts there are no forms of <hi rend="italic">sui-</hi> for the verb "to follow," whereas there are 68 forms of <hi rend="italic">siv- </hi> attested in FIOLA. RIALFrI however, offers both. In this text there are 3 other forms with <hi rend="italic">siv-</hi>, one <hi rend="italic">seut</hi>, but none with <hi rend="italic"> sui-</hi> unless the minims are reconstrued in those appearances as well, thus <hi rend="italic">siveç</hi> here, though the connectors are in fact <hi rend="italic">suiveç.</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b1789" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">guioner</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 346), "guide." </note>
 <note xml:id="b1807" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">esclaris</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 307), re <hi rend="italic">esclarir</hi> and the change of conjugation in Franco-Italian. </note>
 <note xml:id="b1830" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: giat</note>
 <note xml:id="b1881" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: nos</note>
 <note xml:id="b1910" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">enci:</hi> cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic"> Lexicalische</hi> p. 290), "ici," 'here.' </note>
 <note xml:id="b1914" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The word <hi rend="italic">et</hi> seems out of place here; emend to <hi rend="italic">e</hi>? Cf. T line 1911, <hi rend="italic">Homo sonto de Carlo Martelo ... </hi> </note>
 <note xml:id="b2115" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Between <hi rend="italic"> les</hi> and <hi rend="italic">afi</hi> at the end of the line is a hole in the MS; afi seems to be written deliberately after it; there does not seem to be any letter missing. J.-C. Vallecalle suggests that it might have been an <hi rend="italic">a</hi> there [possibly scraped off?], making the line read <hi rend="italic">Posible çonse il fust, bien le sai a fi,</hi> that is, "This [Huon's mission in Hell] would be possible, I know certainly (... if Hell were built on earth)."</note>
 <note xml:id="b2130" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">gieter </hi> may have been the original reading of the text, for "how to shoot a bow".</note>
 <note xml:id="b2145" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS seems to be missing the abbreviation for <hi rend="italic">n:</hi><hi rend="italic">m'acontent</hi>; cf. V. 747 </note> 
 <note xml:id="b2152" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> T 2126: <hi rend="italic">Se p[er] devin miraclo non m'avene</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b2154" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> These 6 lines are very difficult to read due to the ink being worn off. Ultraviolet does not help much.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2159" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">aquitier</hi>: there are 16 forms beginning with <hi rend="italic">aquit-</hi> (and one other following <hi rend="italic">d'</hi>) compared to 9 that are clearly quit-, so we have divided those following <hi rend="italic">d</hi> as beginning with the vowel.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2175" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: resont with a caret below to insert a tiny <hi rend="italic">p</hi> written above the line.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2182" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: le nay ster</note>
 <note xml:id="b2186" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">n</hi> and <hi rend="italic">u</hi> are frequently very similar in the MS. <hi rend="italic">Ansi</hi> is perhaps also possible or intended.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2195" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: Bout</note>
 <note xml:id="b2197" type="lex" resp="#LZM">For the construction <hi rend="italic">in genoillon</hi>, see Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi> pp. 338-39).</note>
 <note xml:id="b2208" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">galon</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi> p. 334), "côté," 'side.' </note>
 <note xml:id="b2244" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">âbandon</hi>="a abandon"</note>
 <note xml:id="b2384" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Veriteç </hi>appears twice (5504, 11099) and <hi rend="italic">veritere</hi> once (6308) to one <hi rend="italic">verté</hi> (8736), so we resolve here as we do. </note>
 <note xml:id="b2412" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">aveit a bone foy</hi>seems to be a MS error with either an extra<hi rend="italic">a</hi>(he had good faith or he went in good faith) or perhaps a <hi rend="italic">u</hi> for an <hi rend="italic">n</hi> (<hi rend="italic">aneit </hi> as some form of "andare"), though there is no such form listed in RIALFrI for other Franco-Italian texts. </note>
 <note xml:id="b2433" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">noç</hi>: Final letter is hard to distinguish; could be <hi rend="italic">os</hi>. </note>
 <note xml:id="b2440" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The phrase <hi rend="italic">sans poy</hi> appears to be equivalent to "sans plus"; could it be an Italianism, with palatalization of the consonant + <hi rend="italic">l</hi> (cf. Modern Italian "più")?</note>
 <note xml:id="b2446" type="interp" resp="#LZM">We believe that<hi rend="italic">savra</hi> is like the use of Modern Standard Italian "sapere," "to taste": it seems (it tastes) like...</note>
 <note xml:id="b2500" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> Compare T, line 2484: <hi rend="italic">grande e derupossa p[er]ché ponto son li agradise</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b2519" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Brown ink through the<hi rend="italic">or</hi> of <hi rend="italic">d[e]morr[re]</hi>. <hi rend="italic">mal</hi> has a line above it; it is not the standard abbreviation for <hi rend="italic">r </hi> or vowel + <hi rend="italic">r</hi>, and there are no other abbreviations with <hi rend="italic">l,</hi> so its resolution is not immediately evident.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2545" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: sta[n]cht</note>
 <note xml:id="b2566" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Compare T, line 2542: Quando e∙l vede avrire la gola ch'el ve<hi rend="italic">de el fogo apredre</hi>; B seems to be understanding <hi rend="italic">vait</hi> for both verbs, <hi rend="italic">baër</hi> and <hi rend="italic">esprenda[n]t</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b2602" type="interp" resp="#LZM">T has understood this differently, line 2584: "I praise [him] willingly (with good heart)." This could also be the meaning here, in which case the preceding line would end with a comma instead of a semicolon.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2614" type="codic" resp="#LZM">M: lö tēptz. This seems to be an unusual case of assonance alone, not rhyme.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2622" type="codic" resp="#LZM">After <hi rend="italic">tost</hi>, scratched out letter in the MS.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2681" type="codic" resp="#LZM">There is a letter scratched out after <hi rend="italic">il</hi> before <hi rend="italic">atant</hi>. This folio in general has many corrections.</note>
   <note xml:id="b2684" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">si stoit</hi>: they had to, they needed to; cf. T 2665, <hi rend="italic">Quando lo zorno</hi> li mancha se ly coven<hi rend="italic">ta</hi> albergare</note>
   <note xml:id="b2687" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">li jorner</hi>: This expression can mean "journey" or "day" in Old French. In Italian, it might have that meaning (DELI, 13th century), but "day" is the first and more frequent meaning. It is difficult to say which is intended here.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2689" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">ge</hi> inserted above the line.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2745" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel's review of Brockstedt includes this laisse. He uses square brackets for additions, parentheses for things he believes should be omitted. Included here are lines where he does either. Not noted are differences in uses of written accents. </note>
 <note xml:id="b2747" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel (Review): ce q(e)'armés </note>
 <note xml:id="b2755" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel (Review): [e]n est </note>
 <note xml:id="b2757" type="ling" resp="#LZM">Note the use of <hi rend="italic">n</hi> here for "nous" (<hi rend="italic">ne</hi> before vowel) object form. This is typical of early Italian texts. See Rohlfs, <title rend="italic">Morfologia</title>, paragraph 460. This is a legal formula meaning in the presence of witnesses.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2764" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel (Review): Qu(e)'aveque</note>
 <note xml:id="b2777" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel (Review): E [va]</note>
 <note xml:id="b2778" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel (Review): (por)forma </note>
 <note xml:id="b2789" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: Lort; the final letter seems to be an anticipation of the following word's final letter. T: Alora se ne vene al maro [...] </note>
 <note xml:id="b2796" type="trans" resp="#LZM">End of the selection transcribed in Stengel's review.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2818" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: ci ņait. Though the <hi rend="italic">n </hi>is expunctuated, it seems to be necessary for the meaning; see translation. </note>
 <note xml:id="b2821" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: vos vos pri ne mie: second <hi rend="italic">vos</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ne</hi> are expunctuated. </note>
 <note xml:id="b2880" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: pelle. <hi rend="italic">p</hi> with a line above is always <hi rend="italic">p[re]</hi> and thus is so transcribed here.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2909" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Abbreviation line very light in the MS.</note>
 <note xml:id="b2911" type="interp" resp="#LZM">MS: vait.seems to be a form of "valoir"</note>
 <note xml:id="b3046" type="lex" resp="#LZM">MS: alieç: CF T-L 278-279 <hi rend="italic">alegier</hi>, "to be eased, lightened"; <title rend="Italic">Folco di Candia</title>> V19, l. 1581.</note>
 <note xml:id="b3065" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Thse laisse initial here has a face sketched into it.</note>
 <note xml:id="b3075" type="interp" resp="#LZM">We interpret <hi rend="italic">aseori</hi> as from *<hi rend="italic">asseoir</hi>, "to rest, stop on a trip."</note>
 <note xml:id="b3158" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">quoy=coi</hi>="tranquille," T-L "still"; <hi rend="italic">s'ora </hi> derives from <hi rend="italic">orer </hi> "anwünschen"="wish"</note>
 <note xml:id="b3163" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">dela</hi> : "over there," not "by there," so one word. There are many appearances of this construction in rhyme position.</note>
 <note xml:id="b3171" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: mont le sen: <hi rend="italic">le</hi> expunctuated</note> 
 <note xml:id="b3193" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">segure</hi>: DELI <hi rend="italic">scure, segure</hi> before 1292, derives from SECŪRE(M), Latin</note>
 <note xml:id="b3200" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Funny face drawn into the capital for this laisse, as for many in this section of the MS.</note>
 <note xml:id="b3228" type="interp" resp="#LZM">This version differs from Turin where it is the serpent that cries out. </note>
 <note xml:id="b3262" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> Or <hi rend="italic">va pur a giter</hi>. This is one case where the French and Italian constructions differ but the meaning is approximately the same: "by rolling he was going to move it" and "by rolling he was going to toss it."</note>
 <note xml:id="b3286" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> For this section, cf. <hi rend="italic">Le roman d'Alexandre</hi>, Branche III, laisses 160-162, part of the "Dangerous Valley" where Alexander confronts a demon in order to leave. (Harf-Lancner trans. of E. C. Armstrong, pp. 470-477).</note>
 <note xml:id="b3354" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> Here Huon addresses the figure aloud.</note>
 <note xml:id="b3361" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> The MS seems to be missing the abbreviation for an "r" here: <hi rend="italic">archiere</hi>, "archer," as in vv. 1710, 9216, 11662, 1204 <hi rend="italic">archiers</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b3398" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> This might be a reference to Dante's hell: those inside the walls of Hell (Canto 10) cannot see the present and see the future only dimly (10.94-105). </note>
 <note xml:id="b3503" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: oi ge, with <hi rend="italic">ge</hi> expunctuated, the <hi rend="italic">g</hi> with a dot above, the <hi rend="italic">e</hi> with dot both above and below. </note>
 <note xml:id="b3522" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: lemme</note>
 <note xml:id="b3678" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Emendation for MS <hi rend="italic">nōs avōs</hi>; note the use of the first person plural as subject.</note>
 <note xml:id="b3686" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: geste beste</note>
 <note xml:id="b3750" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Cf. Turin, line 3704: <hi rend="italic">quando y[n] m</hi>ia vita tanto ben fato averò</note>
 <note xml:id="b3763" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">si seiron</hi> could also read <hi rend="italic">s'iseiron</hi>, "they went out"; there are no similar forms for "to sit," and Turin has them sitting down, "putting" themselves at the table.</note>
 <note xml:id="b3838" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">alor</hi> could also read <hi rend="italic">a lor</hi>, "to them." Cf. T 3801 <hi rend="italic">a le soue done</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b3907" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: vons</note>
 <note xml:id="b3952" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: el (inserted above the line)</note> 
 <note xml:id="b4119" type="interp" resp="#LZM">T, line 4079: <hi rend="italic">De zorno</hi> y[n] zorno quanty y[n] naserano (line 4079); it would seem that the Italian writer did not understand the text.</note>
 <note xml:id="b4148" type="interp" resp="#LZM">MS: fable pece home</note>
 <note xml:id="b4204" type="biblio" resp="#LZM">This is Psalm 133, verses 1-2; Dante also quotes it in his <title rend="Italic">Monarchia,</title> Book 1.</note>
 <note xml:id="b4254" type="refer" resp="#LZM">The following line (4212) in T reads, "con più marinary chi mena<hi rend="Italic">una grosa nava</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b4290" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">te[re]rre</hi>: This is unusual, perhaps the adding of an unnecessary abbreviation mark when the full word is already present.</note>
 <note xml:id="b4360" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Cf. Matthew 7.14, "For the gate is narrow and the way is hard, that leads to life, and those who find it are few." Vulgate: "<q xml:lang="la">Quam angusta porta, et arcta via est, que ducit ad vitam: et pauci sunt qui inveniunt eam!</q>" If we were to transcribe Stroite ert la voie qui no l'atient a tant it would reflect an Italianate structure with <hi rend="italic">a tanti: "Stretta è la via che non l'ottiene a tanti</hi>" or "<hi rend="italic">non la tiene a tanti</hi>"– "that not many can hold to it' "or "that not many can succeed at it"</note>
 <note xml:id="b4407" type="refer" resp="#LZM">This is a complicated passage, with non-standard forms: <hi rend="Italic">aroman </hi> in particular poses a riddle. </note>
 <note xml:id="b4418" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio") includes from here these laisses 164-174, line 4664. She uses a capital letter only for new sentences, not at the beginning of each line, and does not note resolution of abbreviations. Any substantial difference in transcription (i.e., not capitals, her resolutions or her standard word division) will be noted. She does not use quotation marks here, so direct conversation is not evident, though she does later in the passage transcribed. </note>
 <note xml:id="b4424" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): ata[c]ha</note>
 <note xml:id="b4440" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): comenciet le jor</note>
 <note xml:id="b4466" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): qui l'ont</note>
 <note xml:id="b4469" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): oille istrent</note>
 <note xml:id="b4482" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): le menton</note>
 <note xml:id="b4503" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The first hemistich of this line seems to be a repeat of 4501 above; in Turin, however, the two also repeat. so it is clearly part of the tradition.</note>
 <note xml:id="b4509" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">charene</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 251), "<hi rend="italic">cherene</hi>: affection"; he cites also <hi rend="italic">Gui de Nanteuil</hi> "carine," so we see to have a combination of the two here (cf. also Matsumura, "cherine," citing <hi rend="italic">Entrée d'Espagne</hi>). But the word also appears in line 1560; between the two, it seems here to mean "penitence," and in fact, Turin reads "<hi rend="italic">gran qu</hi>aresema fay, ancha no[n] vite la simele" (line 4461), with "Lent" as the original derivation. </note>
 <note xml:id="b4513" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">flagelle</hi>: Cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 326), "flageller, fouetter," 'to whip.' </note>
 <note xml:id="b4515" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): dapne elle</note>
 <note xml:id="b4517" type="inter" resp="#LZM">It is unclear whether this line belongs to Huon or to Prester John. Meregazzi interprets it as being Prester John who says it; we include it as part of Huon's response. </note>
 <note xml:id="b4538" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Istrent, istront</hi> appear a number of times in this text; <hi rend="italic">aman</hi> this once, but also in <title rend="Italic">Attila</title>, where it is defined as "subito" IX, 254. T clearly did not understand: <hi rend="italic">li stre[n]ze la man</hi>, "he shook his hand."</note>
 <note xml:id="b4555" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): por ice</note>
 <note xml:id="b4570" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): un quartier de pem</note>
 <note xml:id="b4573" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): ostalaisent; there does not seem to be any record of a similar verb, more likely ostà (past participle of "oster" or "ost[el]er") + a form of the verb laisser = well-lodged. Cf. Turin line 4524. </note>
 <note xml:id="b4589" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): n'a nil de voir</note>
 <note xml:id="b4596" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS : adonet; the <hi rend="italic">e</hi> cross-stroke is very light but present. Since the scribe is in general very careful expunctuating errors and otherwise correcting, this seems to be a true error and we here emend. Meregazzi: adonct</note>
 <note xml:id="b4597" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): feroi ge. Her word division does not alter the meaning, the verb remains present conditional, first person; the ending is frequently -<hi rend="italic">oige</hi> for that form (see Mainone, <title rend="italic">Formen</title>, pp. 15-17; <title rend="italic">Laut</title>, p. 49).</note>
 <note xml:id="b4616" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): mille visque, mant en la sor. However there are no forms "visque" in the MS, and frequently "jusque" (with its abbreviations) has a similar form.</note>
 <note xml:id="b4640" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): qu'il vit</note>
 <note xml:id="b4651" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): pam bescuit; she also notes, "corr. <hi rend="italic">anone</hi> in <hi rend="italic">avoine</hi>"</note> 
 <note xml:id="b4652" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">asié</hi> comes from <hi rend="italic">aasier </hi>(TL), "to reassure."</note>
 <note xml:id="b4662" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio"): qu'il en gardast</note>
 <note xml:id="b4664" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("L'Episodio") stops here to pick up again later.</note>
 <note xml:id="b4665" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Tobler transcribes lines 4665-4672 (p. 619).</note>
 <note xml:id="b4669" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel includes this section in his "Eine weitere Textstelle," numbering it 4669-5008.</note>
 <note xml:id="b4692" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The end of the line could also be interpreted <hi rend="italic">fai ces demostreison</hi>, but since Turin reads "fazy demostranza" we construe it this way. There are no other forms faicés; <hi rend="italic">faige</hi> and <hi rend="italic">faigés</hi> are related to "fatigué," but there are three <hi rend="italic">faice</hi> tokens from "to do/to make."</note>
 <note xml:id="b4698" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Eine weitere"): dau [sien] consoil</note>
 <note xml:id="b4703" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Catchword after this line: A Ynide </note>
 <note xml:id="b4704" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The previous line, at the end of folio 32V, ends with the catchwords <hi rend="Italic">A Ynide</hi> which do not then begin the next folio or signature. There is a space in the MS after <hi rend="Italic">arcives</hi> that seems to be scraped; something is visible around the edges. With ultraviolet, one can almost see "q" and "e", and maybe something above the line too, qe with u above the line? Or just a bit of chalk solution or whatever they used.Thus we give this as an emendation. Stengel ("Eine weitere," p. 39): L'Arcives[ch] </note>
 <note xml:id="b4739" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: plais</note>
 <note xml:id="b4745" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The reading <hi rend="Italic">Tholomé</hi> here is problematic, since Tholomeus has not been designated head of the band of ambassadors or otherwise much discussed until now. MS T, line 4745, reads "Servire debe esere tal sire [et] de grande [et] <hi rend="italic">de menore</hi>"; perhaps the original here was "tal ome" (such a man), referring to the king, perhaps referring to the king. There are two possible avenues for distraction, the first written, and the second oral. In the first column of this folio, in line four (this is line 3 of column two) in line 4707, "Tholomeu" appears, so could have distracted a copyist. If the scribe were writing under dictation, he might have thought he heard"tol ome" instead of "tel ome," and would have added the "h" after the "t" because he had just encountered the name earlier [with thanks to colleagues for confirmation].</note>
 <note xml:id="b4766" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Eine weitere," p. 41): fil econtre</note>
 <note xml:id="b4787" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The end of this line and the next are missing in the MS.</note>
 <note xml:id="b4799" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: selong</note>
 <note xml:id="b4835" type="lex" resp="#LZM">MS: peçe=OF "pieça"; Stengel ("Eine weitere"): Lle</note>
 <note xml:id="b4866" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS indeed reads <hi rend="italic">bein</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b4871" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Langlois lists Teris as Lord of Vermandois (p. 668).</note>
 <note xml:id="b4920" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This line is incomplete in the MS. These laisses are not in B, so there can be no reconstruction from that text.</note>
 <note xml:id="b4928" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: un êve since <hi rend="italic">êve</hi> is always feminine in this text="une eve"</note>
 <note xml:id="b4934" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: pote[r] for 'porter,' the gate-keeper.</note>
 <note xml:id="b4940" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Something is clearly missing in this line, perhaps <hi rend="italic">de [servir] vos</hi>? Cf. T, line 4782, "<hi rend="italic">de complir</hi>e la vostra volontady"</note>
 <note xml:id="b4978" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This line is incomplete in the MS. In MS T, v. 4820 reads "Ay, cristianità, como ay tuo onore p[er]duto!" There is a letter after <hi rend="italic">m</hi> that was removed, it looks like another <hi rend="italic">m</hi>; the rest of the letters are bled through from the back. </note>
 <note xml:id="b5008" type="trans" resp="#LZM">End of Stengel's "Eine weitere" transcription.</note>
 <note xml:id="b5012" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This line is incomplete in the MS. In MS T, v. 4851 reads "<hi rend="italic">Dona," diz</hi>e Berardo, "che loro lasate-ly y[n]trare". There is clearly a difficulty with this line, though the general idea is clear: "Lady," said Berardo,"may you allow them to enter."</note>
 <note xml:id="b5034" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: jambaseors</note>
 <note xml:id="b5053" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: colleste</note>
 <note xml:id="b5083" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Unusual abbreviation form: <hi rend="italic">empeos</hi> with a sign over <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi rend="italic">o-</hi>; perhaps a two-part sign? </note>
 <note xml:id="b5112" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: serees; the second <hi rend="italic">e</hi> has a tiny dot below and a bigger one above; not clear though if it should be expunctuated. We have done so here. </note>
 <note xml:id="b5132" type="interp" resp="#LZM">MS T, line 4955 reads: "<hi rend="italic">vuy avite p[er] vuy tram</hi>iso, [et] zò e my y[n]seme siemo." <hi rend="italic">ensoine</hi> : cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, pp. 300-301), "scusa," 'excuse.'</note>
 <note xml:id="b5150" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">cu[m]</hi>: the final "n" here is the "vertical m" found in Latin texts. Cf. CPLEDTM, Fasc. 1, p. 28.</note>
 <note xml:id="b5172" type="interp" resp="#LZM">We understand <hi rend="italic">strine</hi> related to the verb "stringere."</note>
 <note xml:id="b5192" type="ling" resp="#LZM">For the construction with <hi rend="italic">irer</hi>, see Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, pp. 352-53). </note>
 <note xml:id="b5233" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: ētase</note>
 <note xml:id="b5363" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: avon. MS T, lines 5179-80 read: "che avante m'averoy lo coro fenduto / e l'anyma de my del tuto avere p[er]duta" [...for I would first have my heart split, and my soul completely lost (i.e., be dead) before I would...]</note>
 <note xml:id="b5379" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">fortese</hi>: Cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 329), "force." </note>
 <note xml:id="b5399" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS T, line 5212: "<hi rend="italic">chi non fosse y[n] vergogna de l'apele</hi>" [who is not ashamed to call him]</note>
 <note xml:id="b5430" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">trasumans</hi>: cf. Dante <hi rend="italic">Par</hi>. 1, 70. This must be one of its earliest usages after Dante (DELI: before 1321, Dante, first use). The final word, <hi rend="italic">desuor</hi>, is problematic; we render as "u" the two downstrokes that are linked both above and below. There is no equivalent in other MSS; the meaning seems to be that he had passed beyond and is now no longer present. </note>
 <note xml:id="b5447" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: baroine. The second and third strokes are clearly linked at the top and the first and second at the bottom.</note>
 <note xml:id="b5460" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: sa aubçēt ("b" also has a titulus over it). We emend here in part because of syllable count and in part because of sense: "sa aubercent" does not make sense: it is either two verbs together or a singular possessive pronoun plus plural verb.</note>
 <note xml:id="b5478" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">reïre</hi>: from the prefix RE- + ire</note>
 <note xml:id="b5479" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Should this be "Canace" from Ovid's <hi rend="italic">Heroides</hi> 11, where she committed incest with Macareus, her brother, and her father Aeolus sent her a sword to kill herself (and exposed the baby)? In 1542 it was made into a play by Sperone Speroni, so was clearly known in Italy in the sixteenth century. For the English translation, see http://www.poetryintranslation.com/PITBR/Latin/Heroides8-15.php#anchor_Toc524696648.</note> 
 <note xml:id="b5482" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS appears to read <hi rend="italic">niiēs</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b5532" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The forms here are unlike others we have seen in this text; and these lines are omitted from the T MS. We have interpreted <hi rend="italic">sorer</hi> as "suer" and <hi rend="italic">scaulir</hi> as "echauffer" through an Italianate "caldo" since Ital "scaldare"=to burn, though one might expect opposite expressions. The T text (in a different order) does mention the 'fire of love,' v. 5346, "Lo feu d'amore sovente li fate sentire." Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, pp. 454-55), relates it to "essorer," with varying meanings according to the text; 'to relax, cool off.'</note>
 <note xml:id="b5555" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: pālam</note>
 <note xml:id="b5564" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: dolonor</note>
 <note xml:id="b5568" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: empëo, where the descender of the <hi rend="italic">p</hi> is also crossed</note>
 <note xml:id="b5670" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: susnel </note>
 <note xml:id="b5725" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">gaberisse</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 333), "raillerie," 'mockery, scoffing.'</note>
 <note xml:id="b5754" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The identity of "Sulliendre" is unclear; there is no record of the name in that form in Classical or medieval literature. The references are missing from the T MS.</note>
 <note xml:id="b5756" type="refer" resp="#LZM">For Porus, see the <hi rend="italic">Roman d'Alexandre</hi>, Branche 3, laisses 30-240.
 <note xml:id="b5758" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The meaning and derivation of <hi rend="italic">desgrendre</hi> are unclear. Perhaps "sgrenre"? For the form, cf. <hi rend="italic">genero=gendre; tenero=tendre</hi> etc.'to seed a fruit/remove bits from cob; recite the rosary; eat with glee'</note>
 <note xml:id="b5812" type="interp" resp="#JCV"><hi rend="italic">Disticha catonis</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Catonis distichorum</hi> 30: Quae culpare soles, ea tu ne feceris ipse, Turpe est doctori, cum culpa redarguit ipsum. [Those things you are accustomed to blame do not do yourself; It is bad for a wise man when his own guilt comes back (to haunt him)]. Text and translation, Jim Marchand, http://faculty.georgetown.edu/jod/texts/distich.trans.html.</note>
 <note xml:id="b5846" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: mebruç</note>
 <note xml:id="b5857" type="lex" resp="#LZM">For the form <hi rend="italic">se lagne</hi>, see Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 358).</note>
 <note xml:id="b5926" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">esmatés</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 311), "terrasser, détruire," 'to crush, destroy.'</note>
 <note xml:id="b5964" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: dorit</note>
 <note xml:id="b5968" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">baster</hi>:=Italian "bastare" [to be enough, to suffice]; attested 1253, DELI (unknown origin; no attestation in OF, TL)</note> 
 <note xml:id="b5979" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">avist</hi>: there are three tokens with this sequence of letters: 5601 and 7579 in addition to this line. In each case it is a form of the verb "to have," interpreted also by Mainone as <hi rend="italic">avist</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Formenlehre</hi> 24), similar to the forms in <hi rend="italic">Entrée d'Espagne, Attila, V4</hi>, etc. As Veillard and Guyotjeannin's <hi rend="italic">Conseils</hi> suggest, the alternation between "u" and "v" (<hi rend="italic">avit</hi> and <hi rend="italic">avait</hi> appear, as do <hi rend="italic">aüst </hi> and <hi rend="italic">aüstes, aüsés</hi>) suggests an interpretation with "v" (<hi rend="italic">Fasc.</hi> I, 25). </note>
 <note xml:id="b5995" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: maçerie: the letter <hi rend="italic">l</hi> seems to have been corrected in <hi rend="italic">r</hi> (for "Margery").</note>
 <note xml:id="b6015" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: nuit demi .pl'. with a caret between <hi rend="italic">nuit</hi> and <hi rend="italic">demi </hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b6028" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Tobler transcribes from here through line 6139 (pp. 607-609).</note>
 <note xml:id="b6067" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Blank folio, Recto and Verso, follows.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6068" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi, "Prete Gianni" picks up her transcription here, her lines 6223-6552, here 6068-6397.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6110" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 32): n'en cuit</note>
 <note xml:id="b6112" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> Tobler: de grant pri . [sic]. The print seems to be missing a letter at the end.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6117" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: mai/s; an "s" seems to be written over an "i"; Tobler: mas; Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 34): m'as</note>
 <note xml:id="b6126" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 34): Si non</note>
 <note xml:id="b6132" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">avenois</hi>: see Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi> p. 224). </note>
 <note xml:id="b6139" type="trans" resp="#LZM">End of Tobler transcribed section.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6158" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 36): fors qui l'en dure</note>
 <note xml:id="b6178" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 38) includes only the final line as a quote. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6194" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">plus mes</hi>: "plus mieux"</note>
 <note xml:id="b6200" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: <hi rend="italic">son son signor</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b6221" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 40): Lors que</note>
 <note xml:id="b6226" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 40): qi conquis</note>
 <note xml:id="b6240" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 42): gardera li mon grant</note>
 <note xml:id="b6288" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 46): la proiere</note>
 <note xml:id="b6294" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 46): benig[n]e chiere</note>
 <note xml:id="b6296" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Line incomplete; T 5987 "charegò-le per vero lo francho conte"</note>
 <note xml:id="b6297" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: over <hi rend="italic">it plu</hi> there is an ink smear.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6304" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">ala Âgollant</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Ala a Agollant</hi>; reference to <hi rend="italic">Aspremont</hi>; Meregazzi: il ala a Gollant</note>
 <note xml:id="b6305" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 46): Hei Diex</note>
 <note xml:id="b6337" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 50): le pieç</note>
 <note xml:id="b6349" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">golir</hi>: an Italian-based form; cf. <hi rend="italic">Guerra d'Attila, goloient</hi>; TLIO <hi rend="italic">goliare</hi>, "desiderare"</note>
 <note xml:id="b6350" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: (t) is inserted above line with a caret under the line before the <hi rend="italic">s</hi> is underpunctuated at end of the word.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6359" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 50): aré tinir. There are no forms "aré" or "tinir" in this text; "tenir" appears 25 times (5 with [n]). "retenir" in various conjugated forms appears numerous times, including "retint." Turin line 6050 read "retenire" in line-final position. The "a-" prefix is frequent in Franco-Italian, as noted above. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6362" type="codic" resp="#LZM">In the manuscript, the final stroke of the <hi rend="italic">–r</hi> is missing, perhaps worn away. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6366" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni," p. 52): acrement</note>
 <note xml:id="b6397" type="trans" resp="#LZM">End of Meregazzi ("Prete Gianni").</note>
 <note xml:id="b6398" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel publishes from here to line 6992. He notes in the introduction that he edits for reading ease: resolving abbreviations, differentiating i/j and u/v and adding punctuation. Any comments related to that edition will be listed by Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe"). Differences in editing style are not noted. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6400" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">mesay</hi>: TL meshaigne=mahaigne=mehaigne, "damage" </note>
 <note xml:id="b6408" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 687): qu'il conseut (with no explanation); MS: cōsent, very clear, but of course confusion between links for minims is quite possible. <hi rend="italic">Quant que</hi>: quando che is a <hi rend="italic">veneto</hi> expression according to Zingarelli 2018, for "quando, proprio quando" </note>
 <note xml:id="b6417" type="inter" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">s'aregone</hi>: Cf. T, line 6108 "s'araduna," to meet; we are interpreting "aregone" as related to <hi rend="italic">aringo</hi> TLIO , "a place for meeting, a meeting" and extrapolate the verb as "to meet"</note>
 <note xml:id="b6425" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 688): (!) At the end of the line</note>
 <note xml:id="b6437" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 689): "Que ferés ...</note>
 <note xml:id="b6473" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">fanos</hi> written as one word in the manuscript, as usual for object pronouns following the imperative.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6475" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">astu</hi> written as one word in the manuscript, as usual for subject following the verb in question.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6484" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 690): Venuç [a] li</note>
 <note xml:id="b6486" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 690): enfer atrover</note>
 <note xml:id="b6495" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 691): luy [g]e</note>
 <note xml:id="b6503" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 691): Conten[t]eç moy</note>
 <note xml:id="b6520" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 692): de ci</note>
 <note xml:id="b6522" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic"> engaigne</hi>: trickery, cunning, wiliness</note> 
 <note xml:id="b6523" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Mestre</hi> could be understood as a feminine plural here, in which case the comparison would be with other female necromancers. The line in general is tricky because the verb seems singular (<hi rend="italic">soit</hi>) but <hi rend="italic">tant</hi> would indicate a plural.</note> 
 <note xml:id="b6531" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 692) : efforç par. Cf. the <hi rend="italic">Roman d'Alexandre</hi>, Branche 3, laisses 207-213, seeking the trees of the Sun and the Moon (ed. Harf-Lancner pp. 528-535). All references to the <hi rend="italic">Alexandre</hi> will be to this edition and the format Branch, laisse(s) or verse(s).</note>
 <note xml:id="b6533" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 692): Et qui distrent</note>
 <note xml:id="b6540" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 692): au roy (!) pooire; <hi rend="italic">Roman d'Alexandre</hi>, Porus I, laisse 217, etc. for Porus.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6549" type="trans" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Alexandre</hi>, l. 3189</note>
 <note xml:id="b6552" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 693): No(n) avons</note>
 <note xml:id="b6554" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 693): qui [tant]ert</note>
 <note xml:id="b6558" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 693): Qu'ici. There are 15 appearances of "ici" versus 140 of "ci" so we have divided differently. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6568" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 693): et la dame en demin (emend) </note>
 <note xml:id="b6571" type="codic" resp="#LZM">We are presuming a missing "a" after "plaise" for a parallel construction with line 6573. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6572" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 694): Que mesremoue art (!)</note>
 <note xml:id="b6578" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 694): a la vetre maison </note>
 <note xml:id="b6586" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">I [n]ombre</hi>: there is clearly an abbreviation line over the <hi rend="italic">i</hi> but it does not seem to make sense here– perhaps the scribe made an error at the beginning of a column. T has no <hi rend="italic">n</hi>. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6607" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 695): Apalpe nos; since the rest of the discourse is in the second person plural, we presume this is too and accent the final syllable. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6611" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 695): sainç [nule] male </note>
 <note xml:id="b6623" type="edit" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Jâ</hi> = Ja a </note>
 <note xml:id="b6628" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Viscardi (Letteratura franco-italiana, pp. 133-34) includes through line 6636.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6633" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">li lusage</hi>: this seems to be a case of "concretion of the article": that is, <hi rend="italic">lusage</hi> is a plural noun for "habits" or "customs." Cf. Rohlfs ¶341, l. 3189, followed by . Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 696), followed by Viscardi: si l'usage; the MS reads clearly "li"</note>
 <note xml:id="b6635" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">sorvage</hi>: TL: sorvenir, hinzukommen, 'to ensue'; Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 696): so(r)vage </note>
 <note xml:id="b6645" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Note the use of verbs of appearing or seeming rather than being.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6649" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 697): est açe; the letters are all written together, not separated. Though OF might suggest pillars, T understood "rooms" (<hi rend="italic">stanzie</hi>, v. 6338). The form also suggests an equivalence with "estage," which might mean residences (cf. T-L: rooms; residences). </note>
 <note xml:id="b6653" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," 697): il [i] vont</note>
 <note xml:id="b6654" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," 697): reguardant</note>
 <note xml:id="b6658" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," 698): le charoill(e)</note>
 <note xml:id="b6668" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Long epic comparison beginning here: victor after a tourney and his arrival. Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 698): ant .II. grant (beginning of line missing); Viscardi (<hi rend="italic">Letteratura franco-italiana</hi>, p. 135), includes the entire laisse based on Stengel. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6670" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 698): gaaign[é]</note>
 <note xml:id="b6674" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Viscardi: puign</note>
 <note xml:id="b6676" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: astu written as one word </note>
 <note xml:id="b6684" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Viscardi: mervoille ot</note>
 <note xml:id="b6687" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Viscardi: soie venu</note>
 <note xml:id="b6688" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe"): Yesu! MS: yhu, with abbreviation line over the "h." Throughout, "Yesu" is Stengel's resolution of this abbreviation.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6696" type="edit" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">E·maintes</hi> = "En maintes"</note>
 <note xml:id="b6699" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">(e)</hi>: written above the line, very light, no caret below (not visible in the microfilm). DELI: <hi rend="italic">vanagloriarsi </hi> "vantarsi, essere pieno di sé," 13th century.</note> 
 <note xml:id="b6707" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: Mes e non: ..: expunctuated 'e' after the first word</note>
 <note xml:id="b6713" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 700): giant [i] vont /note>
 <note xml:id="b6717" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 701): l'estriver. This is the only appearance of the expression in the text, and "le" is written slightly apart from the following word; see introduction on vowel + s + consonant. Cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, pp. 319-20), "étrier," "stirrup."</note>
 <note xml:id="b6729" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 701): Döes</note>
 <note xml:id="b6731" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 701): pas [ni] noise ni cri</note>
 <note xml:id="b6735" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 701): fiuç (de) Davi</note>
 <note xml:id="b6736" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Matthew 27, 46; Mark 5, 34</note>
 <note xml:id="b6741" type="ling" resp="#LZM">Note the word order: <hi rend="italic">le plus</hi> + noun + adjective</note> 
 <note xml:id="b6742" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Compare the illumination at the bottom of this folio.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6755" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 702): salue[e]</note>
 <note xml:id="b6759" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS, Stengel: l'asist. This does not make sense, since the queen approaches him then speaks to him. Cf. Turin line 6448 "<hi rend="italic">dapresso luy s</hi>'aseta e possa li rasona"; it can be a banal error of misreading a written text to confuse "l" and the long "s"</note>
 <note xml:id="b6760" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 703): ne l'[av]oit</note>
 <note xml:id="b6766" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 703): devers, which normally means "in the direction of"; "de devers" would mean from the area of ("du côté de," Matsumura). Thus two words here, as they are in the MS.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6772" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 703): Qu[e] il </note>
 <note xml:id="b6776" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 703): Tant que [d] (l)'enfer aige (<hi rend="italic">Tant que</hi> + subjuntive for 'Until')</note>
 <note xml:id="b6778" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 704): feütee (which would bring the line to 10 syllables); but cf. v. 4129, where two syllables are not necessary. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6779" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 704): desfiëe </note>
 <note xml:id="b6782" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 704): dame l'oit </note>
 <note xml:id="b6785" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 704): delïee; perhaps a better emendation would be "tot [li] delïee," for 12 syllables</note>
 <note xml:id="b6795" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 704): enfer [la] </note>
 <note xml:id="b6800" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 704): g'estoie (two clearly "stoie"; two clearly "estoie"; two not clear, this and <hi rend="italic">questoie</hi>, v. 10177) </note>
 <note xml:id="b6810" type="trans" resp="#LZM">See Dante, <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 5, 112-122, for the joy to sadness trope, here reversed.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6817" type="refer" resp="#LZM">(<hi rend="italic">qe</hi>) inserted above the line with caret below, but very light with tiny letters, not visible in microfilm.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6823" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 705): Et retorne; perhaps possible since "avoir" is the auxiliary verb of the previous line. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6824" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Sections of these three lines of the MS are here practically unreadable since somewhat rubbed off; as the middle of the section, the beginning of this line in particular is difficult to distinguish. Whether it is <hi rend="italic">vos</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ves</hi> cannot be determined.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6845" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p.706): m'ait mort'e (ni) perie </note>
 <note xml:id="b6858" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 707): raïne </note>
 <note xml:id="b6864" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 707): s'embla </note>
 <note xml:id="b6867" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 707): embracé </note>
 <note xml:id="b6869" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 708): Aces </note>
 <note xml:id="b6891" type="inter" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">peçé traitor</hi>: this could <hi rend="italic">peçe traïtor</hi>, "worst traitor"; we have followed Turin's usage of "pechà traditor"; had it been "worst" Turin would have read "peçor" or something similar rather than "pecha" from Latin PECCATU(M).</note>
 <note xml:id="b6896" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 709): sentirés [dunc] d'un </note>
 <note xml:id="b6903" type="codic" resp="#LZM">See first (left) part of the illumination below, where he holds a rock in his hand while he kneels in the garden.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6911" type="refer" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Le Roman d'Alexandre, Branche</hi> 3 for the plot to kill him; <hi rend="italic">Branche 4, laisses 4-11</hi>, particularly 8-33 (Harf-Larcner 752-83) for the actual poisoining.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6919" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 710): moy, [diex], ni </note>
 <note xml:id="b6923" type="codic" resp="#LZM">See the second (right) part of the illumination below, with fires, three angels (one with an open book) and devils coming out of the house on the right. </note>
 <note xml:id="b6936" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 711): (en)vers </note>
 <note xml:id="b6955" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 712): poït</note>
 <note xml:id="b6957" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 712): luy [et] conforter</note>
 <note xml:id="b6982" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 713): [A]lor</note>
 <note xml:id="b6983" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 713): vers (le) ciel</note>
 <note xml:id="b6984" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 713): qu'envoiantes</note>
 <note xml:id="b6989" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: <hi rend="italic">por</hi> expunctuated after <hi rend="italic">moy</hi>; there is also a scratch through the middle of the word, cutting each letter in half. Stengel ("Keuschheitsprobe," p. 713): (por) [per] diex</note>
 <note xml:id="b6992" type="trans" resp="#LZM">End of Stengel, "Keuschheitsprobe" (his line 7147).</note>
 <note xml:id="b6993" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Begin Stengel, "Suche" (his line 7148). He uses square brackets for his emendations/additions, and parentheses for his items to remove. He seeks to regularize the lines to 10 or 12 syllables, usually in comparison with the Turin version and Andrea da Barberino.</note>
 <note xml:id="b6997" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">aneslepas</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 292): "eneilepais," "immédiatement."</note>
 <note xml:id="b7011" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> FEW: <hi rend="italic">talevas</hi>, "bouclier en bois"; cf. <hi rend="italic">Roman d'Alexandre</hi> "talavat/z" (RIALFrI, 22.XII.2017), from *TALAPACIUM (https://apps.atilf.fr/lecteurFEW/lire/131/35)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7017" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p.1): Pou(t)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7018" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 2): (qu'il)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7026" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 2): Fors (da)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7029" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">(t)</hi>: inserted above the line, with a dim caret below.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7031" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">c(h)ar</hi>: very light insert, with no caret below.</note> 
 <note xml:id="b7038" type="codic" resp="#LZM">See illumination below; on left, ship with line tied to horse; on right, Huon fighting off the birds. Lots of blood, some birds in air, some on ground, and flock coming toward him. Cf. <hi rend="italic">Roman d'Alexander</hi> again, for attacks near a pond (Branche 3, laisses 64-85) that include griffons that carry away horses (3, 66; Harf-Lancner pp. 368-87, esp. 370-71).</note>
 <note xml:id="b7044" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 3): b[er] natural</note>
 <note xml:id="b7052" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 2) : per(e) </note>
 <note xml:id="b7058" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p.3) : Pr[ent] les</note>
 <note xml:id="b7075" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">(l)aris</hi>: again, very light insertion above the line and no caret. This was probably a correction from a saut de même au même: the preceding <hi rend="italic">al</hi> ends with an <hi rend="italic">l</hi> so the writer realized afterward the missing l.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7081" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 3): hom [abesoign]os</note>
 <note xml:id="b7091" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 4): descoverte [f]os</note>
 <note xml:id="b7097" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 4): quuens e(t)l(i) destrer </note>
 <note xml:id="b7117" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 4): fust (il) cheü</note>
 <note xml:id="b7125" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 4): Le quuens [Hue] d'Auvergne</note>
 <note xml:id="b7128" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Possibly <hi rend="italic">s'ant desis</hi>; see translation for the alternate meanings.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7131" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 5): P[ou] sant</note>
 <note xml:id="b7132" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 5): Mès [cum se] membre </note>
 <note xml:id="b7136" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 5): pecheor [et] çaitis</note>
 <note xml:id="b7138" type="interp" resp="#LZM">For the second hemistich here, see v. 7135, that ends in the same way; this line might be a scribal saut. See translation.</note> 
 <note xml:id="b7157" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 5): herra [il]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7170" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 6): iluech [il] fust</note>
 <note xml:id="b7173" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 6): A (tal) fuson (s'en) ist</note>
 <note xml:id="b7217" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The initial letter of <hi rend="italic">quuens</hi> is capitalized, which is unusual for this MS.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7226" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">avit</hi>: If read <hi rend="italic">aiut</hi>, then the meaning would differ: "Well he helped him so that the horse is not hurt." This section is difficult to parse. We decided to follow Turin, though there are other possibilities (see translation). Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 7): avi[n]t</note>
 <note xml:id="b7232" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 8): revint [el] serpant </note>
 <note xml:id="b7236" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The division between downstrokes in the MS is unreliable: <hi rend="italic">p[er]cuit/p[er]ciut</hi> are both possible.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7242" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 8): jor[nee]s </note>
 <note xml:id="b7260" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 8): ni [a] talant </note>
 <note xml:id="b7264" type="codic" resp="#LZM">There is a scraped section of MS before <hi rend="italic">t[ro]va</hi>, long enough for one letter. It too has the appearance of liquid correction fluid in the MS.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7269" type="interp" resp="#LZM">If <hi rend="italic">roy</hi> refers to God, then it should be capitalized, but it is not clear here whether the poem refers to Charles or to God.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7275" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Note the unusual abbreviation (for this MS) above <hi rend="italic">sorpagne</hi>.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7282" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 8): tue et magagne.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7283" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: marois as 7279 above. T: "<hi rend="italic">De le p</hi>rede "(line 6965); cf. T:"<hi rend="italic">Li gra[n] p</hi>redon" (6963, cf. 7279 here).</note>
 <note xml:id="b7285" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: q vif (q with line over top, normally <hi rend="italic">que</hi>)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7296" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">rocheit</hi>: cf TL <hi rend="italic">recet</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b7306" type="refer" resp="#LZM">See illumination below: merpeople, male and female. Possible source: there are a number of similar monsters in the <hi rend="italic">Roman d'Alexandre</hi>, 3, 164 (for mermaids); for men in two parts above the navel, 3, 181, etc. </note>
 <note xml:id="b7312" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> As Meregazzi says ("Ugo," 19), the <hi rend="italic">Roman d'Alexandre</hi> cites "li Otifal" (p. 319, l. 19, ed. Michelant), so we have divided this into <hi rend="italic">Roman d'Alexandre</hi> cites "li Otifal" (p. 319, l. 19, ed. Michelant), so we have divided this into <hi rend="italic">L'Ocifal</hi>. However, Harf-Larcner uses "Liotifal" (III, 2452) for "Ichtyophages"; grammatically, an article seems to be necessary in both the <hi rend="italic">Alexandre</hi> and here. </note>
 <note xml:id="b7321" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 10): l'eve [en vont] </note>
 <note xml:id="b7323" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 10): jor (ap)parant</note>
 <note xml:id="b7325" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 10): Voit [le] le</note>
 <note xml:id="b7329" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 10): [Et] en</note>
 <note xml:id="b7342" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 11): fu [al] monter</note>
 <note xml:id="b7343" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">si </hi> at end of line with a dot before it; in the line, a caret below with the same dot to indicate point of insertion. </note>
 <note xml:id="b7346" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 11): Mout [il]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7347" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel: <hi rend="italic">abescuç</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b7352" type="refer" resp="#LZM">See illumination below with rendering of the creatures.</note> 
 <note xml:id="b7358" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">au pré:</hi> nowhere does <hi rend="italic">aupré</hi> appear, whereas <hi rend="italic">pré</hi> and <hi rend="italic">aprés</hi> do appear. Furthermore, here the text makes a point of saying that Huon has just come down the mountain. T: quando un tal remore <hi rend="italic">è al pra venuto</hi> (l. 7037). Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 11): storbeillons li [est] au pré</note>
 <note xml:id="b7360" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Illumination in fact shows creatures first standing by water then falling from sky amid flames and light. Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 11): vive force (but 1st letter higher, last r); cf. T: Per liura forza, line 7039.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7366" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 11): (Au)Si</note>
 <note xml:id="b7367" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Cf. Dante and Brunetto Latini in <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>: the seventh circle, those of the violent, includes the violent against nature, the sodomites, who walk under a rain of fire (canto 15).</note>
 <note xml:id="b7369" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 11): Que (de)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7372" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 12): encor pluç</note>
 <note xml:id="b7384" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 12): (de)storbeillons</note>
 <note xml:id="b7391" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 12): Lu e[l] </note>
 <note xml:id="b7395" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 12): Mainte(s)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7401" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 12): l'en a öy</note>
 <note xml:id="b7404" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 12): cist [si] ert</note>
 <note xml:id="b7415" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 13): Si[l] leise</note>
 <note xml:id="b7420" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 13): environ,</note>
 <note xml:id="b7422" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 13): ot hons.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7437" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 13): nuls [mal]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7439" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: unay; Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 13): i m'ay</note>
 <note xml:id="b7441" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche"): trait[re][...] me straray</note>
 <note xml:id="b7443" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche"): ert [en] moy</note>
 <note xml:id="b7455" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 14): dit [il],</note>
 <note xml:id="b7464" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," 14): le veut [il]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7467" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">plais</hi> written below the line, following the next line with a box around three sides</note>
 <note xml:id="b7475" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">a il</hi> is written as one word in the MS</note>
 <note xml:id="b7488" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 15): part (ala)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7492" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">ap[re]nonl</hi>: one cannot help but wonder if there is perhaps something missing here; lines 7475-93 are problematic; Turin has omitted the equivalent of lines 7492-93 and altered line 7490. </note>
 <note xml:id="b7493" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">a soil</hi>: a difficult expression; cf. V4 Roland v. 6009; R. F. Cook, p. II/372; he also notes in his glossary, "unclear" and refers to his note. </note>
 <note xml:id="b7495" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 15): Volonter vos [di]ray</note>
 <note xml:id="b7498" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 15): si confort[e]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7499" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 15): sont [forment] </note>
 <note xml:id="b7504" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 15): [et] dricer</note>
 <note xml:id="b7505" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 15): S[e] il le</note>
 <note xml:id="b7508" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 15): l'out (il)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7524" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 16): poïs[se]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7543" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 16): selonch (le) pooir</note>
 <note xml:id="b7544" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 16): Doi[ven]t fer</note>
 <note xml:id="b7545" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 16): se [acono]ist</note>
 <note xml:id="b7554" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: la fair; but the line does not make sense without emendation, and a scribal "t" for "r" is a banal error. The other possibility would have been to follow T 7234: perché l'afare è si grande, como eio vo pu<hi rend="italic">r pensando</hi>, "because the matter is so important, as I believe," adding the verb "is" after <hi rend="italic">l'afair</hi>. See also note in the translation.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7555" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 17): voir(e)ment</note>
 <note xml:id="b7566" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 17): valor suy [ge]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7567" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 17): plus [ci] ester</note>
 <note xml:id="b7575" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 17): mes (de) deu</note>
 <note xml:id="b7580" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 17): de [nule] rien (dou sigle) vivent</note>
 <note xml:id="b7583" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 17): (m)es</note>
 <note xml:id="b7585" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 18): mout [fort] s'adolosa</note>
 <note xml:id="b7590" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Epic simile: Huon like good gold in a furnace, longer it's there, better it's refined.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7592" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 18): clers [il] vient</note>
 <note xml:id="b7594" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: pruç. The second letter is not clear, but seems like an "r"; cf. <hi rend="italic">proer</hi> in V4=<hi rend="italic">prover</hi>, "to test, to confront one thing with another" (Beretta, p. 588, sub voce)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7599" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 18): cuers l[e cl]ama</note>
 <note xml:id="b7612" type="edit" resp="#LZM">This could be emended to <hi rend="italic">sigue</hi>, "he had followed his path." </note>
 <note xml:id="b7613" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. Luke 2, 19 "Maria autem conservabat omnia verba haec, conferens in corde suo." (Vulgate) </note>
 <note xml:id="b7616" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 18): son affer(e)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7620" type="lex" resp="#LZM">DELI <hi rend="italic">attento</hi>: "che tiene la mente rivolta ad un oggetto" dated to the fourteenth century (Dante); related to "attenti" used with military for "Attention!"</note>
 <note xml:id="b7634" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 19): d[es] osiaus</note>
 <note xml:id="b7639" type="codic" resp="#LZM">See illumination below: Huon vs. serpent with two griffons, bleeding badly.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7648" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 19): qu'il [ert] mort</note>
 <note xml:id="b7651" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 19): part [se] trait</note>
 <note xml:id="b7653" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 19): nuls [autre]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7654" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 19): fer[e] nuls</note>
 <note xml:id="b7665" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 20): le mes(t)ere</note>
 <note xml:id="b7668" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 20): li veu[len]t</note>
 <note xml:id="b7669" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 20): nos(i) partir[ont]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7670" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 20): compagn(on)... si s'acostere</note>
 <note xml:id="b7671" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 20): qui(ln) non</note>
 <note xml:id="b7677" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Possibly this could be <hi rend="italic">d'amere</hi>, "of loving"; however, it lacks a pronoun as a referrent. See also the various references in Dante's <hi rend="italic">Comedy</hi> to Virgil as parent: <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 23.38, for instance. Furthermore, the Turin version reads "d'amare."</note>
 <note xml:id="b7680" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 20): droit[e]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7688" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 20): dote (fou ni)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7689" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> MS: perice. "peris"="de pierre" (<hi rend="italic">EE, GdA</hi>), but in 1355-56, the pope says that there is wood in it. Also, this adjective would not normally precede a noun.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7694" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 21): dentrel(e)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7701" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">soie</hi> might be here the feminine possessive adjective, possibly in an Italianate construction. This would be the only time in the text the form would appear after the noun. It could also be <hi rend="italic">s'oie</hi>: "he also had [held] the entire time." The three lines 7701-7703 refer to the episode in the illumination at the bottom of the page, where burning masses fall into water, and spirits are led along the side of the stream. T 7383 reads, "Vite un monte che tuto se corla e tuto <hi rend="italic">brusa</hi>" for 7702; there is no equivalent to 7701. Perhaps it means "He called on God, Holding the cross in his hand the whole time." In line 7702, the word "sevre" or "seure" could rather be "essever," "esseu" as drain, channel, ditch from "to stream out, flow away" (similar to English sewer).</note>
 <note xml:id="b7704" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 21): jusque[n] la</note>
 <note xml:id="b7705" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 21): conso[m]ant</note>
 <note xml:id="b7716" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 21: se fie</note>
 <note xml:id="b7717" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Ên</hi>="Et en"</note>
 <note xml:id="b7719" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. ): se [es]laisent</note>
 <note xml:id="b7722" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 21): D[e] aler</note> 
 <note xml:id="b7729" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 22): de spir(i)t</note>
 <note xml:id="b7734" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">quue[r]</hi>: could this be an error of abbreviation for "quue[n]"?</note>
 <note xml:id="b7744" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 22): as spirç [disant]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7748" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 22): e spir(i)ç</note>
 <note xml:id="b7751" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 22): [ja nul]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7759" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">doplé</hi>: this could be second person singular; the preceding line is all second person plural in addressing Huon and his party; the following line is second person singular (<hi rend="italic">as</hi>), so either is possible.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7760" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 22): main, [que] garder</note>
 <note xml:id="b7761" type="codic" resp="#LZM">T: <hi rend="italic">romanemo quie</hi>, "we stay here"; Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 22): por ce mainir a toy.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7762" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 22): "Autre non puet [estre]." di[t] le quuens demanoy; cf. T 7440: "Altro no[n] pò esere," lo [con]te dize," de presente. </note>
 <note xml:id="b7764.1" type="interp" resp="#LZM">T 7442: "Ora me dite," dize lo [con]te, "a ponto a ponto, n<hi rend="italic">o[n] me celate</hi>: Turin has two forms of the verb "to say." Here we seem have "Ore m'oÿ," "Now listen to me" in order to keep the syllable count. The verb form however would be second person singular, not plural as at the end of the line. </note>
 <note xml:id="b7764.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 23): "Or(e) moy"dit li cons "[dites], ni..."</note> 
 <note xml:id="b7766" type="interp" resp="#LZM">An alternative for lines 7766-7767 with different punctuation implying different speakers: "Figure ont d'om t[er]ran." "Tot ce vos no[n] ageç; / Que ate[n]t ce a toy?" plusor dit d[e]maineç. </note>
 <note xml:id="b7769" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 23): E un de ceus respont: "[Tu] par un forseneç (cf. T 7447).</note>
 <note xml:id="b7773" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 23): tot [ei] somes </note>
 <note xml:id="b7788" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 23): "De [mout] greignor </note>
 <note xml:id="b7793" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 23): Nen fu ce(s)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7796.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS has <hi rend="italic">jsrlm</hi> with bar over <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7796.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 23): li jué (!)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7797" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> Stengel ("Huons Suche," p 23): salue e Sau(l)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7800.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: puer, with <hi rend="italic">i</hi> above the line: form of Latin <hi rend="italic">puer</hi>, "child"</note>
 <note xml:id="b7800.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 24): puer (!)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7804" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 24): Or[e] ... e[st]...</note>
 <note xml:id="b7813" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. Brunetto Latini to Dante, <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 118-120, and various places where the sinners cannot remain because of another group coming. </note>
 <note xml:id="b7828" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> There seems to be something missing here, a verb. Stengel: [s'en vont] inserted. T: Le sperity malvasy s'en vano al centro del profondo </note>
 <note xml:id="b7830" type="refer" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">andon</hi>: TL lists "andon, ?" (Horn), col. 384; we presume it to be a form of "andare"</note>
 <note xml:id="b7832" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> It would seem that there was a saut de même au même here, with the verb "to fall" omitted, that probably began with "cai-" as well as the word <hi rend="italic">çaitif</hi>. Cf. <hi rend="italic">cait</hi> (5950), <hi rend="italic">chait</hi> (7280).</note>
 <note xml:id="b7841" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 25): s'(en) avit</note>
 <note xml:id="b7853" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: ponser. The first vowel was corrected; it seems that an "a "was changed to an "o." The lines of the "o" are heavier. <hi rend="italic">Laise</hi> for "las"; cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 359), "laiser," on the confusion of stems.</note> 
 <note xml:id="b7859" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 25): Pois se stoit [il colgieç, endormi( r) tost si fu</note>
 <note xml:id="b7869" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 25): [en] une chave</note>
 <note xml:id="b7872" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 26): Quant [il] le vit</note>
 <note xml:id="b7873" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 26): que [i]l n'oit </note>
 <note xml:id="b7874" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 26): si [a] dit</note>
 <note xml:id="b7877" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 26): [Et] quant</note>
 <note xml:id="b7880" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> There seems to be something missing here; at the end of a column, it is not surprising to find a skip. The Turin version is different in this section; see the same laisse number in that version.</note>
 <note xml:id="b7882" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 26): "Je toy conjur" [dist il] "au nom da part Yhesu</note>
 <note xml:id="b7890" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 26): Cum [je] vau</note>
 <note xml:id="b7891" type="trans" resp="#LZM">MS: Une clers; Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 26): Un(e) clercs</note>
 <note xml:id="b7893" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 26): dire [saince] decevemant </note>
 <note xml:id="b7898" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 26): doman(dan)t</note>
 <note xml:id="b7902" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 26): Ensi [fu] le dilúvie, cum a diex</note>
 <note xml:id="b7903" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 27): De ogne gneracion d'animal (i)ci fu ver(e)mant</note>
 <note xml:id="b7908" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 27): pués [fu]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7911" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 27): no[s] va lui[n]tanant</note>
 <note xml:id="b7913" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 27): le jor dou vener[di] sant</note>
 <note xml:id="b7918" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 27): lor (tot) l'animal</note>
 <note xml:id="b7921" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 27): et achoi (!) atant</note>
 <note xml:id="b7940" type="codic" resp="#LZM">There is an empty ruled line in the the MS between lines 7940 and 7941; Stengel inserts: [Soe mer fu estraite voiremant de Rabis], derived from the Turin soa madre fo veramente trata de Rabisia, l. 7660. </note>
 <note xml:id="b7942" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 28): Hom(e)</note>
 <note xml:id="b7946" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Arleschamps / Aliscans is the famous battle that Guillaume d'Orange [William of Orange] fought against the Saracens, losing all his kinfolk, and especially Vivian. </note>
 <note xml:id="b7948" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 28): j'è par nom</note>
 <note xml:id="b7955" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 28): [A] sainct Jacque </note>
 <note xml:id="b7958" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 28): Sil(e) </note>
 <note xml:id="b7959" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 28): laide[n]gé</note>
 <note xml:id="b7960" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 28): e (ces) mon. This is a typical Italianate construction: cf. "questo mio amico"</note>
 <note xml:id="b7962" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 28): [re]viençerent</note>
 <note xml:id="b7971" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 28): recov[r]irent</note>
 <note xml:id="b7973" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche"): jorne[e]</note>
 <note xml:id="b7988" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 29): (a)loïs </note>
 <note xml:id="b7992" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 29): cum [nos] or</note>
 <note xml:id="b7997" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 29): tenoit [il] la ville et li do[n]jon</note>
 <note xml:id="b7998" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," 29): après (de)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8010" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This section of the MS is difficult to read; perhaps there was water damage? </note>
 <note xml:id="b8011" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 30): embrace[r], ne dit [ne] oy</note>
 <note xml:id="b8025" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 30): dampné [en] vont</note>
 <note xml:id="b8029" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 30): fe[ï]sent</note>
 <note xml:id="b8034" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 30): hom(e)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8042" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 31): Diex [vos] aït</note>
 <note xml:id="b8057" type="codic" resp="#LZM">scharagais: see "scaraguaita," Bezzola, <hi rend="italic">Abbozzo</hi> (154). </note> 
 <note xml:id="b8058" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 31): [ce]l erbais</note>
 <note xml:id="b8064" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 31): l'en di[t]</note>
 <note xml:id="b8066" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche,"p. 31): nom (de) ce</note>
 <note xml:id="b8074" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 31): [r]estora. But T-L, "gut machen"; "ersetzen" etc.</note>
 <note xml:id="b8093" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 32): sent(r)ent, following the Turin use of "sentir" rather than "s'entrer" </note>
 <note xml:id="b8094" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 32): qui (lor) veïst</note>
 <note xml:id="b8095" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 32): Tote (la) montagne</note>
 <note xml:id="b8105" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 32): Mout (en) fu</note>
 <note xml:id="b8114" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 33): la [ou] ont</note>
 <note xml:id="b8117" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 33): Mout la va [re]gardant</note>
 <note xml:id="b8120" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 33): la tient [et] aseç</note>
 <note xml:id="b8123" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: avoir. T: <hi rend="italic">per sy avea</hi> pregà. Though the MS is very clear, this makes the greatest sense and is a typical copying error. Should one instead run it together with the following line, it could be construed that he staying up all night <hi rend="italic">having</hi> prayed, but it seems to be a stretch.</note>
 <note xml:id="b8130" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 33): requer[t]</note>
 <note xml:id="b8136" type="interp" resp="#LZM">An octave is the week following a holy day, based upon the Latin system of counting the day from which the count is made; so, a week.</note>
 <note xml:id="b8149" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 34): apert(e)mant</note>
 <note xml:id="b8152" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 34): savoir d[e] alchun </note>
 <note xml:id="b8160" type="refer" resp="#LZM">See note for line 1643.</note>
 <note xml:id="b8163" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 34): [Pués] a terre</note>
 <note xml:id="b8165" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 34): animal (et) tot (ces) qui</note>
 <note xml:id="b8166" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 34): adès [tre]tot</note>
 <note xml:id="b8167" type="lex" resp="#LZM">MS: fenue. This form does not appear anywhere else in Franco-Italian literature. T 7847: <hi rend="italic">Suo hofizio</hi> fazea</note>
 <note xml:id="b8170" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 34): [Et] quant Ugon</note>
 <note xml:id="b8176" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 34): avant (et) Ugon</note>
 <note xml:id="b8181" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">parlla[n]t</hi>: the final <hi rend="italic">t/</hi> is almost entirely washed out. </note>
 <note xml:id="b8192" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 35): per[e] aresteç</note>
 <note xml:id="b8199" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 35): A maint (et) maint</note>
 <note xml:id="b8200" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: butēt, very light, almost whited out.</note>
 <note xml:id="b8203" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 35): mostrent (et) signe</note>
 <note xml:id="b8204" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 35): S'il veu[t]</note>
 <note xml:id="b8205.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">enclostre</hi>: clearly written together in the MS. This is a Franco-Italianism, by someone very conscious of language structures. It derives from énkāuston; as DELI points out, the -l- was inserted. However, one must also note that Latin -CL- (/kl/), like other consonants before -L- is normally palatalized in Italian (Rohlfs ¶¶¶ 247-248; 250; 270), the spelling -clo- may represent a false etymology on the part of a scribe.</note>
 <note xml:id="b8205.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 35): si savra [toz] lor</note>
 <note xml:id="b8208" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 35): [a]fere</note>
 <note xml:id="b8212" type="inter" resp="#LZM">MS: <hi rend="italic">sorjugeç</hi>. This seems to be a scribal error for "forjugeç", 'condemned'; cf. line 10994. </note>
 <note xml:id="b8221" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 36): [Mist la en sa mosnere]. For <hi rend="italic">mosnere</hi>, see Holtus (Lexicalische, p. 377). </note>
 <note xml:id="b8222" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 36): Le frer[e]</note>
 <note xml:id="b8229" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 36): d'(en) ore</note>
 <note xml:id="b8241" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 36): jor[nees]</note>
 <note xml:id="b8242" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 36): Quant (il) oit beneoiç [les sainç peres] qi ... </note>
 <note xml:id="b8244" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 36): va [et] li</note>
 <note xml:id="b8245" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 36): Hue (tretot)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8246" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 36): long [pur] i veron</note>
 <note xml:id="b8250" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 37): [Et] maint</note>
 <note xml:id="b8261" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 37): la mer [chait et] ensi [cum] creison</note>
 <note xml:id="b8269" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 37): veeç (que)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8277.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Ms: son son</note>
 <note xml:id="b8277.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 37): son (son) sir</note>
 <note xml:id="b8283" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): Mout [il] mercie</note>
 <note xml:id="b8286" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Scribal error? Line was written twice by scribe, once as last line of a column, again as the first line of a column. We omit the repetition. The first version, on 57Vb, reads "puis quil oit troveç par lui nët oblie"; the second, 58Ra, "puis quil oit toueç par luy nert oblie" </note>
 <note xml:id="b8287" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): qui [il] l'oit, similar to our interpretation with the raised dot for the missing "i" </note> 
 <note xml:id="b8289.1" type="interp" resp="#LZM">MS: conte. One wonders if this should be "[en]contré" for "to meet" since a list of what they encountered follows. These few lines are difficult to comprehend; see the translation annotations as well.</note>
 <note xml:id="b8289.2" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): fu [il] puis</note>
 <note xml:id="b8291" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): (e)scampé</note>
 <note xml:id="b8296" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): De riens qu[e]</note>
 <note xml:id="b8299" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): Un[e] val[é]</note>
 <note xml:id="b8301" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): maint [grant] esclap</note>
 <note xml:id="b8304" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): mostrent (tot)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8306" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): [Et] pués </note>
 <note xml:id="b8307" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">adesés</hi>: compare <hi rend="italic">Foucon</hi> V19, line 6434, "Ch'el venist in França por son cor adasier" RIALFRI</note>
 <note xml:id="b8311" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): civauça (li ber)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8313" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): Qu(e) un(e) jor</note>
 <note xml:id="b8314" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): fluns (Tigris)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8315" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): Un (petit) repaire</note>
 <note xml:id="b8316" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 38): Iluech (li ber)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8320" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 39): leisir dormi(r)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8322" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 39): vit [il]</note>
 <note xml:id="b8328" type="interp" resp="#LZM">MS: e del son. Here, "e" seems to be from the verb "to be."</note>
 <note xml:id="b8329" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 39): Cum (ert)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8339" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 39): Tu as [a]</note>
 <note xml:id="b8344" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 39: adonqne (typographical error?)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8348" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 39): vi[n]t le pont de [nostre] departie</note>
 <note xml:id="b8351" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 39): aurent [tre]tuit</note>
 <note xml:id="b8355" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 40): Quant [plus] non porent (il plus), aval </note>
 <note xml:id="b8356" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 40): Autre (remis)</note> 
 <note xml:id="b8361" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: Te tenir; cf. T, line 8040: <hi rend="italic">de tenere</hi>sempre...</note>
 <note xml:id="b8362" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 40): [Et] por ce</note>
 <note xml:id="b8368" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 40): [Et] en air</note>
 <note xml:id="b8370" type="interp" resp="#LZM">This line is missing from T. The first hemistich is problematic; it is grammatical, but knowing how to fish and not getting anything though they know how is a little strange. Perhaps it was something with "avoir à" originally; "A pescher s'avomes," "We must fish" [...]. "se" as pronoun for the first person plural is well-documented (see Wünderli, "Se omnipersonnel dans L'Aquilon de Bavière"). Rohlfs (¶702) gives examples of "avere" with an infinitive without a preposition, but it is unclear to him and also from the examples whether an "a" is assimilated into either the conjugated verb or the dependent infinitive. He notes that in northern Italy various verbs are used with infinitive meaning "dovere," but gives no examples with "avere." Since the hemistich does make grammatical sense as it stands we have not separated a pronoun from the verb, but suggest this alternative meaning. </note>
 <note xml:id="b8385" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 40): Si vos (riens) de ma queste (car) rien (vos) en</note>
 <note xml:id="b8386" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 40): J[e] en </note>
 <note xml:id="b8388" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 41): Sanç (la) devine ... (mès); </note>
 <note xml:id="b8391" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 41): avant que (c)il </note>
 <note xml:id="b8403" type="interp" resp="#LZM">See note at line 8307. </note>
 <note xml:id="b8405" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 41): si [de] deu [il] non</note>
 <note xml:id="b8407" type="interp" resp="#LZM">See l. 2412, <hi rend="italic">aveit</hi>: from the verb "avoiier," to set off.</note>
 <note xml:id="b8409" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 41): par[oi]t</note>
 <note xml:id="b8412.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: don (with an apostrophe above the "n"). This is a single example in the entire MS of "n" with the apostrophe-like abbreviation, so its meaning is not clear; here "donque" seems to be the best interpretation for meaning (it is missing in T). </note>
 <note xml:id="b8412.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 41): don' (!)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8413" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 41): [tres]tote</note>
 <note xml:id="b8416" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 41): [Le]tre</note>
 <note xml:id="b8427" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 42): [Maintenant]</note>
 <note xml:id="b8428" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 42): s'est(oit)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8430" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 42): pechieç [av]oit</note>
 <note xml:id="b8433" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 42): q[e] il</note>
 <note xml:id="b8439" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 42): pas un[e] cenue</note>
 <note xml:id="b8441" type="refer" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">De profundis clamavi</hi>: One of the penitential psalms, 130 (129 in the Septuagint version): "Out of the depths I cry to thee, O Lord!" </note>
 <note xml:id="b8442" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 42): "Ad te (d'ne) domine"qui(l)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8446" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 42): non l'a[vo]it</note>
 <note xml:id="b8452" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 42): Celle [la voie li mostre]; </note>
 <note xml:id="b8455" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 42): que de[s] tenebre</note>
 <note xml:id="b8466" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 43): cuy [il] l'avoyt</note>
 <note xml:id="b8467" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">sen</hi>: this seems to be a form of "gente" </note>
 <note xml:id="b8481" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">preste</hi>: while in French forms this can mean "quickly, readily," in Italian it could mean "early" (DELI, already 14th century)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8483" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 43): loant [la] gloire [deu] celeste</note>
 <note xml:id="b8486.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: en is lightly written in above the line before <hi rend="italic">apres</hi>, with a small caret below the line.</note>
 <note xml:id="b8486.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 43): puis après [se] signa</note>
 <note xml:id="b8494" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 44): (Per nos) Te fa</note>
 <note xml:id="b8497" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 44): (par toy) ne</note>
 <note xml:id="b8506" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 44): [A] deu</note>
 <note xml:id="b8508" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 44): Que [vestre] non par</note>
 <note xml:id="b8509" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 44): quier la ver(i)té; usually Stengel has emendations of items to remove in parentheses; the "i" is not present. The line is ten syllables without it, so this seems to be Stengel's error. </note>
 <note xml:id="b8513" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 44): n(e)is</note>
 <note xml:id="b8517" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 44): n'est(oit)</note>
 <note xml:id="b8518" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 44): Après (tretot) ice [tot] l'estre l'en geïs; "geïs" seems to be a form of "to recount," "gehier" (T-L jehir) </note>
 <note xml:id="b8521" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 44): nuls hom [qui] seit huy vis</note>
 <note xml:id="b8522" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 44): a (tre)tot conceïs</note>
 <note xml:id="b8528" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Genesis 2:10–14 lists four rivers in association with the garden of Eden: Pishon, Gihon, the Hiddekel (=Tigris?), and the Euphrates; so the Fison in MS is probably the Pishon. </note>
 <note xml:id="b8530" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 45): partir[oi] ge</note> 
 <note xml:id="b8533" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: Em proy.The "o is expunctuated.</note> 
 <note xml:id="b8535" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 45): voy (a) tot jors</note>
 <note xml:id="b8536" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 45): a rais[on]ner; for syllable count, <hi rend="italic">â raisner</hi> would also be possible</note>
 <note xml:id="b8538" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 45): demora [il] </note>
 <note xml:id="b8539" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 45): Ugon [mostre] </note>
 <note xml:id="b8541" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 45): [et] pois pris [a] comunïer</note>
 <note xml:id="b8554.1" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 45): font il "(Ja) Ni</note>
 <note xml:id="b8554.2" type="refer" resp="#LZM">For the apples that cannot rot, cf. the two that the angel provides in the <hi rend="italic">Entrée d'Espagne</hi>, line 15042, and that the hermit and Roland share.</note>
 <note xml:id="b8564" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 46): oit [il] herré</note>
 <note xml:id="b8568" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 46): Quant [li] son</note>
 <note xml:id="b8570" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 46): leisir [de] trop</note>
 <note xml:id="b8573" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 46): [Et] refrener</note>
   <note xml:id="b8579" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">anchué</hi>: cf. T-L "encui" from Latin HODIE; here also <hi rend="italic">anchuy, ancuy</hi></note>
  <note xml:id="b8580" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 46): davant [tot] l'aer</note>
 <note xml:id="b8582" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 46): en oit [il] tüé</note>
 <note xml:id="b8588" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 46): [Et] ceus</note>
 <note xml:id="b8594" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 46): deu (e)sperance. Again, this seems an error; there is no initial e- in the MS.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8610" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 47): po[r] luy font [pou de] defendance</note>
   <note xml:id="b8613" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 47): [plus non] sostinent</note>
   <note xml:id="b8618" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 47): amb[e]dos. The following line is mislabelled in Stengel, "66b" for "60b"</note>
 <note xml:id="b8619" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">haitisse</hi>: this seems to be a confusion between <hi rend="italic"> aatir</hi> and <hi rend="italic">haster</hi>; the <hi rend="italic"> -isse</hi> is chosen for rhyme</note>
   <note xml:id="b8621" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 47): oisel(lon) que</note>
   <note xml:id="b8624.1" type="interp" resp="#LZM">See T: per mé la rivera; clearly the writer here understood "l'areine," like MSI "la rena," 'the sand"</note>
   <note xml:id="b8624.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 47): Pormi la reine a or mainel(e)</note>   
   <note xml:id="b8628" type="lex" resp="#LZM">For the form <hi rend="italic">laine</hi>, see Holtus (Lexicalische, p. 358).</note>
   <note xml:id="b8635" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 48): las, [que] non</note>
   <note xml:id="b8636" type="trans" resp="#LZM">("Huons Suche," p. 48): Sparagner [la] le veut</note>
   <note xml:id="b8637.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS seems to be missing the definite article, which is necessary for sense as well as syllable count.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8637.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 48): Vait s'en quuens [Hue], proposing instead that the name is missing; perhaps the scribe thinks of "quuens" as a nickname.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8642" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 48): [Il] morbirent</note>
   <note xml:id="b8655" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 48): Al cef davant po[u]</note>
   <note xml:id="b8656.1" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 48): Un[e] grant</note>
   <note xml:id="b8656.2" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: Un gnt (with two dots over "n") masse</note>
   <note xml:id="b8657" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: du cengler</note>
   <note xml:id="b8666" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 48): [a]chaminer</note>
   <note xml:id="b8670" type="trans" resp="#LZM">M. Scattonlini edits from this line through 10382 in her dissertation. She has generously allowed us to compare readings, sharing her transcription with us. Where we differ in reading, it will be noted. She does not use capitals at the beginning of each line, or diereses, and the punctuation differs; these we do not note. In addition her word divisions can differ. She also resolves all abbreviations for "p" with <hi rend="italic">per</hi>, where we vary according to context. The copy that we have is electronic, and therefore we do not give page numbers; the line numbers should suffice, though she uses Stengel's line numbers for the Berlin version.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8674" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 49): Quil(e) pais</note>
   <note xml:id="b8675" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 49): le vit, [va] adès (va)</note>
   <note xml:id="b8677" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 49): Mès (ja)</note>
   <note xml:id="b8679" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 49): serp(ant)</note>
   <note xml:id="b8683" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 49): [vive] force. But cf. line 7360 above.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8685" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 49): puisqu[e] il</note>
   <note xml:id="b8689" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: ne ̓l; wherever I use the raised dot, she uses the apostrophe; it will not be commented again. </note>
   <note xml:id="b8700" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: nen seroit</note>
   <note xml:id="b8702" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: e obliay ... e' fi [...]</note>
   <note xml:id="b8709" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: neanch (cf. Italian "neanche")</note>
   <note xml:id="b8710" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: pués</note>
   <note xml:id="b8711" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 50), Scattolini: voil [conv]ant</note>
   <note xml:id="b8713" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: age nul</note>
   <note xml:id="b8714" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: magiay; Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 50): (qi) ni ma[n]giay</note>
   <note xml:id="b8724" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: clamese'n colpe</note>
   <note xml:id="b8726" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini resolves <hi rend="italic">cu[n]</hi> consistently.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8729" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: dastus, as always combining following pronouns. This will not be commented again.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8736" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">pieté</hi> here seems to convey something like Aeneas's epithet, "pius Aeneas," that is, one who respects religion, country and home, and heads a divine mission. </note>
   <note xml:id="b8745" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 51): sir(e) Naçarenus</note>
   <note xml:id="b8752" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 51): Voy (en)ci ; Scattolini: "Voy enci toe mere, si l'avoi esleus"; the subject of the second hemistich is not clear. With the -s ending, it seems a second person singular– two of the other three forms are definitively so (the third is in rhyme).</note>
   <note xml:id="b8754" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Huons Suche," p. 51): merci (de moy) douç e ben[eoiç] fius</note>
   <note xml:id="b8758" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: le scripture; she divides generally with the s- impura as a start of the word, as in Italian. This will not be remarked again.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8759" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: ferai (MS: ʃerai)</note>
   <note xml:id="b8761" type="trans" resp="#LZM">End of Stengel's "Huons Suche" transcription.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8762" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Transcribed by Tobler, lines 8762-9038 (pp. 609-14). Since there is only one Tobler article, we do not give any precisions other than the line number.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8765" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: e[r]t cheue</note>
   <note xml:id="b8772" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The hand under the chin is a traditional pose for one pondering that has come through to modern times; cf. Rodin.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8777" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: <ex rend="angle">et</ex> Hue; the line is somewhat problematic. This is the only appearance of "hue" as a verb, elsewhere it is a form of "Huon." But there is "il dit" and the line is 10 syllables so we are not emending.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8791" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: el dit, "N'avoir [...]</note>
   <note xml:id="b8808" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: <ex rend="angle">Di va</ex></note>
   <note xml:id="b8809.1" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: e le malvais</note>
   <note xml:id="b8809.2" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">el malvais</hi> for "et + il" <hi rend="italic">malvais</hi></note>
   <note xml:id="b8811" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: que ti rien</note>
   <note xml:id="b8818" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Presumably the devil is referring here to the siege of Auvergne by Charles Martel in order to take Ynide.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8821" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: seroi ge</note>
   <note xml:id="b8822" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: Fuyci</note>
   <note xml:id="b8823" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: creroi ge</note>
   <note xml:id="b8828" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Tobler: laut [o]steil</note>
   <note xml:id="b8829" type="ling" resp="#LZM"> The rhyme here calls for a diphthongue, but the standard form is <hi rend="italic">traïs</hi> to mark the hiatus. Cf. the situation with "oÿ" in vv. 1643 etc. Cf. below, line 8831.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8830" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. T 8502: zò fo senifichanza che nula no[n] l'amasty</note>
   <note xml:id="b8835" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: fesis mançer</note>
   <note xml:id="b8840." type="interp" resp="#LZM">Or possibly, <hi rend="italic">en ci berais</hi>, "drink it here / thus"; however, we here follow T's word division; cf. line 11168 "cibe." There is only the formswith bev- for 'to drink' in this MS (4 forms), and see Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 290) for <hi rend="italic">enci</hi>. </note>
   <note xml:id="b8840.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: enci berais (she gives  "tu t'acibe" for Turin 8512).</note>
   <note xml:id="b8843" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Cf. T 8514 : coventa che yo te mene a le gra[n] tenenbre. We emend basing on the Turin line for a frequent paleographical error of "r" for "t". </note>
   <note xml:id="b8846" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: Chain</note>
   <note xml:id="b8851" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: de ci ore</note>
   <note xml:id="b8857" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: a don</note>
   <note xml:id="b8859" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini ends the direct address with this line.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8862" type="lex" resp="#LZM">For <hi rend="italic">enbron</hi>, see Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 288).</note>
   <note xml:id="b8875" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> T reads "six feet" (<hi rend="italic">de sy piede</hi> me parea longo, line 8546).</note> 
   <note xml:id="b8879" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: t'encontron; T 8550: te contoe</note>
   <note xml:id="b8880" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> This section of conversation is problematic to understand. This line and the preceding are significantly different in the Turin MS. The scribe would seem to have misunderstood or omitted something from his original here; the translation adds that this is Huon speaking here, our best guess.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8881" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: "Non creira s'a toy non [...]</note>
   <note xml:id="b8885" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: qu'e[st] (sic)</note>
   <note xml:id="b8890" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: za usir poras</note>
   <note xml:id="b8906" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: m'es mostree</note>
   <note xml:id="b8913" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: <ex rend="angle">de</ex> jant</note>
   <note xml:id="b8918" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: çorné (emendation not necessary; the sounding of a horn is part of the Day of Judgement)</note>
   <note xml:id="b8929" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: [de]strucion; but this adds a syllable to a 5+5 line</note>
   <note xml:id="b8936" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Dante (<hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi> 9.22-30) recounts Virgil's trip to hell at the bidding of Erichtho, perhaps based on <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi> 6.562-65. </note>
   <note xml:id="b8938" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: ll'inferno</note>
   <note xml:id="b8955" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: sastu, combining verb with following subject as always. Not further remarked.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8959" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: auroient</note>
   <note xml:id="b8974" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">âlgun</hi> for "a algun"</note> 
   <note xml:id="b8975" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">afaitement</hi>: see Bezzola, <hi rend="italic">Storia dei gallicismi</hi> (253). </note> 
   <note xml:id="b8982" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: de ci, as always. Not remarked further.</note>
   <note xml:id="b8984" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: exilment</note>
   <note xml:id="b8992" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: l'en</note>
   <note xml:id="b9003" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: qui te voy</note>
   <note xml:id="b9008" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: en doit destrie</note>
   <note xml:id="b9009" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: a une fontaine</note>
   <note xml:id="b9020" type="codic" resp="#LZM">p<ex rend="angle">er</ex>duç: no abbreviation line is visible in the MS; Tobler: pdu'x; Scattolini: perduç</note>
   <note xml:id="b9025" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Tobler: ɾaincte Marie. Forms of "Marie" with the saint prefix appear 19 times; of those, 6 are abbreviated. Of the remaining 13, 11 are "sancte" with only 2 "saincte," so we here follow the most frequent, though overall "sainct/e" forms are more frequent (93 to 52, including adjectives, superlatives, verb). In line 9032 below, two unabbreviated forms "saincte vie" appear, so we resolve to follow those.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9026" type="ling" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">a conduir</hi>: separated future, "will lead," typical of the northern Italian peninsula (see Rohlfs, vol. 2, <hi rend="italic">Morfologia</hi>, ¶ 590).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9027" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: n'aura</note>
   <note xml:id="b9035" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: cue char</note>
   <note xml:id="b9038" type="trans" resp="#LZM">End of Tobler's transcription selection.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9039" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Beginning of Stengel's transcription of "Huons aus Auvergne Höllenfahrt." As elsewhere, only differences will be noted: [ ] indicate his emendations, ( ) his suppression of a MS reading. He edited through laisse 385, line 10079.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9045" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">examplir</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, pp. 305-306), "accomplir, observer (la loi, etc.)," "to fulfill, perform, observe (the law, etc.)."</note>
   <note xml:id="b9048" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: <ex rend="angle">e</ex> fuy</note>
   <note xml:id="b9058" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: l'andeman a defloy</note>
   <note xml:id="b9071" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: s'il conjuray,  "and he begged" vs. "and he begged him"</note>
   <note xml:id="b9074" type="interp" resp="#LZM">el = et il </note>
    <note xml:id="b9075" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: estara</note>
   <note xml:id="b9109" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: desor; this follows Turin 8779, "de sopra," 'up above'; but "des or," 'from now on,' also is possible.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9137" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: si prāt very light at end of line. T: <hi rend="italic">per l'altr</hi>uy ridre el se vergogn âspramente </note>
   <note xml:id="b9142" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: verra. There are three appearances of <hi rend="italic">venra</hi> and three (including this) <hi rend="italic">vēra</hi>, plus five others with "nr" in the stem, and none with "rr"; thus we expand "nr" </note>
   <note xml:id="b9153" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Vidossi (<hi rend="italic">Le Origini</hi>, pp. 1202-19) includes laisses 350-361 (not completely; sections are omitted). Vidossi (p. 1202-03 n1) says that he and Arese have transcribed and translated from a photograph of the Berlin MS; they mention Stengel's "Huon' saus Auvergne Hollenfahrt" [sic]. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9167" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: voeç</note>
   <note xml:id="b9170" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: Will<hi rend="italic">el</hi>me...luy la asis</note>
   <note xml:id="b9179" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: da mont a val</note>
   <note xml:id="b9180" type="codic" resp="#LZM">T has an additional line following this: 8849 <hi rend="italic">si foseno l'u</hi>no sopra l'altro tuty metute "if they were placed one on top of the other" </note>
   <note xml:id="b9184" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: ni mist</note>
   <note xml:id="b9191" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: le avis</note> 
   <note xml:id="b9192" type="interp" resp="#LZM">This lines is problematic; it is ten syllables as it stands, but the subject of the verb is unclear, and "stranglotir" has two possible meanings; in either case something missing: the subject or the object. One possible emendation, if there were a <hi rend="italic">saut de même au même</hi>, would be missing <hi rend="italic">le/li a</hi> before stranglotis: "strangled them" or "extinguished it."></note> 
   <note xml:id="b9193" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: sianç</note>
   <note xml:id="b9207.1" type="ling" resp="#LZM"> MS: dovien. This is the only appearance of that form. Note, however, that <hi rend="italic">doiven</hi> appears three times (7925, 10369, 11855) but <hi rend="italic">devien</hi> appears three times as well (6964, 8091, 11660), so the position of the diphthong varies.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9207.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: doiven</note>
   <note xml:id="b9209" type="lex" resp="#LZM">T: semenare, "to sow"; one wonders if that was also the intention here, "a devil sowed [planted]"</note>
   <note xml:id="b9211" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: Guill<hi rend="italic">el</hi>me, as always for the name; not further noted.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9216" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: aviser</note>
   <note xml:id="b9227" type="codic" resp="#LZM">See illumination at the bottom of the page for the four gates; they would seem, however, to be out of order. The one to the right seems to have its gates on the ground, with a figure of a man above; the third from the binding seems to have a lion above. Note the three men to the left; Aeneas, Guillaume d'Orange, and Huon. Huon seems to either have a brown face here, or be wearing a mask. All three are identifiable through their clothes as seen in the earlier three illuminations..</note>
   <note xml:id="b9236" type="refer" resp="#LZM">This quote (or paraphrase) would seem to be related to classical condemnations of hubris, such as that of Hesiod in his <hi rend="italic">Theogony</hi> (where he relates the succession of gods getting what is coming to them in return for assaulting authority), and in particular his <hi rend="italic">Works and Days</hi>, where he illustrates how hard work merits an appropriate reward, in opposition to the hubris for glorious deeds advocated by the classical epics of Homer. He especially praises Justice, Zeus's favorite daughter. See http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0132%3Acard%3D1 for the translation into English (esp. chapters 255-73 for Justice).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9246" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: qu'el </note>
   <note xml:id="b9249" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">planoy</hi>: "planets" (Mainone, <hi rend="italic">Laut und Formen</hi>, p. 32)</note>
   <note xml:id="b9254" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">regraigne</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, pp. 294-95), "rugir," "to roar, to bellow." </note>
   <note xml:id="b9261" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: e<hi rend="italic">rt</hi> de menor</note>
   <note xml:id="b9265" type="refer" resp="#LZM">This is a reference to Harrowing of Hell.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9268" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: la versa (but cf. v. 9219, "Fasoit le jonchs tretotes averser" where the verb must have the a- prefix)</note>
   <note xml:id="b9273" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: navant [...] serra (there is no abbreviation)</note>
   <note xml:id="b9278" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: cil que la enç</note>
   <note xml:id="b9284" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: que l'a</note>
   <note xml:id="b9286" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: ert, de. Scattolini notes that this line and the following three are only present in B and T, and contain a specific reference to Purgatory so that they are more similar to visionary literature than other versions. She suggests that the reference to reading something in line 9288 in particular might be reading the <hi rend="italic">Tractatus de Purgatorio Sancti Patricii</hi> (358).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9288.1" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The second hemistich here is problematic; the meaning seems clear, but the lexeme division is not. Vidossi notes that there seems to be a damaged spot. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9288.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: lejera (since the line is twelve syllables without hiatus here, we do not add a dieresis; in general in this text, reflexes of <hi rend="italic">laisser</hi> do not have a hiatus according to the syllable count.)</note>   
   <note xml:id="b9289" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> Vidossi emends: "davant [dit] je t'ois" = "ti avevo parlato" [I had spoken to you]</note>  
    <note xml:id="b9298" type="interp" resp="#LZM">MS: anue d'vois; <hi rend="italic">anve</hi> is understood here for "envers." This line is absent from T. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9310" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. Dante <hi rend="italic">Par.</hi> 33.64; Graf p. 107.Cf. Dante Par. 33.64; Graf p. 107. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9314" type="ling" resp="#LZM">e<hi rend="italic">n</hi> plois: compare line 7494 for the construction with <hi rend="italic">en</hi>: s'il vos e<hi rend= "italic">n</hi> plaist </note>
   <note xml:id="b9320" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 5.31, "bufera"</note>
   <note xml:id="b9326" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Graf, p. 107; Inf. 4.13. Much of this laisse derives from expressions in <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, especially Canto 3. </note> 
   <note xml:id="b9331" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Note that here Huon is able to touch Guillaume physically, though he was not able to embrace him earlier. This contradiction is not dissimilar to the situation in <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9334" type="interp" resp="#LZM">As for many numbers in this text, the second part is written above the first, so above .x. is the 'm'. Note that the noise here is compared with sounds of war- weapons, hunting and blacksmithing– before moving to natural comparisons more typical of Dante. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9335" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: que tot a point </note>
   <note xml:id="b9337" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. St. Brendan; Gardiner, pp. 115-116. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9339" type="refer" resp="#LZM">For the sound of water, see <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 16. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9343" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">blasfemer</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 235-36). </note>
   <note xml:id="b9345" type="refer" resp="#LZM">This line through line 10500 skipped by Vidossi in his translation into Italian. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9346" type="lex" resp="#LZM">For cobre, see Möhren, p. 321; it comes from old N. Italian, and is attested in old Bolognese and old Genovese. For the idea, see <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 18.2: "pietra di color ferrigno" </note>
   <note xml:id="b9348" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 24.124, "vita bestial" </note>
   <note xml:id="b9349" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">mer</hi> = "mirent," from the verb "metre" </note>
   <note xml:id="b9352.1" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: Ore si garde: qui muer sainç sper oit mal</note>
   <note xml:id="b9532.2" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 3.9.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9358" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: a ge dit</note>
   <note xml:id="b9362" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: balestre</note>
   <note xml:id="b9377" type="codic" resp="#LZM">'l' inserted above the line, with caret below.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9378" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">enquesicion</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 298), "enquête," "investigation, inquiry." </note>
   <note xml:id="b9388" type="ling" resp="#LZM">Here we resolve "cu<hi rend="italic">m</hi>" to keep a parallel construction. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9393" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Line edited at the end; after 'son' there is a light line and then the first downstroke of 'm' seems inserted, darker, very close to that line. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9397" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS <hi rend="italic">a</hi> expunctuated with <hi rend="italic">e</hi> above. We give the corrected reading here. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9399" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: laser</note>
   <note xml:id="b9402" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: nen ont</note>
   <note xml:id="b9403" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> This scene is illuminated at the bottom of the page, the left-most panel, with multiple bodies in coffins, surrounded by devils with red flames coming out of their bodies. The insects are not visible. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9404.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">e</hi>- inserted with caret below.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9404.2" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 3.66; 3.69.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9408" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: sor, emended. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9410" type="refer" resp="#LZM">T 9074: che zascun el so corpo speza </note>
   <note xml:id="b9413" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Dante, <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 3.103-105. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9415" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: de pere</note>
   <note xml:id="b9417" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: sedaine; cf. P=sodoma.; T: sotomity</note>
   <note xml:id="b9420" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> Cf. Dante, <hi rend="italic"> Inf</hi>. 33.135.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9421" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. Dante, <hi rend="italic"> Inf</hi>. 22.15; <hi rend="italic">Morgante</hi> 18.144.8. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9423" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Third part of the illumination at the bottom of the page: figures with blotches on their clothes, devils around, and another figure looking down, looks like he's being pulled by devils. Center illustrates the three figures, Aeneas, Huon, and St. Guillaume, in that order.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9425" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: set</note>
   <note xml:id="b9426" type="lex" resp="#LZM">See TL <hi rend="italic">pustule</hi> col. 2103; for <hi rend="italic">marmosse</hi>, cf. <hi rend="italic">marmoser</hi>, FEW <hi rend="italic">marm-</hi> ; Matsumura, "marmotter"</note>
   <note xml:id="b9429" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: en fiert; cf. <hi rend="italic">Attila</hi>, "enferer"</note>
   <note xml:id="b9430" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Dictionaries refer to "enfrener" for "enferner," but here there might also be a play on words: "to put into inferno, hell" (see Hindley, for example) </note>
   <note xml:id="b9433" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: vanegl<hi rend="italic">ori</hi>e, here one word but two words in previous line</note>
   <note xml:id="b9443" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Dante, <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 33.142-47 . </note>
   <note xml:id="b9446" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: n'el font</note>
   <note xml:id="b9449" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Dante, <hi rend="italic">Inf. </hi>14.39, etc.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9451" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. Graf, p. 107; Dante, <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 7.64 ff. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9455.1" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolin: por man</note>
   <note xml:id="b9455.2" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">porman</hi> appears in the <hi rend="italic">Entrée d'Espagne</hi> specifically in the form "ja porman" in the meaning "bientôt" [soon].</note>
   <note xml:id="b9466" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: ceran; this word does not seem to appear in any dictionary, but the MS reading is clear; it would seem to mean either a place or a time. <hi rend="italic">Terran, terren</hi>, etc. appears numerous times in this text, and in other F-I texts both as noun and adjective; in RIALFRI on 9 Nov. 2018, <hi rend="italic">teran</hi> appears 19 times, frequently in rhyme, and "c" and "t" confusions are frequent in paleographical tradition.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9468" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. Dante, <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 2.13; according to tradition, Aeneas had a son after his death, whom his wife bore in the woods, so named him "Silvius." Various Latin historians give "Aeneas Silvius" as the son of Silvius (Livy, <hi rend="italic">Ab urbe conditor</hi> 1.3; Dionysius of Helicarnassus, <hi rend="italic">Antiquitates romanae</hi> 1.71); according to the same historians, his successor was Latinus Silvius. In any case, the descendants of the rulers of the Trojan settlement took the cognomen "Silvius" attached to personal names. Here then the "Silvian" seems to refer to the family line initiated by Aeneas's father, Anchises, whom Aeneas brought with him away from Troy. The father did not make it to the Italian peninsula. Scattolini notes that the reference is backwords and turned around though refering to <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> (361 n641).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9471" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the first part of the illumination at the bottom of the page. Several figures are in water up to the waist, with devils at the bottom, rocks over head. The furthest right figure in the swamp has an 'S' over his head. In the middle are the two figures, Huon and Guillaume (who is always identified with a halo, and is in bare feet). Huon is turned toward the left, to Saudin. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9473" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Note the -<hi rend="italic">nt</hi> ending in an <hi rend="italic">-n</hi> laisse. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9475" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">rufian</hi>: Cf. Möhren who defines it as "maquereau" from the Italian (p. 320). </note>
   <note xml:id="b9479.1" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: qu'ils ont ovran</note>
   <note xml:id="b9479.2" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> T 9142: lor àno lavorato. It is difficult here to know how to interpret "ovran," which might explain the preceding verb. If a past participle, Scattolini's reading makes sense. Mainone (<hi rend="italic">Formen</hi>, p. 15) gives "part," but that could be either present or past.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9481" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini argues that the laisse is part of William's discourse to Huon (361 n651).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9494" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The second (rightmost) portion of the illumination on this page is a mangonel hefting stones, a series of which go across the top of the illumination. The drawing is very detailed and would no doubt interest a historian of arms. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9500" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Brown spot in the middle of the line, over end of 'tu' and beginning of 'gre', as above in 9477 at the end of the line. Furthermore, the illumination at the bottom is in two parts. The first consists of the jugleor with devils around them with fire coming out of them. The furtherst right of the figures has "S" above his head to indicate "Saudin"; there is a brownish wash over their lower extremities that could be the source of the spots elsewhere on the page. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9503" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">di</hi> above the line with caret below.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9505" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Graf, p. 109; <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 21.50 ff. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9507" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini inadvertently mislabels here, 65 r b (her v. 9664).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9508" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">E 'n</hi> for "et in" </note>
   <note xml:id="b9509" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Huon apparently asks this question. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9519" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi: <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 10.22-24. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9552" type="refer" resp="#LZM">For the form <hi rend="italic">inferin</hi> see Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 350).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9562" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">t</hi> inserted above the line with caret below. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9564" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: seroi ge</note>
   <note xml:id="b9572" type="refer" resp="#LZM">For <hi rend="italic">robist</hi> see Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 431) and Mainone (<hi rend="italic">Laut und Form</hi>, p. 30); <hi rend="italic">fagon</hi> is more problematic; see <hi rend="italic">Attila</hi>, "facion: .... fazione, l'insieme di schiere di soldati." 
     Mainone is unclear as to the meaning; he originally suggests <hi rend="italic">robist</hi> as deriving from a verb form, but being the adjective "wild" [Fr. "rubeste," Ital "rubesto"], each of the sinners in the mud ( he suggests "fagon" is like "fango," "mud," in T and P). Holtus also designates <hi rend="italic">robist</hi> as an adjective. ; for fagon, Attila, "facion: .... fazione, l'insieme di schiere di soldati." Mainone is unclear as to the meaning; he originally suggests robist as deriving from  a verb form, but being the adjective "wild" [Fr. "rubeste," Ital "rubesto"]  each of them in the mud (he suggests "fagon" is like "fango," "mud," in T and P). Holtus also designates it an adjective, "sauvage, violent," [wild, violent] but does not clarify <hi rend="italic">fagons</hi>, which does not appear in any other F-I text listed in RIALFRI (as of 6 Dec. 2018).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9573" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: menistr; there is no abbreviation. For the lines 9573-75, Cf. Graf, pp. 107-108; <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 3. 103-105. The 'mo' of <hi rend="italic">mort</hi> in the next line has been edited. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9579" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi> 290): <hi rend="italic">enclusé</hi> comes from "accuser" (It. <hi rend="italic">incusare</hi>). However, there is also the form based on "nailed," 'encloer', so possibly this could be "how Charles Martel trapped him" or "nailed him" in the sense of stuck him with the job, making Huon a Christ figure as if nailed to his cross.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9599" type="refer" resp="#LZM">This could reflect <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 3.52-54, where Dante sees an "'nsegna" that spirits follow mindlessly.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9604" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the illumination at the bottom of the next page, 67R, next to this description. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9607" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Meregazzi: <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 3.84. The next line appears in Graf, p. 108.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9608" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">cenis</hi>: cf. Mainone (<hi rend="italic">Laut</hi>, p. 29 n1), "Asche"; he notes that it also appears in <hi rend="italic">Hector [et Hercule]</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Attila</hi>; RIALFRI adds Martin da Canal's <hi rend="italic">Estoires de Venise</hi> to the list of other occurences.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9612.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">d</hi> is inserted above the line, with an abbreviation mark over it.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9612.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: desperis</note>
    <note xml:id="b9616" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Graf, p. 108; Meregazzi, <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 3.72-73.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9617" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 3.125.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9623" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 2.88-90, Beatrice to Virgil.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9626" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the figure to the left of the illumination below, with bow and arrows in a quiver at his waist. Naked figures are visible in the water under the boat also.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9642" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 24.15.</note>  
   <note xml:id="b9653" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> Meregazzi, <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 3.109-11; cf. Graf, p. 108.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9655" type="codic" resp="#LZM">There is no abbreviation at all on the word 'etres'. The illumination shows Charon with an oar, not a sail; T 9314 gives "remo," 'oar.' </note>
   <note xml:id="b9656" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 3.111. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9657" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 8.17; 8.24 where Phlegyas (Flegïas) and Filippo Argenti appear. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9659" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> The first three words of the line were scratched out and then replaced.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9661" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> For <hi rend="italic">confés</hi>, see Mainone (<hi rend="italic">Laut</hi>, p. 24). </note>
   <note xml:id="b9662" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Graf. p. 108, for these three lines. <hi rend="italic">Inf.</hi> 3.88-89. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9663" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 3.88-96. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9670" type="refer" resp="#LZM">For <hi rend="italic">flés</hi> see Mainone (<hi rend="italic">Laut</hi>, p. 24). </note>
   <note xml:id="b9681" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: aplantés</note>
    <note xml:id="b9695" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 12.13-20, Virgil to the Minotaur. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9700" type="refer" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 12.26-27. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9713" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Dares the Phrygian. See note in the translation.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9716.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The illumination at the bottom of this page is of a city with five towers visible, a figure in red (with head covering) at the top of the first gate on the left, nearest the three visitors who are at the far left. The gate figure holds a book with black dots to represent writing on it. Note that the tower is square, suggesting that "reont" refers to something else. <hi rend="italic">Charere</hi> (line 9915) means both "chair" (<hi rend="italic">cattedra</hi> in MSI) and "highway" in this text, as confirmed by other Franco-Italian texts. In fact, the gateway is rounded and the human figure is at the highest point. Since this is a scholar with a book, it makes the most sense for him to be in a chair or seat. The portion remaining in the Turin MS (folio 146R) shows a loggia with rounded openings to the left of the illumination, with the three travellers outside to the left. One figure inside (with a fancy headdress) is on a chair with a baldacchino in a polygonal shape (not quite a circle, but circular) above. Since the walls in the Berlin MS illumination reach outside the frame, there is nothing above the figure who is on top of the gate there. It is unclear therefore whether the Turin version is a variation of meaning, but in any case, it is one possible explanation of <hi rend="italic">reont</hi>.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9716.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: ques sont en l'escur aire</note>
    <note xml:id="b9717" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: fi sclaire</note>
   <note xml:id="b9733.1" type="lex" resp="#LZM">See Mainone (<hi rend="italic">Formen</hi>, p. 45);  <hi rend="italic">estieç</hi> is a form of the present here.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9733.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: ert ros</note>
   <note xml:id="b9741" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">aseios</hi> (Mainone <hi rend="italic">Laut</hi>, p. 38): "durstig," 'thirsty'</note>
   <note xml:id="b9744" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">dei</hi>: preposition "de" + plural masculine article in the Italian form.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9746" type="tranns" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: [l]amenta. See line 542 and note.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9749" type="interp" resp="#LZM">T 9405: <hi rend="italic">cosỳ</hi> feze Guielmo a Ugo [...]; clearly the names are here reversed, unless something is missing from the line. </note>
   <note xml:id="b9750" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">sclavine</hi>: type of mantle or cloak. Cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 307, with incomplete definition), but Matsumura, "esclavine," "manteau d'origine slave," "cloak of Slavic origin."></note>
    <note xml:id="b9765" type="trans" resp="#LZM">As Scattolini points out, the verb "bere" [to drink] present in Br and T, is missing here.></note>
   <note xml:id="b9785" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: en le contraire (missing initial "E")</note>
    <note xml:id="b9797" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: pechieç le mostra (MS: lē)</note>
    <note xml:id="b9800" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: que numerable</note>
   <note xml:id="b9801" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: acorcer; her reading would mean "to shorten"</note>
   <note xml:id="b9812" type="refer" resp="#LZM">'oscura valle', <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 29.65</note>
   <note xml:id="b9816" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. Dante, <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 3.03-105.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9821" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">prevonde</hi> = "prevoire" (Mainone, <hi rend="italic">Laut</hi>, p. 36)</note>
   <note xml:id="b9825" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">aubre</hi>: see Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 211), "tree"; but that does not seem to work here</note>
   <note xml:id="b9827" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 'tu is' is scraped out underneath and this is written over.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9838" type="codic" resp="#LZM">There is a dot on the line after <hi rend="italic">noisse</hi> in the MS.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9840" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Hand and ink are different here; tighter writing and the ink smears a bit black.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9841" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">herté</hi>: cf. <hi rend="italic">Geste Francor</hi>, line 6289; critics have been divided between "charity" and "hatred." The source however would be unclear. It cannot be "inheritance" or "heir" here. Mainone (<hi rend="italic">Laut</hi>, p. 18 n1) says this doubtless is confused with "deshaitier," which resolves the issue. Scattolini: heité</note>
   <note xml:id="b9842" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">empuit</hi>: seems to derive from <hi rend="italic">emplir</hi> "to fill," with the vocalisation of the "l" (perhaps by false analogy)</note>
   <note xml:id="b9853" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: ascemble</note>
   <note xml:id="b9869" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 4.31-42. Dante, however, does not have inhabitants in agony, but on "sanza speme vivemo in disio," "without hope we live in desire" (Durling and Martinez, pp. 72-73).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9871" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: for 'qu'el plaisist a Diex om<hi rend="italic">n</hi>ipotent':</note>
   <note xml:id="b9877" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 4.41-42.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9884" type="refer" resp="#LZM">The Harrowing of Hell is here narrated first person by Aeneas, in answer to Huon's question, starting with the next line. Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 4.52 ff.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9890" type="lex" resp="#LZM">MS: se nest devie; Stengel: se 'n est; <hi rend="italic">devie</hi> and <hi rend="italic">encolorie</hi> seem to refer to "substance" which is feminine, though the noun for God is usually masculine. Our interpretation is based on Scattolini (325).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9898" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: de loin iluech mie</note>
   <note xml:id="b9900" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: ne crie</note>
   <note xml:id="b9905" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: il</note>
   <note xml:id="b9915" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The illumination at the bottom of this page is of a city with five towers visible, a figure in red (with head covering) at the top of the first gate on the left, nearest the three visitors who are at the far left. The gate figure holds a book with black dots to represent writing on it. Note that the tower is square, suggesting that <hi rend="italic">reont</hi> refers to something else. <hi rend="italic">Charere</hi> (line 9915) means both "chair" ("cattedra" in MSI) and "highway" in this text, as confirmed by other Franco-Italian texts. In fact, the gateway is rounded and the human figure is at the highest point. Since this is a scholar with a book, it makes the most sense for him to be in a chair or seat.  The portion remaining in the Turin MS (folio 146R) shows a loggia with rounded openings to the left of the illumination, with the three travellers outside to the left. One figure inside (with a fancy headdress) is on a chair with a baldacchino in a polygonal shape (not quite a circle, but circular) above. Since the walls in the Berlin MS illumination reach outside the frame, there is nothing above the figure who is on top of the gate there. It is unclear therefore whether the Turin version is a variation of meaning, but in any case, it is one possible explanation of <hi rend="italic">reont</hi>.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9935.1" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> There are several historical figures by the name Nicomachus to whom this may refer. Aristotle's father and son were both so named; the <title rend="italic">Nichomachean Ethics</title>, a compendium of Aristotle's notes (or Aristotle's notes plus Nichomachus's comments on them) may have been dedicated to the son. Nicomachus of Gerasa, who lived in the first century AD, was a mathematician about whom little is known. His work on the magical properties of numbers and a manual on harmonics, an early discussion of musical theory and pitch. Various other works of his were lost. Since there are references to necromacy in this section, the second identity seems more likely(AEB).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9935.2" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">blastemer</hi>: for the form, see Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, pp. 325-26).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9945" type="interp" resp="#LZM">As Scattolini points out, this version may be inaccurate, since it would be odd for the door opening to be named "Nicomacus"; T gives "anbasadore" instead of "pertus" (note for her lines 1067-66).</note>
   <note xml:id="b9947" type="interp" resp="#LZM">T: Un nome scrisse sopra la porta de sussa</note>
   <note xml:id="b9948" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Scattolini discusses the confusion of this line and the following in the four different versions (note for her lines 1068-69, p. 366). As she notes, it argues for T not deriving from B.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9949" type="interp" resp="#LZM">a l'ep<hi rend="italic">er</hi>dus: Guillaume speaks to Huon and Aeneas.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9950" type="refer" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Farabus</hi>: al-Farabi, a great Arabic philosopher, known as Alpharabius in the West, viewed as the "second master" after Aristotle. He lived in the 9th-10th centuries and was known for scientific (which include mathematical and musical works) and philosophical writings (AEB). </note>
   <note xml:id="b9951" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> See translation for a delineation of speakers in this exchange."</note>
   <note xml:id="b9963" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: a Farabus</note>
   <note xml:id="b9964" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: dialetiche [e] l'autre</note>
   <note xml:id="b9971" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: ni avoir (see introduction on distinguishing pronouns)</note>
   <note xml:id="b9972" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The final letter of "ce<hi rend="italic">r</hi>t " is smeared in the center.</note>
   <note xml:id="b9982" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">sagurament</hi>: cf.  Ital. "sciagura"; <hi rend="italic">sagure</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Aquilon</hi> vol. 3, p. 310), "malheur, accident"</note>
   <note xml:id="b9983" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: quee<hi rend="italic">n</hi>s</note>
   <note xml:id="b9989" type="codic" resp="#LZM">In the ending of the final word, an <hi rend="italic">o</hi> is changed to <hi rend="italic">e</hi> with a line at the bottom of the letter. </note>
    <note xml:id="b9994" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: Forte est</note>
   <note xml:id="b10003" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Scattolini points out that there seems to be an entire line missing following this one: this one is exactly paralle to the Br reading that is followed by "Llo bon conte U[gon] abraça et aplaine" which would obviate the need for presuming a blank in the middle of the following line ('The good count Huon embraced and caressed [aplanir] with his two arms Aeneas who led him').</note>
   <note xml:id="b10004" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The line is complete, but something is clearly missing for the sense here; cf. T: <hi rend="italic">Dize lo [con]te a Eneas, chy lo mena</hi> [The count asks Aeneas, who leads him]. Br similarly reads <hi rend="italic">Dist li quens Ugues ad Eneas qi lo maine</hi> (v. 1117).</note>
   <note xml:id="b10014" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Scattolini divides the conversation differently, rebeginning the quote with this line. We understand "straine" as from the verb <hi rend="italic">estreindre</hi>.</note>
    <note xml:id="b10029" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">e</hi> above the line with caret below.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10037" type="interp" resp="#LZM">This could be either "fit il" or "fit, 'il n'est'" without a difference in meaning.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10043" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini skips this section with French epic heroes, to pick up later, at line 10315.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10051" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">pure</hi> below the line into the edge of the page.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10053" type="codic" resp="#LZM">(e) is in the binding. MS 'oscüe'</note>
   <note xml:id="b10062" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: sc[r](i)pture: <hi rend="italic">i</hi> above the line as abbreviation.</note>
    <note xml:id="b10071" type="interp" resp="#LZM">In this manuscript there are two forms: <hi rend="italic">par poy</hi> (2 appearances) and <hi rend="italic">por poy</hi> (one appearance), but only <hi rend="italic">por</hi> appears with <hi rend="italic">val</hi> and its derivatives. Mixed lists are not unknown, so I have resolved thus here.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10075" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: cu[m] The abbreviation mark here is in the form of a vertical "z"; cf. Viellard, <hi rend="italic">Conseils</hi>, Vol. 1, p. 28, # 11.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10093" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> These are all Saracens from <hi rend="italic">Aspremont</hi>: Agolant is the ruler of the Saracens, father of Helmont, and killed by Girard's nephew Claire. Uliens is one of Agolant's judges, an important Saracen in the second half of the poem, killed by Richier, grandson of Duke Berengier.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10105" type="refer" resp="#LZM">This does not follow the French version of <hi rend="italic">Aspremont</hi>; Roland killed Eaumont (=Helmont=Almonte). There is nothing about Helmont sleeping. See laisses 286-7 in Suard's edition. The sleeping recalls the motif of Roland killing Ferragu in the <hi rend="italic">Entrée d'Espagne</hi>, where Ferragu took a nap using a rock as a pillow, and Roland was tempted to kill him with a stone (vv. 3535-3555).</note>
   <note xml:id="b10108" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Stengel here proposes the emendation <hi rend="italic">(homes)</hi> after .jj. to follow the plot of <hi rend="italic">Aspremont</hi>, where Roland kills Eaumont on the second day of the battle. However, <hi rend="angle">jors</hi> seems more appropriate for that reason. Cf. F. Suard, ed., <hi rend="italic">Aspremont: Chanson de geste du XIIe siècle</hi>, Champion 2008, vv. 3897-5545.</note>
    <note xml:id="b10142" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">canter</hi> has a mark above the 'c', like an apostrophe- meaning unclear, but definitely ink and not a defect in the parchment. T: cercare</note>
   <note xml:id="b10148" type="refer" resp="#LZM">"Death by chessboard" is a chanson de geste motif: in the <hi rend="italic">Geste Francor</hi>, Ogier the Dane kills Charlot, Charlemagne's son, with a chessboard; in <hi rend="italic">Renaut de Montauban</hi>, Bertholet has died thus also, and further incidents appear in the <hi rend="italic">Batârd de Bouillon</hi> and in <hi rend="italic">Parise la duchesse</hi>, but there is no known incident relating to Thibaut killing his brother-in-law Folco in the East. On chess in the Middle Ages and its uses, see Jenny Adams, <hi rend="italic">Power Play: The Literature and Politics of Chess in the Late Middle Ages</hi>, U of Penn P, 2006; Nicholas Perkins, ed., <hi rend="italic">Medieval Romance and Medieval Culture</hi>, D. S. Brewer, 2015. An Italian novella, in fact, insists on Thibaut's family relationship to Guillaume through Folco (married to Anfelise, Thibaut's stepsister, niece of Desramé), <hi rend="italic">I Conti di antichi cavalieri</hi>, ed. Alberto del Monte Cisalpino-Goliardica, 1972, pp. 118-22.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10158" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The illumination at the bottom of this page, 70V, has three parts. Starting at the left, the three men travelling through Hell, Guillaume in front and frontal; Huon to his left and side view; and Aeneas barely visible behind Guillaume's right. In the middle is a lady, side view, in a fancy purple dress with gold decorations; and to the right is a crowned man on a white horse with his sword raised to strike. His trappings are all gold- spurs, saddle, bit. </note>
    <note xml:id="b10177" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: este followed by expunctuated <hi rend="italic">-e</hi>: dots both below and above.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10182" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Guilla[u]me</hi>: there is an abbreviation apostrophe after the two <hi rend="italic">ll</hi>'s, so though the name is usually spelled <hi rend="italic">Guillame</hi> in the text we have added the <hi rend="italic">u</hi> here.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10188" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> Dante, <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>.,3.103-105.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10196" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the first part of the illumination at the foot of 71R: three men are outside a city wall, within which (center) is a knight without a head covering, but a beard and long haïr, in flames. He wears armor covered by a yellow tunic decorated with black G's.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10203" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the second part of the illumination on 71R, to the right. Inside the city wall, devils are pushing that same figure (in yellow with black G's) into a cave opening (Hell, one presumes).</note>   
   <note xml:id="b10206" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Girardo au Fraite [de Vienne] is a chanson de geste character, lord of Burgundy, Milon's brother, father of Rainier, grandfather of Oliver according to the <hi rend="italic">Geste Francor</hi>. He revolted against Charlemagne, refusing to aid him in <hi rend="italic">Aspremont</hi>. René Louis, <hi rend="italic">De l'histoire à la légende</hi>, 3 vols, Imprimerie moderne, 1946-47, proposes various theories about the multiple Girards in chansons de geste. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10225" type="codic" resp="#LZM">After <hi rend="italic">laig</hi>, letter scratched out; again looks like white-out over the spot.</note>   
   <note xml:id="b10233" type="lex" resp="#LZM">We are assuming that <hi rend="italic">camperon</hi> comes from the verb <hi rend="italic">campare</hi>; cf. OF 'eschamper'.</note>
    <note xml:id="b10243" type="refer" resp="#LZM">There are no other forms of this as noun or as adjective. However, the suffix <hi rend="italic">-borg</hi> does appear, where <hi rend="italic">-urg</hi> does not. "The Burgundian" is Girard, lord of Vienne, known not only for his pride but his fierce fighting against the Saracens.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10246" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">non vaut si</hi> is written over a scratch-out.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10247" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The <hi rend="italic">bone</hi> is very hard to read because of a black smear at the top of the folio that almost completely covers it.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10258" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The original could have read "por voir et por semblant"; cf. 2912, 3930, etc. ("por voir") and 2450, 10258, etc., ("por semblant"), something like "truly and seemingly"</note>
   <note xml:id="b10263" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">s'apaser</hi>: for OF "s'apaisier," 'se reconcilier'. One wonders if this should be emended to <hi rend="italic">s'apa<ex rend="angle">rl</ex>er</hi>: he began to discuss/talk with those whom he met. This section is difficult to understand (though clear to read) through the next line. T also is problematic, so the archetype must have been so.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10305" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">po[est]és</hi>: cf. forms of "e[st]" and four other forms of <hi rend="italic">poeste(s)</hi>. T: per fare a luy dalmazo, si aveseno posanza, v. 9959.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10316" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini picks up her transcription again here.</note>
    <note xml:id="b10321" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 8.43-45, where Virgil embraces and kisses Dante for reacting strongly to Filippo Argenti. While Dante does not show Virgil laughing, strong positive emotion is present in both.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10329" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Tisiaus</hi>: Tisias is reported to have been the first theoretician of rhetoric in ancient Greece. It is taken that he was the student of one Corax, who has left no written work. Tradition has it that, after the fall of the monarchy in Sicily in the 5th c. BCE, the rise of democracy occasioned a need for persuasive speech (command no longer being accepted). One successful Sicilian practitioner was Gorgias who went to Athens in 427 BCE, where he became a major figure among the Sophists. In the <title rend="italic">Gorgias</title>, Plato accused rhetoricians of favoring opinion over truth, success in the moment over enduring verities. (See also <title rend="italic">Phaedrus</title> 267a-b.) Thus, in the history of rhetoric, Tisias would stand in the same relationship to rhetoric as the Sophists to sophistry. Support for this view comes in the theory that Corax was not a separate person, but that the word, which means "crow" is actually a derogatory nickname for Tisias himself. Rhetoric received a higher standing with Aristotle, fascinated with how things break down into their component parts, who wrote his <title rend="italic">Rhetoric</title> as an analytical guide to, and practical manual for, the art—but he distinguished it from logic (dialectic). In the later Middle Ages, therefore, Tisias may be taken as a mythical founder, an archetype for all who indulge in untruth for emotional effect. Whatever his reputation in antiquity, in this passage, Berlin, lines 10324-10351, Tisias seems to represent all seven liberal arts (10328). The reference to his singing includes another of the seven: grammar, logic, rhetoric, arithmetic, geometry, astronomy, and music. Wilfred Major, Epicharmus, Tisias, and the Early History of Rhetoric, <title rend="italic">Harvard Studies in Classical Philology</title> 107 (2013), 55-72; A. G. Hinks, "Tisias and Corax and the Invention of Rhetoric," <title rend="Italic">The Classical Quarterly</title> 34,1/2 (Jan.-Apr., 1940), 61-69. (Alan E. Bernstein).</note>
   <note xml:id="b10332" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: canter la usance</note>
   <note xml:id="b10335.1" type="interp" resp="#LZM">This scene may refer to the beginning of the mass; at that era, the "introit involves the singing of a Psalm, which by this period would have been sung alternatingly by two choir bodies." It may be like improvisory practice where "one singer or group of singers would sing the original chant tune, and the other voices might improvise or sing composed counterpoint above it" and "vocal polyphony was used during mass, often with a low line carrying the chant tune, and upper voices providing countermelodies, improvised or otherwise." Where and when it was done and if the celebrant was involved would be difficult to verify since the specific origin of this story is not known. We thank Remi Chiu (Fine Arts (Music), LUM) his collaboration. We also thank Francesca Gambino (U. of Padova) who pointed out that "abis" as an adverb could reflect the  verb "abesse"  ("abaisser") in line 10333, "low(er)." "bis" in its modern sense first appears in the nineteenth century according to DEAF. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10335.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: biscant</note>   
   <note xml:id="b10337" type="codic" resp="#LZM">There appears to have been a <hi rend="italic">saut de même au même</hi> in an original text here, since both B and T repeat the same verb in two lines in a row. The second would be more likely "dit"/"dist" or "fait."</note>
   <note xml:id="b10342" type="interp" resp="#LZM">El = et + il</note>
   <note xml:id="b10345" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Scure</hi> appears twice in the text; obscure or oscure in various forms, seven times. There are no forms with an <hi rend="italic">a-</hi> prefix.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10351" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini: mai<hi rend="italic">n</hi>t [et] en</note>
   <note xml:id="b10353" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The identity of these devils is not positive, but Dante's Flegias appears in Inf. 8; Classical Phlegyas tried to burn down Apollo's temple at Delphi and thus Apollo condemned him to suffer in the afterlife; Ajax committed suicide in shame; Brugier we are not sure about at this time.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10363" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">ras</hi>: Turin has "rasy", shorn, but in OF "ras" can also mean "guilty." That (guilt) however would not be immediately visible to the bystander.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10374" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The construction of this line is somewhat unclear: <hi rend="italic">croie</hi> is clear in the MS; in T the line is also problematic. Cf. line 420, <hi rend="italic">cro ge</hi>.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10379" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Scattolini ends a quote here, but the beginning is not clear.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10380" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">hoeç</hi> is written over a scratch out.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10382" type="trans" resp="#LZM">End of Scattolini's transcription.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10385" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Illumination at the bottom of 72R illustrates this scene; at the left the three travellers through Hell, Huon, St. William and Aeneas, led by Huon. To the right, naked figures are lifted by a devil with fire around (v. 10396); below, in a pool of blue, other naked figures with a dragon and little fires. Above the devil at top in middle, the initial 'R' in white on the blue upper portion, for Roger (v. 10401).</note>
   <note xml:id="b10394" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. the devils in pitch of <hi rend="italic">Inf</hi>. 21-22, esp. 22.131, 'falcon [...]' </note>
   <note xml:id="b10402" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">stoit</hi> appears 37 times; and only one other time might there be <hi rend="italic">istoit</hi>, line 2684 (see note at that line). Thus we interpret here as "qui stoit". Cf. Turin 10054,"<hi rend="italic">Ora me con</hi>ta ch'è stà lo tuo pecato"</note>
   <note xml:id="b10406" type="biblio" resp="#LZM">See Meregazzi, p. 34. </note>
    <note xml:id="b10456" type="refer" resp="#LZM">MS: toe. This is oddly formed- looks like 'tor' since final letter partially behind second.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10476" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the subject of the illumination at the bottom of 72V. To the left are our three travelling figures, with Aeneas at the front this time; in the middle is a king on horseback, with gold crown and leggings, completely covered with armor and decorations; his horse is also covered with a blue cloth decorated with two lions rampant. The king holds a lance inclined up. To the right are two naked figures with bloody holes. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10477" type="codic" resp="#LZM">A spot on the MS here is over the last letter; it looks like a round candle wax spot scraped off (it does not go through the folio).</note>
   <note xml:id="b10478" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The <hi rend="italic">Roman d'Alexandre</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Alexander Romance</hi>) is quite important in <hi rend="italic">Huon</hi> for its voyages into the East and for its moral commentary. Alexandre tried to rule the world and the air and seas, which was frequently construed as overreaching. For a summary of the story and information about the various versions, the basic reference work is George Cary, <hi rend="italic">The Medieval Alexander</hi> (Cambridge UP, 1956; rpt. 1967). A more recent compendium is David Zuwiyya's <hi rend="italic">A Companion to Alexander Literature in the Middle Ages</hi> (Brill, 2011).  For specific influences, see Meregazzi (1937); for further bibliography, see Morgan (2015).</note>
    <note xml:id="b10501.1" type="refer" resp="#LZM">VV. 10501-10103 reproduced and translated in Vidossi (Origini pp. 1214-1215), without capitals except at the beginning of sentences.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10501.2" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Note the assonance in this laisse, as opposed to rhyme generally found.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10509" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">estandre</hi>: Holtus in <hi rend="italic">Aliscans</hi> defines "estandre" as Italian “estendere," which means  'to extend, stretch,' and in his <hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi> (p. 278) equates it with "destendre," meaning 'to kill' among other things.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10511" type="ling" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">alâ vendre</hi>: "alla a vendre": in Italian, "andare" is constructed with the preposition before an infinitive. It is not clear whether or not that preposition would be present here. The few forms followed by an infinitive are split between its presence and its absence, and a number are like this case here, where the infinitive also starts with an "a." </note>
   <note xml:id="b10513" type="refer" resp="#LZM">This is not, of course, the <hi rend="italic">Chanson de Roland</hi>'s fate for Ganelon, where he is torn apart by horses only. There, it is his thirty oath-swearers who are hanged. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10516" type="interp" resp="#LZM">This statement fits with the Dantean configuration of hell, where Lucifer and other traitors are at the deepest point, furthest from heaven.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10525" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The MS hand is slightly different here: abbreviation lines are shorter, writing tighter through the end of this column. Last reference to Aeneas is in this line. Vidossi and Aresi reproduce and translate into Italian (<hi rend="italic">Origini</hi> pp. 1214- 1218, even pages). </note>
   <note xml:id="b10526" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the scene of the illumination at the bottom of 73. Three men to the left, led this time by St. Guillaume, with Aeneas standing to the back, in front of a hairy devil on a bench. The devil is in chains crossed across his chest and holding his legs together; he holds a crown in his right hand and a ring in his left. There are other similar devils behind him holding spears and pastoral cruxes (like the papal one). </note>
   <note xml:id="b10574" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Vidossi: l'en feise "se così facessi, molti agirei malamente" = 'if I did that, I would act very badly.' But this is not supported by the MS reading because of the verb ending. The line could be emended to "ovr<ex rend="angle">e</ex>ra<ex rend="angle">i</ex>s" for raise syllable count to 6+6 (cf. line 2218).</note>  
    <note xml:id="b10582" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Note that this is the one of the three gifts comprising the tribute that is not illustrated in the illumination on 73R. </note>
    <note xml:id="b10599" type="biblio" resp="#LZM">End of Vidossi and Arese's transcription and translation. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10606" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: paus: not attested in other Franco-Italian texts in this collocation. T reads "pasy", 'passes'. We emend to "païs"; perhaps <hi rend="italic">a saut de même au même</hi>, seeing <hi rend="italic">crueus</hi> afterward.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10619" type="ling" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">la ci</hi>: this is an unusual construction, appearing nowhere else in the MS. It would seem to be direct object (referring to food) plus adverbial "there." </note>
   <note xml:id="b10628" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> There is no abbreviation in the MS.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10652" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">faigé</hi> : this may be a lenited form of "fatigué": intervocalic t>d>ø. It is not found in RIALFrI (14.IV.19). Cf. lines 1965, 11142, <hi rend="italic">faigeç</hi> (equivalents in T: <hi rend="italic">fadigà; afinato</hi> [<hi rend="italic">afiné</hi> = "épuisé," Matsumura]).</note>
   <note xml:id="b10664" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The first part of illumination, 74R, bottom: hairy devil carrying Huon at table through the air. He's sleeping on the table, with various things on the table. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10670" type="biblio" resp="#LZM">End of Stengel's "Hollen...," v. 10827.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10671" type="biblio" resp="#LZM">Begin Stengel's "Karl Martel's Enführung," his v. 10828.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10681" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">quasa</hi>: the word in this particular form does not seem to appear in other Franco-Italian texts or in commentary about Huon. It appears to be a variant spelling of "casser," here in the reflexive form. Matsumura documents both the abstract sense (WatrS, <hi rend="italic">quasse</hi>) and the reflexive, but not together (as does T-L). Other appearances in Franco-Italian, while spelled with the same initial form, generally refer to physical combat (RIALFrI). T-L: REW <hi rend="italic">quassare.</hi>However, there is a typical Franco-Italian verb that is reflexive: <hi rend="italic">squassare</hi>, "to shake up, to shake violently"; cf. <hi rend="italic">Aquilon de Bavière</hi>, vol. 3, p. 321, and entries in RIALFrI for "squaserent" (all "soi" or "se squaserent").</note>
   <note xml:id="b10692" type="interp" resp="#LZM">This section is somewhat comic, showing Huon as a naïf, not unlike Charlemagne in the Geste Francor, who marvels that someone (in his case, an angel) managed to get into the royal tent.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10699" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel emends to <hi rend="italic">[tres]tot</hi>; he emends to relate to Rajna's transcription of T. It would increase the syllable count to 12. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10706" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">fron</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 331). In F-I, <hi rend="italic">fron</hi> is feminine, under influence of Ital. "fronte." This and the one in v. 8886 are the only examples of six appearances where it might construed as feminine. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10715" type="codic" resp="#LZM">In the second part of the illumination below, Huon is inside a house by a window with grey outside, and his head is still on table, sleeping. Food items are on the table, including a partially-full glass, a flask of liquid, rolls and various containers. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10723" type="codic" resp="#LZM">A fold in the MS runs through these three lines, across "moiller," "encontrer," "Nul" </note>
   <note xml:id="b10743" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> MS: sa moitist. There is no lexical item like this elsewhere in this text. The closest possibility in OF dictionaries seems to be "amoistir," to dampen, thus our word division. Looking elsewhere in the text we find "moit" (v. 7121) from "to move"; Matsumura lists "amovoir" but not reflexive form; T-L lists a possibly reflexive "movoir." If this were the case, it would signify "to gesticulate" as the text suggests already when he begs for pardon (v. 10730). The following tears and frequent expressions elsewhere about his dampening himself with tears make that seem more attractive as a possibility. We thank our consultants for their suggestions here.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10758" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The "que" or other conjunction seems to be missing here; cf. T 10413, "el no[n] pare ch'el sapia parlare [...]"</note>
   <note xml:id="b10762" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: aspë; T 10417: aspeto. There is no form "asper" or "aspre" as a noun; however, see l. 9352, <hi rend="italic">sper</hi>, so we are interpreting this as a form of "esper" (cf. TL "esperer," "esperance"; Matsumura "espoire, espere" fem., F-I, "esperance" <hi rend="italic">Entrée</hi>).</note>
   <note xml:id="b10765" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Cf. l. 1591, when Huon recalls knowing Sanson's father at Carcassonne. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10768" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: Or(e), to reduce syllable count to 12.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10781" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: [au]tresi</note>
   <note xml:id="b10790" type="inter" resp="#LZM">This is a problematic line; <hi rend="italic">ator</hi>; DEAF "condition, état"; T-L: Stand, Zustand; Matsumura: condition; caractère; équipement; entourage; parure. Cf. line 12049. The meaning here is unclear, as is the word division; the MS reads a separation "la tor"; T 10446 reads similarly, "la tore." Since final consonants are frequently lost, here it may be equivalent to "la torne," defined in Matsumura "dédommagement," 'compensation'. Again, we thank our consultants for assisting with this line. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10796" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: Qu(ant)' a</note>
   <note xml:id="b10797" type="inter" resp="#LZM">Stengel: Ce (n)est [de] l'enfer che je ay che[rché] segnor (based on T); che can also signify "ce" and since with it the line is 10 syllables, should be considered as a possibility. It could also be missing a final consonant: <ex rend="brackets">cher</ex> = "that I hold dear." </note>
   <note xml:id="b10800" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: Conseler [vos] devéç</note>
   <note xml:id="b10807" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: [nul] autre</note>
   <note xml:id="b10819" type="inter" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">afeitement</hi>: while OF <hi rend="italic">afaitement</hi> has the standard definition of "arrangement, appearance, or construction" (cf. Matsumura, T-L), or a "collection of graceful qualities"  (DEAF-él), Italian also has the sense of "enchanted thing"; cf. DELI for <hi rend="italic">affatturare</hi>, "to put under a spell; to alter, falsify'/counterfit" already in the fourteenth century (before Dante). This seems to be the sense here, 'magical creation/origin.' </note>
   <note xml:id="b10833" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: (le) respont</note>
   <note xml:id="b10844" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: Parler [ge] voil</note>
   <note xml:id="b10856" type="inter" resp="#LZM"> MS: se smoue. Forms of <hi rend="italic">smou</hi> appear 4 times, esmou 3 times. Since the two are separated in the MS and there is no overwhelming evidence either way, we print here in two words.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10857" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: qui (qu')</note>
   <note xml:id="b10863" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: "[que] soit ... </note>
   <note xml:id="b10864" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: chier[e] </note>
   <note xml:id="b10871" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: furent [il] </note>
   <note xml:id="b10872" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: main [ont] tenue </note>
   <note xml:id="b10893" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: l'afer[e]</note>
    <note xml:id="b10903" type="inter" resp="#LZM">el = et + il </note>
   <note xml:id="b10907" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: [e]n avray</note>
   <note xml:id="b10914" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: De [ce] qu'il dit non [le] croit il nïent </note>
   <note xml:id="b10920" type="interp" resp="#LZM">This line is a bit confusing, and T does not help; it seems to be "that you come out underneath" literally; the same is true for T 10571.</note>
   <note xml:id="b10922" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> Stengel: Cuides [tu]</note>
    <note xml:id="b10938" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: Va [tost]</note>
   <note xml:id="b10939" type="codic" resp="#LZM">(i) above the line with caret below. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10941" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the scene illustrated in the illumination of 75V: At Charles's court (from left to right), the devil in the form of a pilgrim and Huon (with a red beard and lots of hair) extend a red cloth with golden birds on it. The king sits on a dais, crowned under a backdrop of white with red at the top. Several armed soldiers are at the far right beside the throne. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10944" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: Nus ni p[o]oit </note>
   <note xml:id="b10954" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> Stengel concludes this line with (!?)</note>
   <note xml:id="b10958" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Again a spot at the end of this line, circular perhaps originally a drop of wax now removed? </note>
     <note xml:id="b10968" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: [Si] tost </note>
   <note xml:id="b10969" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the scene of the illumination here on 76R: At Charles Martel's court still with Huon in bourgeois clothes to the left with some soldiers, to the right other soldiers with another bourgeois, and in the middle above Charles Martel on the red cloth decorated with gold birds, held up by haïry devils some red and some blue-gray. Crown is the same as in previous illumination, and the ring is not in presence either. </note>
   <note xml:id="b10994" type="ling" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">sorjugie</hi> seems to be a scribal error for "forjugie"; cf. line 8212. </note>
   <note xml:id="b11001" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): Cest[uy]</note>
   <!--checking notes to here
 <note xml:id="b" type="" resp="#LZM"></note>
 -->
 <note xml:id="b11003" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): (en)ça, le autre (en) la</note>
 <note xml:id="b11004" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): nos (il) doit</note>
 <note xml:id="b11009" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): por (nulle) rien que sie</note>
 <note xml:id="b11031" type="inter" resp="#LZM">Perhaps to be emended to "Jusqu'un anç"?</note>
 <note xml:id="b11032" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung") : Iloch (il) sera</note>
 <note xml:id="b11041" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: redue. Cf. <hi rend="italic">duire</hi> (TL), and Ital <hi rend="italic">ridurre</hi>, past particple <hi rend="italic">ridotto</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b11057" type="codic" resp="#LZM">As usual, the "or" is written above the roman numeral. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11069" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Initial 'D' of this line the reverse of spot mentioned on 76R. The left side of the <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is scraped or light. It would appear to be candle wax: the parchment page is thin and one can see through. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11072" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: laë, the two vowels are written as a ligature sharing the right side of the <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and the left side of the e; it seems to be a correction. Since the reference is to a choice, a process-- <hi rend="italic">ovrement</hi>–we write <hi rend="italic">le</hi>. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11073" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel: s'[il] avront feit </note>
 <note xml:id="b11077" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): vos dir[e] m'oëç</note>
 <note xml:id="b11086" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): fust [tot] doneç</note>
 <note xml:id="b11109" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): p[o]oit </note>
 <note xml:id="b11125" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): [a vos] par moy</note>
 <note xml:id="b11130" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">ferçay</hi>: seems to be from "forcir" rather than "fercir" which is only attested in reflexive forms. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11147" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): vit, (puis) merveille</note>
 <note xml:id="b11164" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): [a]gusté</note>
 <note xml:id="b11191" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): [re]grace</note>
 <note xml:id="b11196" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung"): [de] tot</note> 
 <note xml:id="b11208" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This folio, though a verso, is highly decorated; with the laisse "Segno<hi rend="italic">r</hi>, seeç e<hi rend="italic">n</hi> pais..." it is like the beginning of a new chanson de geste, with a large and gilded capital, along with marginal color in red, green, blue, and gold. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11213" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 887): sauç; the MS reads clearly <hi rend="italic">sanç</hi>, but the first letter has some sort of marking (similar to the abbreviation with <hi rend="italic">p</hi>) </note>
 <note xml:id="b11216" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 887): christï[e]ntie</note>
 <note xml:id="b11223" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 887): miller [que]'n</note>
 <note xml:id="b11224" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 887): Paris[e]</note>
 <note xml:id="b11226" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 887): il (i) vent ... barnie</note>
 <note xml:id="b11227" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 887): demorent (et) a</note>
 <note xml:id="b11230" type="codic" resp="#LZM">There is an 'x' marked between this verse and the next in the right margin. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11237" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">balaor</hi>: listed by Holtus under <hi rend="italic">bailir</hi>, "donner," bailior, "conducteur" (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, 227-28), but see <hi rend="italic">Guerra d'Attila</hi>, "baleor: palco, balcone" and <hi rend="italic">Entrée d'Espagne</hi>, "baucons: balcone". T reads "baladore" in lines 10886, 10887. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11241" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 888): [oit] parlee</note>
 <note xml:id="b11243" type="ling" resp="#LZM">Note that this one form is not in sight rhyme in this laisse. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11249" type="codic" resp="#LZM">line after <hi rend="italic">al</hi> and before <hi rend="italic">balaor</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b11260" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Capital 'D' with a face drawn in it. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11262" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">bufoy</hi>: cf. <hi rend="italic">Guerra d'Attila</hi></note>
 <note xml:id="b11270" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 889): Jer(u)salem</note>
 <note xml:id="b11274" type="refer" resp="#LZM">See note for line 1643.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11284" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 889): (elle) venoit</note>
 <note xml:id="b11287" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">r</hi> above the line with no caret below, but it seems to be the same handwriting. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11289" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 889): un(e) jor</note>
 <note xml:id="b11310" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">garpu</hi>: cf. "guerpir," 'to abandon' (T-L); Entrée d'Espagne; Niccolò da Verona</note>
 <note xml:id="b11315" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 890): [e]lecion</note>
 <note xml:id="b11317" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 890): s'[è] moüe </note>
 <note xml:id="b11336" type="interp" resp="#LZM">We are interpreting <hi rend="italic">conostre</hi> as an imperative here.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11349" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">trovâ tant</hi> for "trova atant"</note>
 <note xml:id="b11352" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 891): tot[e] jant</note>
 <note xml:id="b11354" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 891): doneor (de) convoitisse</note>
 <note xml:id="b11359" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The <hi rend="italic">-en-</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Veneç</hi> is in a circular brown spot, which does not seem to be wax (it does not go through the parchment). This section is illustrated in the illumination here on 78V: to the left are Huon in his recognizable yellow outfit, together with a group of men; in the center is a raised platform made of wood (with balustrade around above like the supports below), with two scenes also. In the first, the archbishop (distinguished by his red robes and typical white ... hat with a red cross) crowns the king (William), who is bearded and long-haïred; in the second, to the right, William marries Belisor—they are holding hands and she is accompanied by other women. Below the raised platform, on the right, are other men, two bearded, two not. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11367" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 891): tot[e] celle</note>
 <note xml:id="b11368" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic"> empois</hi>: we are presuming this is from "empeser"; cf. Godefroy's and Matsumura's citation of <title rend="Italic">Anticlaudianus</title>, defined, "appuyer fortement." It appears as one word in the MS.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11373" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Entführung," p. 891): oit (a) non</note>
 <note xml:id="b11377" type="biblio" resp="#LZM"> End Stengel, "Karl Martel's Entführung", v. 11534. Begin Stengel's "Schluss", v. 11535.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11379" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 267): Por</note>
 <note xml:id="b11392" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 268): esillé. But cf. the preceding line: [...] asige, [...] prendront, where a singular and plural verb </note>
 <note xml:id="b11393" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 268): fuiç ont</note>
 <note xml:id="b11395" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">gardenaus</hi>: cf. Holtus (Lexicalische, pp. 335-36), "cardinal." </note>
 <note xml:id="b11409" type="interp" resp="#LZM">In Italian, "adire" means specifically "to go to [legal means], to sue"; thus this seems to imply some legal application. </note>
 <!--restart note check here -->
 <note xml:id="b11416" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> This is not a sight rhyme.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11439" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">oit</hi> could be either from "to have" or from "to hear"; since this is rhyme position, there is no dieresis, whichever meaning it holds. Turin uses a form of "to hear."</note>
 <note xml:id="b11462" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This line and the next are out in the margin in line with the capital below. To the left is a large parenthesis around the two with a cross in the margin to the left of it. Should they be reversed? </note>
 <note xml:id="b11472" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">-ç </hi> of <hi rend="italic">sanç</hi> was changed from 't'. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11481" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 270): adex en</note>
 <note xml:id="b11492" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 270): Ançois</note>
 <note xml:id="b11496" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">m</hi> above the roman numeral 'iiii' as usual.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11498" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 270): reciut (see introduction)</note>
 <note xml:id="b11540" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p.272): v'erent</note>
 <note xml:id="b11546" type="edit" resp="#LZM">The only full forms of this name are <hi rend="italic">Willame</hi>, but there are two similar appearances of <hi rend="italic">Guilla[u]me</hi>. We resolve the abbreviation <hi rend="italic">W'ill'ame</hi> here like those.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11547" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">despacer</hi>: cf. 8091, <hi rend="italic">despaiç</hi> (cf. Wünderli, <hi rend="italic">Aquilon</hi>, vol. 3, p. 268). The beginning of the quote is unclear; it could possibly begin with this line and follow to the next. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11556" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 272): en promis</note>
 <note xml:id="b11569" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">deruer</hi> in OF is listed as transitive (Matsumura; T-L), and is transitive in the GdA; however, DELI lists the Italian reflex form (deriving from the same etymon), <hi rend="italic">dirupare</hi> (first attested in Boccaccio, ca. 1336), as intransitive, and through lenition this could be the form here. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11570" type="edit" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">ên</hi> = "et en"</note>
 <note xml:id="b11580" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS, Stengel ("Roms," p. 273): lay; MS: lay</note>
 <note xml:id="b11583" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">D(i)ex</hi>: the <hi rend="italic">i</hi> above the line (with no caret below) was clearly intended, but same ink and nib. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11584" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The illumination at the bottom of 80R relates to the fighting in the streets of Rome. The entire scene is within city walls, with a siege engine off to the extreme left (evident by its wood supporting structure in contrast to the continuous city walls). In the center is a religious figure in clerical garb giving a blessing with his right hand raised, two fingers out; he faces his right (our left). There are no recognizable figures in the fighting, all are in Western armor garb, with faces / necks covered (so no beards evident) and in armor, with no distinguishable armor covers. Some horses are also present. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11586" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: mërent. The two dots normally stand for an <hi rend="italic">r</hi> plus a vowel, but here an <hi rend="italic">r</hi> is already present. Turin l. 11222: Allor de speto li metono, followed by a description of broken trunks and clothes thrown out. Stengel: merrent </note>
 <note xml:id="b11599" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 273): feit é a escïent</note>
 <note xml:id="b11601" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 273): mil[ler]</note>
 <note xml:id="b11611" type="refer" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">trepas de vent</hi>: Cf. Dante's <hi rend="italic">Purg.</hi> 11.100-102: "Non è il mondan romore altro ch'un fiato/ di vento, ch'or vien quinci e or vien quindi,/ e muta nome perché muta lato."</note>
 <note xml:id="b11623" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 274): Fetes</note>
 <note xml:id="b11627" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 274): que [non] feront asé</note>
 <note xml:id="b11640" type="edit" resp="#LZM">Âlemans: "a Alemans"</note>
 <note xml:id="b11645" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 274): Cuide [lor] fer</note>
 <note xml:id="b11660.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">deivent</hi>: the MS minim links cannot be clearly distinguished; there are many forms in <hi rend="italic">doiv-</hi>, and none in <hi rend="italic">deiv-</hi> for "devoir" we interpret thus.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11660.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 275): devïent </note>
 <note xml:id="b11663" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 275): mil[le] </note>
 <note xml:id="b11668" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 275): cinque cent. Note the use of the long-n type abbreviation after "cq" in "cīncq" </note>
 <note xml:id="b11670" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 275): l'un [fu] rois; he adds another line after this, based on Turin: [E l'autre fu le rois de Lombardie gent,] </note>
 <note xml:id="b11674" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 275): et [il] lor</note>
 <note xml:id="b11681" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 275): ben voilent</note>
 <note xml:id="b11689" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 276): A(le)</note>
 <note xml:id="b11701" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 276): mill(er) [bel et fer]– emended based on Turin</note>
 <note xml:id="b11712" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">qi </hi>inserted with caret at line level; very tiny writing. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11731" type="codic" resp="#LZM">In the left margin is a small <hi rend="italic">x</hi> in front of this line. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11734" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is above the roman numeral, as usual. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11760" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms" p. 277): A celuy [pont] </note>
 <note xml:id="b11763" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> The illumination at the bottom of 81V shows the battle outside the city, with the city walls to the left and two groups confronting each other on horseback. On the center left, there is a brown horse with a red cover, gold lions on it; to the right is a white horse with a green blanket covered with a flowered design. Above this, a man's head (with reddish-brown beard) is upside-down, presumably cut off. It is interesting that though foot-soldiers and archers are mentioned with each group none are illustrated.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11765" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms" p. 278): gard(e)</note>
 <note xml:id="b11774" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">a</hi> inserted above the line with caret below. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11780" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 278): et il [fu] quart </note>
  <note xml:id="b11796" type="interp" resp="#LZM">el = "et" + "el"; chataille (Mainone, Laut p. 14): "catagne, cataine (<ex rend="angle">capitaneus</ex>)?"</note>
 <note xml:id="b11809.1" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 279): Ugon [li] ançoner</note>
 <note xml:id="b11809.2" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">ançoner</hi>:while the meaning to the term seems clear, locating a specific origin is difficult. In the <hi rend="italic">Geste Francor</hi> one finds "ançioner," which Mussafia, in the phrase "non sia ançoner" interprets "non sia tenuto in onore" [not held in honor], deriving it from <hi rend="italic">ancien</hi>, so literally here, "the most senior." Another alternative is that it might be derived from "ancone" : in T-L this is a banner with the Virgin Mary on it ( from Greek eikon); ançoner would be the banner-carrier, the leader (cf. Matsumura, "ancoine"). Or finally, it could derive from <hi rend="italic">ainçois, ançois</hi> for "first," here with a suffix, so the first, the leader (<hi rend="italic">ainz</hi> takes numerous combinations and -<hi rend="italic">er</hi> is a typical Franco-Italian suffix, particularly for a person; cf. Holtus, <hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi> p. 99, p. 115). </note>
 <note xml:id="b11837" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Perhaps <hi rend="italic">sent</hi> = 'sait'? See Turin. Then it would translate to something like: "It was the pope who knew about it." The problem exists because of what the pope had promised the Germans when he was desperate. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11841" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 280): Petit (en); for <hi rend="italic">romanent</hi>, cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 424).</note>
 <note xml:id="b11842" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 280): [et] si</note>
 <note xml:id="b11846" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 280): mil[ler]</note>
 <note xml:id="b11848" type="codic" resp="#LZM">(t) above the line with caret below</note>
 <note xml:id="b11853" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 280): Mout [il] li regreta</note>
 <note xml:id="b11860" type="codic" resp="#LZM">'le' is followed by an expunctuated 's'</note>
 <note xml:id="b11862" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The abbreviation mark above the 'p' seems more like a random ink spot.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11872" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 280): a lor</note>
 <note xml:id="b11873" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 280): (de)robant</note>
 <note xml:id="b11880" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 281): Cit ait</note>
 <note xml:id="b11885" type="codic" resp="#LZM">'l' inserted before 'hostel' in the reddish-purple ink of the rubrication, with a caret below in the same. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11895" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> escont: cf. Holtus (Lexicalische, p. 309), on the difficulty of distinguishing escondre, "to hide," from escondire, to refuse.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11901" type="codic" resp="#LZM">At the top of the upstroke of the 'h' in 'Franchois' is a wormhole.</note>
 <note xml:id="b11905" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 281): mil [homes]</note>
 <note xml:id="b11911" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The illumination at the bottom of this 82V shows the confrontation of the pope. The pope is in red in the middle, with his right hand raised. He is on a throne. To his right (viewer's left) is a very short king in a crown dressed in blue, with his arms crossed and men behind him, swords drawn. To the right (pope's left) are other men, also with swords, the second one with his half-way out of the sheath. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11913" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms" p. 281): [A] cestuy</note>
 <note xml:id="b11918" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">faice</hi>: we are interpreting this as a present indicative, following the usage of T, though Mainone lists it as a present subjunctive (), and the other three forms are. Here however, it's difficult to join an active present optative with the third person for sense. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11920" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms" p. 282): bien [com] la</note>
 <note xml:id="b11923" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms" p. 282): et [tot] le pople</note>
 <note xml:id="b11929" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This line is so long that the final -r is in the initial 'L' of the second column. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11930" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms" p. 282): tant ge[nt] erent</note>
 <note xml:id="b11956" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Âlemans</hi>: a Alemans</note>
 <note xml:id="b11958" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 283): lor [gent]</note>
 <note xml:id="b11964.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM">'i' expunctuated between 'o' and 's' of 'Apostoille </note>
 <note xml:id="b11964.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 283): Laison ester</note>
 <note xml:id="b11968" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 283): qu(a)' avons</note>
 <note xml:id="b11969" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 283): voudro ge; for voudrouge as conditional, see Mainone (Formen, p. 34). </note>
 <note xml:id="b11971" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 283): ques(i) poit</note>
 <note xml:id="b11973" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 283): jons. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 355), gives this as a form of "joindre" meaning "venir," "to come," that appears in Franco-Italian. T gives "zonse", "to join" (cf. MSI 'giunse'). However, with two syllables (as in i ons) the line is a decasyllable, and "i" appears frequently as 'there' in this text. There is no connection between the "i" and the "o": compare ior and several other combinations in the column to the left. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11976" type="trans" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">E·n</hi> = "e(o) un" </note>
 <note xml:id="b11979" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">chantons</hi>: cf. OF "chant; canton" (T-L), MSI "canto; accanto"</note>
 <note xml:id="b11986" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 283): ci en sons; the MS writes "ensons" together. </note>
 <note xml:id="b11990" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 283): deu por reclamoit</note>
 <note xml:id="b11991" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 284): que la voit </note>
 <note xml:id="b11993" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 284): cristinté </note>
 <note xml:id="b12000" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Toit</hi> here for "tout"; also in 12007 below. Cf. <hi rend="italic">Aquilon de Bavière,</hi> vol. 3 (Glossary). </note>
 <note xml:id="b12009" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 284): saçe bien avant: Si por</note>
 <note xml:id="b12017" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 284): v'avendroit. The two downstrokes seem more linked at the top than the bottom. In either case, the meaning is not that different: "would come to you all" vs. "would come from it." </note>
   <note xml:id="b12040" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 285): robé furant; laus we are understanding as a form of "louer" / "lodare"</note>
   <note xml:id="b12041" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 285): teaçon</note>
   <note xml:id="b12056" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 285): pap' e empereor; êmpereror here = e empereor</note>
   <note xml:id="b12064" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 285): moire (et) li</note>
   <note xml:id="b12075" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 285): Da (la) part ... (fu) .iiii. ...</note>
   <note xml:id="b12079" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms" p 286): fu l'un, son</note>
   <note xml:id="b12084" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms" p. 286): part (le) fu</note>
   <note xml:id="b12094" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 286): doviant</note>
   <note xml:id="b12096" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 286): respondrent: « Si er lor ovremant» .</note>
   <note xml:id="b12097" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 286): veiseç</note>
   <note xml:id="b12104.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The illumination here on 83V is the <hi rend="italic">ordalie</hi>, the judicial combat: inside a palisade, two groups are fighting. To the left is the pope with two other clerics, one in white and one in red. To the right is a stylized tree (outside the palisade enclosure). </note>
    <note xml:id="b12104.2" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">stange</hi>: cf. DELI "stanga," 'long, wooden pole' used for the two sides of a cart to place horses, or to divide stalls in a barn (med. Lat in Bologn, 1253; Boccaccio 1348-53), <hi rend="italic">Geste Francor</hi>, poles used to hit others.</note>
   <note xml:id="b12106" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the hair side of the parchment and in this section, the pores are visible and make reading more difficult.</note>
   <note xml:id="b12107" type="codic" resp="#LZM">T: Combatre deno y[n]semele; de bon gra li pr<hi rend="italic">ende</hi>; Ms: pnat, an initial abbreviation line over the 'p' and then one also over the 'a. </note>
   <note xml:id="b12108" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 287): [se] saigne (soy)</note>
   <note xml:id="b12121" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 287): i sofer; T 11752: <hi rend="italic">entrate no[n] fono molto, mé y[n]tra tute fereno</hi></note>
   <note xml:id="b12124" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 287): vient (a) l'encontrer</note>
   <note xml:id="b12127" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The final word here is in the margin; 'cō' is readable, but the 't' with the 'r' above is inside the binding and only visible in person.</note>
   <note xml:id="b12136" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 287): li guerer</note>
   <note xml:id="b12151" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 288): preu [a]complirons</note>
   <note xml:id="b12153" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: li requier; possible emendation:<ex rend="angle">s</ex>i requier = they attacked each other</note>
   <note xml:id="b12155" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">çambeler</hi>: champeler = combattre, 'to fight' (Matsumura); cf. T-L champel, champal</note>
   <note xml:id="b12158" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">emplaier</hi>: cf. Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi>, p. 297), "couvrir de plaies," "to cover with wounds."</note>
   <note xml:id="b12167" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The illumination at the bottom of 84R shows the end of the combat: in the same palisade, the pope and various other men (not the clerks in 83V) are in the middle, with one armed man lying to the left and one to the right, on piles of armor/men. To the viewer's left is a man in a red surcoat with a golden lion; his eyes are closed. To the viewer's right lies a man with a yellow surcoat over his armor; it has black imperial eagles on it. His eyes are open. </note>
   <note xml:id="b12176" type="ttrans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 288): navré, amor diex a lor ...</note>
   <note xml:id="b12178" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">douent</hi> from 'dotere, doër/douër' "pouvoir d'un bien, d'une qualité," "to endow."</note>
   <note xml:id="b12183" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 289): cum poit</note>
   <note xml:id="b12186" type="lex" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">joïsse</hi>: Cf . Holtus (<hi rend="italic">Lexicalische</hi> pp. 356-57), "jugement"</note>
   <note xml:id="b12196" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Under <hi rend="italic">pde</hi>, above <hi rend="italic">cristenté</hi>, a wormhole in the MS.</note>
   <note xml:id="b12198" type="interp" resp="#LZM">It is unclear whom the poet might have in mind for reconquering the Empire from the Germans in 100 years (Turin gives  400 years). Giovanni Villani's <hi rend="italic">Nuova Cronica</hi> (ed. by Giuseppe Porta [ Parma: Fondazione Pietro Bembo / Ugo Guanda, 1991]; e-text downloaded 10 June 2018,   https://www.liberliber.it/mediateca/libri/v/villani/nuova_cronica/pdf/nuova__p.pdf) which dates to the beginning of the fourteenth century, mentions various rulers named "Carlo Martello," and it is a recurring name in the Anjou family. The <hi rend="italic">Cronica</hi> notes that Charlemagne's family ceased ruling at the time of Ugo Ciapetta, Duca d'Orliensa. It tells of a Carlo Martello in the 1280's (pp. 200 ff), who, by his actions in the southern portion of the Italian peninsula and Sicily, seems to refer to the Charles Martel who lived 1271-95. The Anjou family in the peninsula in any case was very important, so either this reference or that of Turin may be linked to the French royal family in the peninsula at the time of the poem.</note>
   <note xml:id="b12209.1" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Tobler includes these lines to the end (p. 606).</note>
   <note xml:id="b12209.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 289): (I)ci</note>
   <note xml:id="b12210" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Tobler: perdon</note>
    <note xml:id="b12213.1" type="codic" resp="#LZM">A large blot on this line, from <hi rend="italic">-vre a- </hi> that also goes down to the following line onto the top of the date.</note>
 <note xml:id="b12213.2" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Stengel ("Roms," p. 289): D'escrivre</note>
 <note xml:id="b12214" type="trans" resp="#LZM">Tobler: ans (omits abbreviation)</note>
  <note xml:id="b12216" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: Julli (capitalized in the MS)</note>
  <note xml:id="b12224" type="codic" resp="#LZM">There is a blank line before the 'Amen' s that starts in 2.5 cm from the normal left margin.</note>
   </div>
 </body>
 </text>
</TEI>