<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Huon d'Auvergne, Turin Biblioteca Nazionale Universitaria N III 19 (T)</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name xml:id="LZM">Leslie Zarker Morgan</name>
                    <resp>Annotations</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Washington and Lee University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Lexington, Virginia</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xml:lang="en">
                    <!-- xml:id ??? See Cummings 52 -->
                    <!-- add encodingDesc -->
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>Italy</country>
                        <settlement>Turin</settlement>
                        <repository>Biblioteca Nazionale Universitaria</repository>
                        <idno>N III 19</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <divGen type="toc"/>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                    <note target="#t1" type="biblio" resp="#LZM">1] Also transcribed by Holtus (2001), pp. 48-50, lines 1-109; Pasinus, 1-10; Peyron 1-16; Graf (1878) 1-72.</note>
                    <note target="#t4" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">4] Rajna here places a description of the miniature: Min. 1. un re (tutto army) e parecchie altre figure; non intendo bene l'imagin/ Yug. dirige un psonag/ porge un breve/ ad un altro ch 'è/ inginocchiato/ forse l'invito d'uon a corte </note>
                    <note target="#t5" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">5] Numbers in Rajna's notebook are in pencil, added later.</note>
                    <note target="#t7" type="codic" resp="#LZM">7] Rajna: 2r. The manuscript began on a recto when he saw it, with 6 lines: 4 followed by a miniature, with two more following it. Here is the beginning of today's MS.</note>
                    <note target="#t10" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">10] In Rajna's transcription, "y." somewhat after "el" above the line.</note>
                    <note target="#t22" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">22] Rajna notes "sic" after <hi rend="italic">vevole</hi>.</note>
                    <note target="#t23" type="edit" resp="#LZM">23] Holtus: los. "y" crossed out; Rajna: "caratt. più picc / forte aggiunte fatte / poi –i =" (marginal note).</note>
                    <note target="#t45" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 45] Rajna, note in right margin (sic). B: <hi rend="italic">Anchois le haete la giant d[e] la [con]trie.</hi> T seems to be missing the verb, "odia"; an emeded reading might be <hi rend="italic">anzo li (odi)a la zente de la contrà.</hi></note>
                    <note target="#t63" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 63] Rajna note: "prima soa e così / parrebbe ancora / non credo si [tr?] /volz corregg".</note>
                    <note target="#t66" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 66] Rajna reverses these two lines, and uses numbering in the left margin to make clear their order.</note>
                    <note target="#t76" type="ling" resp="#LZM"> 76] Cf. Crusca, <hi rend="italic"> al dilungo</hi>, vol. 1. </note>
                    <note target="#t93" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 93] Rajna, note "no del solito inchiostro / più nero delle giunte." At the beginning of his transcription, Rajna comments more on the various details of handwriting than toward the end.</note>
                    <note target="#t102" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: seneschalcho, with the first "e" changed into "i" with a dot above and filled in. </note>
                    <note target="#t109" type="biblio" resp="#LZM"> End of Holtus (2001) transcription.</note>
                    <note target="#t110" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna's notebook has "V" in the left margin, together with a crossed-out label, "IV."</note>
                    <note target="#t120" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna omits this line and later inserts in the right margin, thus beginning the line numbers of his transcription being off from the total. </note>
                    <note target="#t123" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: messy note here, running over beginning of the following line: "O e in? / (non) mi pare" after having crossed out "Em?"; the "non" is written after, squeezed in; he clearly was not sure. The "E" covers the beginning of "Charlo" below.</note>
                    <note target="#t124" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">This line omitted in Rajna initially, inserted in right margin according to signal similar to "F." MS: ācorte, at the beginning of the line.</note>
                    <note target="#t125" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">prendea</hi>: the "e" is not clearly formed, missing the loop. However, here as elsewhere, if there is not a dot for the "i" I presume that it is an "e": thanks to M. Scattolini for this tip. In the right margin, Rajna has added a note, "I vari aggiunti nei margini sono stati saltati nella trascrizione frettolosa." Perhaps this explains the problem with this line: the king should have taken him by the hand, "prenduto" or something similar, and instead there are two verbs, "avè" and "prendea."</note>
                    <!--line 125 needs a second type, "Rajna", since his comment reveals a problem with the original MS -->
                    <note target="#t194" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">Rajna: zos, with a mark in the margin; note on left side, referring to that mark: "qui un (a) lett. cancellz/ e sopra scritto un e, a.i./ Si dice legittima, legg. zosa." He has an "a" crossed out in the right margin.</note>
                    <note target="#t196" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> MS: baldovĩo; Rajna: baldovij, with a note in the left margin, "corr. in baldovĩo a.i." </note>
                    <note target="#t199" type="ling" resp="#LZM"> It is difficult to make sense of this line; I'm interpreting "each of them knocked his own down thoroughly," which requires understanding "le sovo" for MS: le sono (the parenthesis are for the emendation). However "n" and "v" are frequently difficult to distinguish; cf. Holtus 1985, p. XXXV. </note>
                    <!-- needs second classification here too, codicological-->
                    <note target="#t206" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna initially misses this line and inserts it afterward in the margin. </note>
                    <note target="#t219" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> There are a couple of ways that this could be interpreted: first, "le roi... / armé, et avec toutes ses armes décorées d'une fleur de lys"; or, "[the king] is armed in weapons all decorated with a fleur-de-lys"; that is, the second word of the line could be a verb or the conjunction.</note>
                    <note target="#t221" type="ling" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">elziso</hi>: this form seems to be from <hi rend="italic">alzire/elzire</hi>; cf. <hi rend="italic">Aquilon de Bavière</hi>, "to kill"; the line then means, "that is, Huon, who wouldn't have killed him [Berardo] at all." Compare to B, where the verb is "to hate."</note>
                    <note target="#t240" type="ling" resp="#LZM">This line does not make sense, since the copyist didn't understand the type of horse, "amoravis" and changed the term to something he knew! Compare with B. </note>
                    <note target="#t243" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna's copy shows a spot above "quelo," but it does not seem to be a dot to an "i" merely an imperfection in the paper. </note>
                    <note target="#t246" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Illumination follows: Rajna, "2 giostra." In fact there is a view of one horsed man from the front, with a crown on his head and a sun on his chest in the center of the page; behind, to the right, there is a side view of a figure in grey on horseback with his lance at the attack position, with the same sun motif on the horse's caparison and a cape visible on his back. </note>
                    <note target="#t263" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna initially omits this line and adds it in the margin afterwards. </note>
                    <note target="#t302" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> B: selong lor coi[n]tenance. Nowhere else in this MS does any such form "sealonga" appear. </note>
                    <note target="#t306" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna initially skips this line and adds it later in the left margin. </note>
                    <note target="#t313" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna note: "li lom o loim, non /loin; ma / il segno sopra non / è un i troppo/ legittimo, ma rro/ poi (mi pare) un segno / p l'asta sotta / posta – se è / fu mal fatto."</note>
                    <note target="#t330" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna, note in margin: (sir, voglio) </note>
                    <note target="#t356" type="ling" resp="#LZM"> "a dove a dove"= <hi rend="italic">a due a due</hi>; cf. "sove" = <hi rend="italic">sue</hi></note>
                    <note target="#t363" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> This line and the following are initially incorrectly ordered in Rajna, who then writes numbers in the left margin to indicate the correct order. </note>
                    <note target="#t380" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">sorprisse</hi>: there is a dot above the second "r," not above the following vowel.</note>
                    <note target="#t413" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna notes that he is not sure whether the MS reads "in" or "m." The strokes are linked. </note>
                    <note target="#t417" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Illumination: two men under tree, one with horns and bells, the other with hat over his eyes. </note>
                    <note target="#t418" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> The MS has been scratched: ve:y is what the MS looks like. B: Quant vos forma (l. 421) </note>
                    <note target="#t436" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna has a mark after "chy" and before "ßve" that is unclear; it looks like a little caret. Perhaps this should read "ss[er]ve"? </note>
                    <note target="#t438" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna omits the "o" of "yo." </note>
                    <note target="#t440" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> There seems to be a line missing here; cf. B 444: Non ai ge soingn fors tout soul de celli (between this line and the following).</note>
                    <note target="#t443" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna omits the "u" of "nuy." These two omissions make one wonder about the "y" in line 444—should it be "yo"? </note>
                    <note target="#t458" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: chre da more in B reads <hi rend="italic">qui n'iert d'amore</hi> </note>
                    <note target="#t459" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna transcribes in reverse order this and the following line; he numbers in left margin to indicate the need to reorder. </note>
                    <note target="#t463" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: ne piga. He underlines the word and has a line under the "p"; would seem to have been uncertain himself of the reading. B: emplie. </note>
                    <note target="#t476" type="biblio" resp="#LZM"> Cf. Dante and the pilgrim's expressions of shame: e.g., Inf. 17.85-90.</note>
                    <note target="#t478" type="ling" resp="#LZM"> For "se tene y[n]tra ello" B: si tient traïe </note>
                    <note target="#t484" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> After the second "pensery," Rajna notes (sic). </note>
                    <note target="#t485" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: <hi rend="italic">anyda parla</hi> </note>
                    <note target="#t514" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna initially omits this line, then inserts it in the left margin.</note>
                    <note target="#t520" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna has a number of marks above this line that appear to be abbreviations: "razŷ...tōrmenta."</note>
                    <note target="#t525" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna initially omits this line, then inserts it in the left margin. </note>
                    <note target="#t544" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> B 549: Ja estes sire, et tot a vos atent </note>
                    <note target="#t569" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> The second half of this line is problematic; the hemistich reads in B: "Oïl, mon bon segnor." </note>
                    <note target="#t623" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">savye</hi>: where the ink is worn, it is frequently difficult to see the tail below the line; this could well read savie. However, under the light the tail can be seen. Here the tail is only visible with the ultraviolet light. </note>
                    <note target="#t624" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna reverses this line and the following, noting the correct order in the left margin. </note>
                    <note target="#t652" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna reads "guer" but the MS clearly reads <hi rend="italic">a sapiate</hi> just at the edge of the burned portion. </note>
                    <note target="#t669" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna reads "guer" but the MS clearly reads a sapiate just at the edge of the burned portion.</note>
                    <note target="#t670" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Illumination follows (Rajna: "4 Fig (Carlo e Sandino)</note>
                    <note target="#t680" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">Rajna, marginal note: "e dei corr. Sng."; this last must be an abbreviation.</note>
                    <note target="#t686" type="interp" resp="#JCV">"Si non, défiez le..." (Literally, "Cela si il se trouve [si il est] que non)" </note>
                    <note target="#t714" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna omits initially and then inserts in the left margin. </note>
                    <note target="#t729" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna reverses this line and the following, and indicates the correct order by numbering in the left margin.</note>
                    <note target="#t750" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">End of the first fascicle of Rajna's notebook. Second begins with next line, "Tor. 2." in upper corner, with "13" in red underneath. From here on, there are only numbers in red in the upper right corner of each opening, not sequential numbers as in the first fascicle.</note>
                    <note target="#t758" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> viva: these last four letters are distinctly different from the other strokes around them. They are smaller, and written above the bottom line of the rest of the verse. Added afterwards, with a different pen? Perhaps originally the end read "li à"? </note>
                    <note target="#t762" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Before "aƣpir" there is a little stroke above the line. However, since there is no caret or other mark to indicate insertion, I do not include it in the text. Rajna: apreso; MS clear has "apresso." </note>
                    <!-- The preceding line needs a second label, Rajna -->
                    <note target="#t786" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Illumination follows this line. Huon is kneeling before a double-crowned figure on a what seems to be a tiled floor (alternating dark and light), looking at a book that figure is holding open. Other figures are visible to the right, and one stands on the side of Huon, a little to our left  looking at a book. Rajna leaves a bit of a blank but does not summarize the illumination as he does for later folios.</note>
                    <note target="#t799" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> See B 804-805: "Sens, abstin<hi rend="italic">an</hi>ce, proece, tot ingual / In vos habite <hi rend="italic">et</hi> ont pris son hostal." The Turin version is missing a line, "Intelligence, abstinence, ability, all equally..." or something similar, before this line. </note>
                    <note target="#t809" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">Rajna reverses this and the next line, and numbers in the left margin to indicate the correct order. </note>
                    <note target="#t813" type="codic" resp="#LZM">pi(ù): blot on page at this point: cannot read the letter underneath</note>
                    <note target="#t820" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">Scattolini notes that vv. 820-821 are reversed in order in comparison with B, creating difficulties in meaning.</note>
                    <note target="#t823" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna notes "altro inch[iostro]/.d. /e mano"; the remaining MS text does not show notable differences, so he must be referring to the initial. The reference for the ".d." is unclear.</note>
                    <note target="#t825" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">Rajna initially omits this line, then inserts it in the left margin. </note>
                    <note target="#t844" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> The capital is like a "G" in capital form in Rajna. </note>
                    <note target="#t854" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">Rajna has a large ink blot at the beginning of (his) 845-46 that blocks part of the reading, and at the end of his 846, has some difficulties: unclear if "fassemo" and then corrects to "demora" (the "o" has been changed and reinforced). </note>
                    <note target="#t856" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: "t(r) a" crossed out after zuro </note>
                    <note target="#t863" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Before <hi rend="italic">che</hi>: crossed out word </note>
                    <note target="#t864" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">ell'era</hi> = "ello era"  </note>
                    <note target="#t913" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna omits this line initially and inserts it later in the right margin. </note>
                    <note target="#t942" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Illumination follows this line. Much of the color is gone: to the far right a ruler under a baldicchino throne wearing a hat with two levels (the upper recessed in relation to the lower) sits while a male figure in parti-colored tights to the viewer's left with his back to the reader holds something in his arms; another figure further to the reader's left is partially visible. </note>
                    <note target="#t964" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: piuue? piude? piuie?  B: cu[n] estre puisent plu. The final strokes of Rajna's handwritten copy are not clear. </note>
                    <note target="#t973" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: fustue? </note>
                    <note target="#t982" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Illumination follows. Rajna: "Figura. "La e più bella d'ussai fin qui trovata è doppia con una sola scena / a destra il palazzo con due torri, dall'usero si vede nel portony Ugo/ benedire le vivande della tavola a cui siede il pilgri_ a sinistra/ si vede in alto un diavolo che vola colla tavola, e sotto fuori dall'uscio/ Ugo e altri che guardon su con atti di meraviglia _ una donna sta / meraviglij o piuttosto atterita a una finestra _ c'è espressione </note>
                    <note target="#t992" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna seems to have "lafu" crossed out before the final "lafu," whether correcting his own error or one of the MS is unclear. </note>
                    <note target="#t1040" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: <hi rend="italic">per</hi> has a dot above the "r" but this appears to be an imperfection of the paper. </note>
                    <note target="#t1053" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Here Graf transcribes 5 lines. Rajna: "lo @te" crossed out after "Quando." </note>
                    <!-- The preceding line needs a second label, Interp -->
                    <note target="#t1062" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> MS: grand; Rajna: grand; there is a final something below the line: "o"? B: <hi rend="italic">brand da galons</hi>, which makes much more sense.</note>
                    <!-- The preceding line needs a second label, Interp -->
                    <note target="#t1083" type="interp" resp="#JCV">  Nil temere uxori de servis crede querenti :/ Semper enim mulier quem coniux diligit odit./ <hi rend="italic">Catonis Disticha</hi>, I, 8 (Éd. E. Baehrens, <hi rend="italic">Poetae latini minores</hi>, III, Leipzig, Teubner, 1881). / « Ne crois pas à la légère une épouse qui se plaint de tes esclaves, car une femme déteste toujours celui que son mari apprécie ». </note>
                    <note target="#t1084" type="codic" resp="#LZM">After "lasa", scratched out "le". </note>
                    <note target="#t1086" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: cħ (in the margin) ᵱocho (chy) non li feze; Rajna note: "scritt. orig/ tutto correz." B: <hi rend="italic">A pués qu'il non li a feit.</hi> My emendation for sense. </note>
                    <note target="#t1088" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: si, "s" written over "l." </note>
                    <note target="#t1103" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: <hi rend="italic">aldare</hi>. The second letter is an odd combination, a long stroke with a small cross at the "t" level that curves slightly to the right, but not enough to be an "s"; there is not a separated dot so Rajna's "i" does not seem likely. </note>
                    <note target="#t1124" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Illumination follows: Ugon standing by box? bed? with black figure flat. (Rajna: "Ug s'arma al letto della moglie addormenty.") </note>
                    <!-- The preceding line needs a second label, Rajna -->
                    <note target="#t1135" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">cobia</hi> = "commiato"; cf. B, congieç. </note>
                    <note target="#t1152" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">Rajna: choro. MS reading is clear, however, there is no "h". </note>
                    <note target="#t1162" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> Graf transcribes five lines beginning here. </note>
                    <note target="#t1169" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> Graf, p. 103.</note>
                    <note target="#t1171" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> Graf: m[i]o, emendation. </note>
                    <note target="#t1181" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> Graf omits ll. 1185-1187; Rajna includes them.</note>
                    <!-- The preceding line needs a second label, Rajna -->
                    <note target="#t1185" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna omits this line initially, then inserts in the right margin.</note>
                    <note target="#t1236" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna note, "corr. da smary; st. / mano" = stesso mano (same hand).</note>
                    <note target="#t1242" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna note, "corr./ da schiary/ st. mano" = stesso mano (same hand). </note>
                    <note target="#t1245" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna note, "corr. da desparty/ st. mano" = stesso mano (same hand). </note>
                    <note target="#t1249" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">Rajna note, "corr. da monte / st. m." The structure here is not totally clear: since the third person plural is rare, should this be "montò-ne" for something like "mounted on them," or is it indeed third person plural?</note>
                    <!-- The preceding line needs a second label, interp -->
                    <note target="#t1264" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Illumination follows: an encircled area (paddock?) and a house with what seems to be a straw roof; a stands man in the entry and the head and neck of the horse in front of him (to the reader's right) with an armed man riding it, just visible before the burned section. Rajna: "U arriva alla casa del borghese". </note>
                    <!-- The preceding line needs a second label, Rajna -->
                    <note target="#t1267" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: giesie. </note>
                    <note target="#t1272" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna initially omits this line and adds it afterward in the left margin. </note>
                    <note target="#t1274" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> Apostolo: the Pope. Cf. B and other Franco-Italian Apostoille.  </note>
                    <note target="#t1276" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> The rest of the folio is blank. There is part of the catchword at the bottom of the page, "denan". Rajna also notes the space: "nuovo quad: iniz più grande tracij?/ in lapis" </note>
                    <note target="#t1283" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna seems to have been having difficulties with his pen / ink here; he has a large "D" here at the beginning of this line; or perhaps he is seeking to show the larger "D" as mentioned in his note. </note>
                    <note target="#t1286" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: ī ? There is no dot on the the letter, so I have transcribed as an "e" though there is no circle around either. Illumination follows: Huon on his knees before the Pope in a very elaborate room with a coffered ceiling. Rajna, "Ug (piviro) ai piedi di un papa gig. Le iniz. sequit a ess transcritte in qto quaderno e manteng spesso la st. grandezza /le segnorò maiuscole." </note>
                    <!-- The preceding line needs a second label, interp -->
                    <note target="#t1289" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> Graf transcribes 11 lines from here. Note that here the new folio in B (F 10) coincides with Turin's new folio. </note>
                    <note target="#t1291" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna notes, "copto / da una / carta / infra..y". Nothing is now visible before line 1297. </note>
                    <note target="#t1296" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> B: nue home si bien non. </note>
                    <note target="#t1300" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> The trascriber had not understood here: it's an impossible thing, not not impossible! </note>
                    <note target="#t1308" type="interp" resp="#LZM">MS: dezo nona ho; Rajna: dezo nona homo; B: qu'il non se feit adon, "that this not be done now." </note>
                    <note target="#t1310" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: homo with the "h" crossed through. </note>
                    <note target="#t1312" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna initially omits this line and inserts later in the left margin.  </note>
                    <note target="#t1314" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> The end of Rajna's line in undeciphrable here; however, since "sabione" appears four times and there are no other expressions beginning with "sab" this seems most logical.</note>
                    <note target="#t1341" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> MS: space between "crosse" and "che": word scraped out? Nothing visible. </note>
                    <note target="#t1343" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: corr. da sigre? </note>
                    <note target="#t1345" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 1345] Rajna initially omits and then inserts in left margin. </note>
                    <note target="#t4195" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4195] MS: <seg>nī</seg></note>
                    <note target="#t4207" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4197 MS: <hi rend="italic">dne et ȳ</hi> with a line drawn through "et y".</note>               
                    <note target="#t4213" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4213] Rajna: the final word is unclear; the two vowels are clearly <hi rend="italic">o</hi>, but the third consonant in particular is difficult to discern, perhaps -r-? Since the equivalent B line ends in <hi rend="italic">sono</hi>, I have extrapolated here.</note>
                    <note target="#t4218" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4218] For initial "M", see v. Rajna 4145, "Memento", here v. 4529. </note>
                    <note target="#t4228" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> 4228] legione; cf.  B4270: region.</note>
                <note target="#t4236" type="codic" resp="#LZM">4326] MS: <hi rend="italic">pre</hi>demo </note>
                <note target="#t4247" type="codic" resp="#LZM">4247] MS, Rajna: lirerespond e possibly a distraction by the following line, emended?  </note>
                <note target="#t4251" type="codic" resp="#LZM">4251] MS: /re/ </note>
                <note target="#t4254" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4254] B: po<hi rend="italic">r</hi> la soe lés; there is a reference to God's law. Here, however, it would seem that "la soa" refers to the faith and the syntax is reconstrued.</note>
                <note target="#t4270" type="inter" resp="#LZM">4270] MS: <hi rend="ital">de avite tanto de podere</hi>; B: Qui ot ce fait, qui ot tant deponés</note>
                <note target="#t4284" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4284] vostra: Rajna, "e corr. da a, / se non erro". It is difficult to tell which letter is intended here.</note>
                <note target="#t4301" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">4301] Rajna: repenteate ? the antepenultimate letter difficult to distinguish. “repente<ex rend="angle">n</ex>te,” ‘repenting’ would make little sense here.</note>
                <note target="#t4306" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4306] Rajna writes (sic) in the margin after this line and also in the following after <hi rend="italic">poy</hi>.</note>            
                <note target="#t4307" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4307] Rajna: poy (sic)</note>
                <note target="#t4322" type="edit" resp="#LZM"> 4322] MS: no verb; B: Le mercheant dit</note>
                <note target="#t4324" type="inter" resp="#LZM"> 4324]  MS: S'ele el fato; Rajna: Sele elfato (he underlines where there is a problem with a section). Cf. B 4367: Si il ne·l feit, por autruy ne·l spereç [If he doesn’t do it, don’t hope for it from anyone else]</note>
                <note target="#t4328" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4328] Rajna marks this line with a cross in the right margin.</note>
                <note target="#t4329" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4329] Rajna: "e fuori" written in margin before his "4310" label.</note>
                <note target="#t4334" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> 4334] biava: MSI ‘biada’, perhaps because of intervocalic lenition and the difficulty of representing đ.</note>
                <note target="#t4339" type="edit" resp="#LZM"> 4339] The following line in B, 4384, reads: Vegant la grant manentie qu’ot aseç [Because of their rich cargo, of which they had so much]</note>
                <note target="#t4343" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> 4343] canta: Difficult to explain for the sense. Perhaps related to "incantare", to auction? Various figurative meanings are also attested; GDLI Vol. II, "9. Attestare, far fede [...] avere significato evidente"(p. 651); "17. Figur. Dire con forza, esprimere in modo chiaro ed energico; proclamare apertamente, con decisione, affermare in modo risoluto"(p. 652).</note>
                <note target="#t4351" type="lex" resp="#LZM"> 4351] disviluppare: sciogliere, slegare, snodare, dipanare; districare (GDLI vol IV, p. 841, col. 1).</note>
                <note target="#t4355" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4355]The initial letter of this line is peculiar, not the normal initial "m"- though three forms of maie appear (ll. 510, 512, 10073) here it seems rather to be an n.</note>
                <note target="#t4359" type="inter" resp="#LZM"> 4359] Cf. B 4405: Tot deust estre riche qi en cestuy reg(n)[e] sta </note>
                <note target="#t4360" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4360] MS: fano with a second "fano" crossed out after it</note>
                <note target="#t4369" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4369] Meregazzi: arivà, and all finals in this laisse -à. Meregazzi’s “Episodio” begins here, p. 13, and continues on odd-numbered pages in her article.</note>
                <note target="#t4378" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4378] MS: el vede chel cantar (with "chel" crossed out); Meregazzi: vedi…de là; note: correction of <hi rend="italic">vede</hi> in <hi rend="italic">vedi</hi></note>
                <note target="#t4379" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4379] MS: et re y. (rest of the line  is gone); Rajna: re underlined; in the left margin, “corr. da .y”</note>
                <note target="#t4384" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4384]  Meregazzi: lesà</note>
                <note target="#t4387" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4387] Meregazzi: d’entorno</note>
                <note target="#t4390" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4390] MS: ac; Rajna: acor; blank space below. Rajna also writes, "Spazio". Meregazzi: vescove… areceveschove ... a cor</note>
                <note target="#t4391" type="edit" resp="#LZM"> 4391] Meregazzi: chi </note>
                <note target="#t4397" type="edit" resp="#LZM"> 4397] Meregazzi: dareto</note>
                <note target="#t4398" type="trans" resp="#LZM">4398] Meregazzi: me voy che site</note>
                <note target="#t4401" type="trans" resp="#LZM">4401] Meregazzi: signore</note>
                <note target="#t4405" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4405] The abbreviation line for the "n" is of y[n] is missing. Meregazzi: Me… yn</note>
                <note target="#t4407" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4407] andocha = B adon; I’m understanding it as “adoncha,”  like OF “adonc,” ‘alors’; Meregazzi: ando[n]cha</note>
                <note target="#t4409" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4409] Meregazzi: yn doso</note>
                <note target="#t4418" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4418] Meregazzi: quisti</note>
                <note target="#t4420" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4420] MS, Rajna: responde; Meregazzi: (?) at the end of the line. B 4467: Le prest d’arme de Deu despoille et repon [The priest took off and put away God’s vestments]; “arme,” ‘arms’, understood as vestments.</note>
                <note target="#t4423" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4423] Meregazzi: tidesco</note>
                <note target="#t4425" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4425] MS, Rajna: andate antrare; Meregazzi: andate (entrare), dize (with a question mark at the end of the line); B 4472: A le autre dit, qe en la glisse son: / “Isseç dehors; cist veut confesion.”  [ He said to the others who were in the church, / “Go outside; this man wants to make confession”]</note>
                <note target="#t4426" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4426] Meregazzi: vuol</note>
                <note target="#t4428" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4428] Meregazzi: intende</note>
                <note target="#t4431" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4431] Meregazzi: Ve conseiaremo</note>
                <note target="#t4432" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4432] Meregazzi: A lagremare ed a plurare</note>
                <note target="#t4437" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4437] No indent or any sign of new laisse in MS.</note>
                <note target="#t4438" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4438] Meregazzi: in zorno</note>
                <note target="#t4439" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4439] Meregazzi: pechador non</note>
                <note target="#t4441" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4441] Meregazzi: de per tanto</note>
                <note target="#t4444" type="edit" resp="#LZM"> 4444] Rajna: ata solvo, with "ata" in the left margin by the line number count.</note>
                <note target="#t4445" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4445] Meregazzi: segnà</note>
                <note target="#t4447" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4447] Meregazzi: e com</note>
                <note target="#t4448" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4448] Meregazzi: Meregazzi: dilo… dime (no further comments on her usage of writing together object pronouns with imperatives)</note>
                <note target="#t4449" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4449] Meregazzi: MS: liquesta. "l'i[n]questa" may have been intended and would be a possible emendation; Meregazzi: l’inquesta</note>
                <note target="#t4450" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4450] Meregazzi: sen vene, as always </note>
                <note target="#t4453" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4453] Rajna: che lolde</note>
                <note target="#t4454" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4454] Meregazzi: vivent</note>
                <note target="#t4462" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4462] Alternate interpretation: dize, “el to afare… </note>
                <note target="#t4467" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4467] MS: e scratched out before danata, where sera is written above the line. Rajna: si è raschiato e (for "danata")</note>
                <note target="#t4468" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4468] Meregazzi: se tristo </note>
                <note target="#t4472" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4472] Rajna has difficulty with this line; in the right margin, he notes "uman non viv*"(?); Meregazzi: […] ch’el non vite omo vivan, with a note “ms. vive… vivan per vite… vivan”;  Cf. B 5420: Tiel çonse voy en vos qe non vi en hom human [I see such things in you that I have never seen in any earthly man]; The verb in the second hemistich seems to be a frequentative, formed on the past participle, so a unique form of “to see”. </note>
                <note target="#t4474" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4474] Rajna: (croce camelly?), in the margin. There is also a mark, | |</note>
                <note target="#t4478" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4478] Meregazzi: lazate</note>
                <note target="#t4479" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4479] Note Rajna's error in numbering.</note>
                <note target="#t4480" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4480] Note the error in sense: a non has been added somewhere along the line, to make the line say the opposite of what was intended in B, saying, "This isn't impossible" which makes no sense unless it refers to God’s assistance in the task. Cf. B, "Ce ert inposible dou tot a hom te[r]ran" (line 4528).</note>
                <note target="#t4482" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4482] Meregazzi: dize; she emends from MS dizo</note>
                <note target="#t4485" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4485] MS: prendrite followed by a crossed out l before the “un,” it appears. The page is torn closely here. </note>
                <note target="#t4487" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4487] Rajna: in the upper left hand corner of this page (his 69V, left of 70 in the microfilm) seems to be written "Nulla / ho omesso"; Meregazzi: poco</note>
                <note target="#t4489" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4489] Meregazzi: vede grande. B 4536: Part n’ay veue, greignor non vi vorman [Part of which I’ve seen, I’ve truly never seen greater]</note>
                <note target="#t4493" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4493] Meregazzi: li più</note>
                <note target="#t4495" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4495] Meregazzi: feramente</note>
                <note target="#t4496" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4496] Meregazzi: za; she only uses the accent for the equivalent of “già”; see also below, 4503, etc.</note>
                <note target="#t4497" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4497] Meregazzi: qui</note>
                <note target="#t4499" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4499] MS: vetuuoso has a line through the second stroke of the “v”; Meregazzi: ell’è de … fede (el è) veretuuoso; B 4547: Hom est de foy et tot le vertuç ha [He’s a man of faith and has all the virtues]. Here the second hemistich is interpreted as “in everything he is virtuous, and he remains so [i.e., virtuous].”</note>                  
                <note target="#t4500" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4500] mante = mante[n]</note>
                <note target="#t4501" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4501] Meregazzi: ynzenochià, as usual for final verbal -a endings in rhyme; cf. 4502, 4505, 4507, 4508, 4509, 4510, 4511, 4512, 4513, 4514, 4515, 4518, 4521,4522, 4523.</note>
                <note target="#t4504" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4504] Meregazzi: a my</note>
                <note target="#t4506" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4506] Cf. B, n'atent tant già (l. 4554)[it’s not fitting]. Meregazzi : non sa per tenereza </note>
                <note target="#t4507" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4507] Meregazzi: per tanto</note>
                <note target="#t4508" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4508] Meregazzi: porteno </note>
                <note target="#t4510" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4510] Meregazzi: in su </note>
                <note target="#t4511" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4511] MS: te deum al with the “l” crossed out. </note>
                <note target="#t4513" type="trans" resp="#LZM">  4513] Meregazzi: me (as always for MSI ma, MSF mais); cf. 4519</note>
                <note target="#t4515" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4515] B: Qua[n]t l'eve fu cornée, chascun si soy lava (l. 4563); Meregazzi : Quando (levo) era …</note>
                <note target="#t4516" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4516] The initial two letters of this line are in the left margin.</note>
                <note target="#t4521" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4521] Meregazzi: a fora</note>
                <note target="#t4525" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4525] Between presto and sevole, crossed out letter y. Not noted by Rajna. Meregazzi: de là.</note>
                <note target="#t4526" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4526] Meregazzi: lielamente</note>
                <note target="#t4529" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4529] MS: despone laventura despone; Meregazzi: (despone) l’aventure; Rajna to right (si è). B 4578: Puis a lor bernage l’aventure despons [Then he recounted Huon’s undertaking to his assembled barons]</note>
                <note target="#t4534" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4534]  For this line and the following, Rajna has switched the second hemistiches; he circles them and indicates with arrows that they are to be switched, writing "errore mio" beside the lines.  </note>
                <note target="#t4539" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4539] Meregazzi: quy </note>
                <note target="#t4541" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4541] Meregazzi: pó </note>
                <note target="#t4544" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4544] MS: yano dito; Rajna: Yano dito; Meregazzi: i ano </note>
                <note target="#t4546" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4546] Meregazzi: questo faroy </note>
                <note target="#t4547" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4547] Cf. B 4598: Et il, a tant, le paroil leise a pont [And he, meanwhile, ceased speaking at that point] </note>
                <note target="#t4549" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4549] molte: the spot was scraped and the word written over it; the ink is slightly smeared. Rajna note in right margin: corr. si. che? (for "romanire molte") </note>
                <note target="#t4560" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> Cf. B 4611: Aseç gi ot princeps, duch et contor [There was a fair number of princes, dukes and counts]</note>
                <note target="#t4563" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4563] B 4614: Oit .vii.c. mille jusquemant en la Sor [He had seven hundred thousand [men] as far as Syria]</note>
                <note target="#t4564" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4564] 4564] This line is in the right margin of the MS; it is not clear how it relates. Should it be only the end of one line? But cf. B 4615, quite long: Zascun ert a son mestier quant ert en ceste cor […]. B 4614-4618 are equivalent to lines 4563-66 here, but in a slightly different order. I follow Rajna in placing it on its own line. He notes, "in marg; è verso incompiuto; il richia/mo è dopo conte." </note>
                <note target="#t4565" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4565] MS (Rajna): parlate</note>
                <note target="#t4566" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4566] Meregazzi: qui</note>
                <note target="#t4567" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4567] Rajna: a no mé; Meregazzi: l’uno a nome haine; B 4619: "Le un n'ait hayne a l'autre, ainç s'aime p[er] amor"; the scribe here seems to have transposed letters in the initial hemistich.</note>
                <note target="#t4568" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4568] Rajna underlines the final vowel of "Tuti" and of servene; in a note at the end of the line "da legg o?"</note>
                <note target="#t4571" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4571] Meregazzi: et a plurare</note>
                <note target="#t4572" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4572] Meregazzi: yn versso</note>
                <note target="#t4577" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4577] Rajna: nel nel,with note in the right margin, (gi???)</note>
                <note target="#t4580" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4580] Rajna, note in right margin: (qui è forse lecito / legg o) in reference to the first vowel in lo teneno. It is difficult to tell, since the form is compressed, whether it is e or o. </note>
                <note target="#t4582" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4582] Meregazzi: ym plurando</note>
                <note target="#t4583" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4583] MS: e soa nave Tadeus; Meregazzi: donata</note>
                <note target="#t4584" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4584] MS: bono nave; Rajna, note in left margin: "corr. da bona nave" with "bon nevo" underlined. The vowels are altered: the final of "bon" is scraped off, with just a bit of ink visible; the other two are oddly formed, and the final letter is followed by a stroke that is not scraped off, leaving the intention unclear though the cross-stroke for the "e" is clear. MS: avuy, with the “v” written above the line.</note>
                <note target="#t4585" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4585] Meregazzi: e tuto</note>
                <note target="#t4586" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4586] Rajna transcribes this line and the following out of order, and numbers them in the left margin to indicate correct order. He does not note the abbreviation on "comada" that is clearly visible in the MS; he does note (in marg) at the end of the line beginning fately. Since the inserted line, written over two lines, is in the left margin, on the verso, the left side is burned, and only two bits (the ends of each half line) remain.</note>
                <note target="#t4588" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 4588] a Dio: perhaps “adio”? I follow previous Rajna and Meregazzi with their division, though it is written as together in the MS.</note>
                <note target="#t4589" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4589] Meregazzi: a topianando</note>
                <note target="#t4590" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4590] Meregazzi: à zò che… fina VII</note>
                <note target="#t4592" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4592] Meregazzi: a zò che</note>
                <note target="#t4593" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4593] Meregazzi: vivente</note>
                <note target="#t4594" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4594] Meregazzi: a tanto</note>
                <note target="#t4595" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4595] Meregazzi: ym presente</note>
                <note target="#t4599" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4599] Meregazzi: ym presente</note>
                <note target="#t4600" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4600] MS: bescota? The final vowel has a thick outside stroke.</note>
                <note target="#t4601" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4601] Rajna: corr.; da che?</note>
                <note target="#t4603" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4601] MS: fono (s/f confusion is a frequent scribal error)</note>
                <note target="#t4604" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 4604] B 4655: Tot le livrast s’il fust son plaquimant [They would deliver it all if it were his pleasure]. Perhaps a missing abbreviation for ‘r’?</note>
                <note target="#t4608" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 4608] Meregazzi: davanti</note>
                <note target="#t4613" type="edit" resp="#LZM"> 4613] End of the first section of Meregazzi’s transcription, p. 31 (her line 4494).</note>
                <note target="#t4617" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 4617] Rajna: lunta = "ontano"</note>
                
                <note target="#t5763" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5763] The second section of Meregazzi, "Prete Gianni," begins here, her p. 31.</note>
                <note target="#t5767" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 5767] Rajna: ɔpagnia; Meregazzi: ... dize, "e la ...</note>
                <note target="#t5770" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5770] Meregazzi: yn verso</note>
                <note target="#t5771" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5771] Meregazzi: ynlasaria; there are no other forms with this prefix. It seems to be a combination of “lassare” and “s’en aller”.</note>
                <note target="#t5773" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 5773] Rajna: vustate?  "a" written over "t"? Meregazzi: vusate</note>
                <note target="#t5777" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5777] Meregazzi: non per tanto</note>
                <note target="#t5778" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5778] Meregazzi: diaulo</note>
                <note target="#t5779" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5779] Meregazzi, p. 33. B6084: Se plus vesquisse qe non fist Jeremie [Even if I live as long as Jeremiah]</note>
                <note target="#t5784" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 5784] B 6089: Je vos merci de la grant cortesie [I thank you for the great courtesy]; “mercier” not understood.</note>
                <note target="#t5786" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 5786] Under “chavalo de la” is a scraped section with the current reading written over it.</note>
                <note target="#t5789" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5789] Meregazzi Laisse XIII.</note>
                <note target="#t5790" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5790] Meregazzi: chavalieri</note>
                <note target="#t5793" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5793] Meregazzi: omo</note>
                <note target="#t5795" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5795] Meregazzi: o non g’andò zamai</note>
                <note target="#t5796" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 5796] Rajna: lo ɔte lo ɔte (sic)</note>
                <note target="#t5797" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5797] Meregazzi notes, “corr. vado in omo”- suggesting an emendation?</note>
                <note target="#t5798" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5798] Meregazzi: vui</note>
                <note target="#t5805" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 5805] Rajna: lasassi; Meregazzi: de presio in the right margin, underlined, possibly a comment on the same word appearing at the end of the following line. However, line B 6111-12 also have the same concluding word, “pris”.</note>
                <note target="#t5806" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 5806] Meregazzi, p. 35</note>
                <note target="#t5808" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5808] Meregazzi: pregeroy</note>
                <note target="#t5809" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5809] MS: che y[n] ne landare vuy… .Cf. B 6115: Que ambdos vos gart que non soieç oncis [That they both keep you from being killed]; Meregazzi: che yn ne l’andare [that in the going/on the trip?] It’s not clear though in that construction what the role of the “ne” is; perhaps “ynn el andare”?</note>
                <note target="#t5811" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5811] MS: lo core li presse; Meregazzi: me presse; B 6117: De pieté m’ais tant le cors espris [You have aroused such pity in my heart]; an “l” for an “s” is a possible scribal error.</note>
                <note target="#t5814" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 5814] "che tu ne torni"; Meregazzi: retorny ancor (titulus not resolved)</note>
                <note target="#t5816" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5816] Meregazzi: sì yn sonto</note>
                <note target="#t5820" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5820] Meregazzi: volonterosso</note>
                <note target="#t5822" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5822] MS: auy y rende (final -e written over an -a); Meregazzi: Dio a vuy</note>
                <note target="#t5825" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> 5825] B 6132: Da toy si part li hom avenois [This {Alvernese}man is leaving you]</note>
                <note target="#t5826" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5826] Meregazzi: fradello</note>
                <note target="#t5828" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5828] Meregazzi: chi me lasse</note>
                <note target="#t5831" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 5831] Rajna: marchese</note>
                <note target="#t5834" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 5834] Meregazzi, p. 37</note>
                <note target="#t5835" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5835] Meregazzi: vaxalo… el</note>
                <note target="#t5836" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5836] Meregazzi: sen (as always; see also v. 5838 below)</note>
                <note target="#t4840" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> 5840] B 6147: Onque mes nef n’avoit tiel estormant [Never before had a ship had such a steersman]</note>
                <note target="#t5847" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5847] Meregazzi: ny tanto ny quanto</note>
                <note target="#t5848" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5848] Meregazzi: Il zorno</note>
                <note target="#t5849" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5849] Meregazzi: sempro</note>
                <note target="#t5851" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 5851] MS: tuty ȳ </note>
                <note target="#t5852" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5852] Meregazzi: In poco</note>
                <note target="#t5856" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 5856] Rajna: pasa</note>
                <note target="#t5862" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 5862] MS: vene for "tene"; Rajna: vene</note>
                <note target="#t5863" type="trans" resp="#LZM"> 5863] Meregazzi, p. 39</note>
                <note target="#t5871" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 5871] Rajna: travaiante; MS: travaliante</note>
                
                <note target="#t7462" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> 57462] The biblical account of Noah and his sons was greatly expanded during the middle ages. For a history of the developments, see Benjamin Braude, "The Sons of Noah
                    and the Construction of Ethnic and Geographical Identities in the Medieval and Early Modern Periods," <hi rend="italic">The William and Mary Quarterly,</hi> 3rd series, 54.1 (January 1997), pp. 103-142.</note>
                
                <note target="#t8321" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">8321] Rajna: che cosa? (asay ne vite) hard to read! </note>
                <note target="#t8323" type="codic" resp="#LZM">8323] MS: morbede: written in smaller letters and "d" with a light slash in the ascender; "b" has "p" (?) written above.</note>
                <note target="#t8328" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">8328] Rajna: r in l (molto)</note>
                <note target="#t8329" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">8329] This line and the following are reversed in Rajna's transcription, corrected by his writing "2" and then "1" in the margin. “molto” was changed from “morto”.</note>
                <note target="#t8335" type="codic" resp="#LZM">8335] The descender in  "p" of "parte" does have a line across it, but is not needed here as mark of abbreviation.</note>
                <note target="#t8350" type="codic" resp="#LZM">8350] Illumination follows; Rajna labels it "Ug e le formiche aurifere"; the entire center of the page is predominated by ants marching from left to right up a hill; the front half of Ugon’s horse is visible at the bottom center.  </note>
                <note target="#t8361" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 8361] Rajna: cosse for "coste"</note>
                <note target="#t8365" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 8365] Square brackets in italicized section from Rajna. Note: "in marg. / mutily col /margin." Line inserted in the right margin over two lines, so end of each not visible, as he says, in the margin, mutilated with the margin.</note>
                <note target="#t8367" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 8367] Once again the line that has been inserted (above, 8365) is almost identical to an already present line, this one.</note>
              
                <note target="#t10892" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 10892] Rajna: agradise. This line and the following in the MS end in a rather rapidly dashed-off letter, but they do seem to  -e.</note>
                <note target="#t10895" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 10895] Rajna seems to write “afadighate” and then correct the “g”</note>
                <note target="#t10896" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 10896] Rajna: line crossed out after luno</note>
                <note target="#t10897" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 10897] Rajna: line crossed out before sa (seems to be an “f”)</note>
                <note target="#t10900" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 10900] MS: zo is in the left margin, before the beginning of other lines. Rajna note: g[iunto]. st[esso]. i[nchiostro]. (for zo)</note>
                <note target="#t10901" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 10901] Rajna: lenguazo</note>
                <note target="#t10908" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 10908] çerte: there is a line here in the MS that seems to be a cedilla. Rajna gives a dash under the line.</note>
                <note target="#t10916" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 10916] The handwriting size changes after this line, becoming much smaller though still the same style.</note>
                <note target="#t10917" type="edit" resp="#LZM"> 10917] MS: [crist]ianeta fede; this is the only time that form appears as an adjective, elsewhere (seven appearances) it is always a noun. For this reason we have emended.</note>
                <note target="#t10919" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 10919] Rajna: fato; MS is not clear: it seems to be an –"o" with a line at the bottom, or perhaps formed in reverse (finishing at the bottom) by the scribe.</note>
                <note target="#t10928" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> 10928] Rajna: altre letre. The MS is burned at this edge here, but it looks like "atre letre," where only part of the first letter is visible. Thus the italics in the text.</note>
                <note target="#t10931" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 10931] Pencil annotation in right margin, "Prete Gianni."</note>
                <note target="#t10937" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 10937] MS: Yerosaleme (crossed-out "e" at the end of the line- slash going through it). Rajna: Ierosaleme. The form of the first letter is like his initials elsewhere, but is difficult to parse, it could be a “G”. The MS is clearly “ Y”.</note>
                <note target="#t10940" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 10940] el gran mal: et el …</note>
                <note target="#t10942" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 10942] Handwriting change at 169v: back to large print. There is a note in the right margin of the manuscript, "nuova.... grafia..."</note>
                                
                <!-- start here -->      
                        <note target="#t11816" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> Rajna: anchora </note>
                        <note target="#t11818" type="biblio" resp="#LZM">Graf, p. 109.</note>
                        <note target="#t11820" type="biblio" resp="#LZM">Graf: recevono; Rajna: benedizione .</note>
                        <note target="#t11831" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Graf: si l'eno? .</note>
                        <note target="#t11832" type="biblio" resp="#LZM">Line not in Graf.</note>
                        <note target="#t11836" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Graf: sauto.</note>
                        <note target="#t11838" type="biblio" resp="#LZM">Various editors cite these final lines, including also Peyron.. </note>
                        <note target="#t11839" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Peyron: oldite.</note>
                        <note target="#t11841" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM">End of Rajna's transcription. The notebook, however, is not ended. It continues through a folio numbered 192. Folio 187 (back and front) is blank. Rajna describes L. I. 14 (Cod. 89) from 188-190; this is a resumé of <hi rend="italic">Octavian</hi>. From folio 190V-192V, he speaks of Cod. xxvj =L. II.14 (?) of parchment sec. XIIIo o XIVo 586 folios in 2 columns, with a listing of contents, including <hi rend="italic">Bovo d'Antona</hi>. </note>
                        
                <!-- <note target="#t123" type="Rajna" resp="#LZM"> ] </note> -->
                        
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
